Good day, everyone.
And um welcome back to the Dante
Workshop. Today we have a very, very
special guest
dialing in from Connecticut, our beloved
Sterling Professor of English, David
Bromwich, live with us today.
Um Besides being the Sterling Professor
of English, um he has been a very
well-read literary and cultural critic.
He was a Yale College grad and a PhD
alum of ours. Um his
one of his uh some of his many books
include Hazlitt, The Mind of a Critic,
Disowned by Memory, Wordsworth's Poetry,
The Intellectual Career of Edmund Burke,
and most recently American Breakdown:
The Trump Years. He has also been a
committee member for the Committee on um
Trust in Higher Education, which just
published its report about a month ago.
Um he still teaches English 125 at Yale
Directed Studies, a course on Moby Dick.
And um we're just so delighted to have
you um contribute to this enlightened
conversation with your student uh Jiang
Xuerchin. And without further ado, I'm
going to turn the podium over to you. I
should also say we're so grateful that
actually, thanks to Jiang's
introduction, we've had um David
Bromwich, Professor Bromwich, join Yale
Center Beijing programs and workshops on
Shakespeare and poetry during COVID,
which um was comfort during difficult
times. Comfort and enlightenment
equally. So, um I'll turn the mic over
to um Professor Bromwich and Joe.
>> Do you want me to just start or um
>> Yeah, just just feel free to start.
Uh
>> Okay.
Uh let let me
um set this up
in a slightly classroom way
and point out that Shakespeare is uh
it
a an irregular, an unwieldy, a sort of
untamed
author in many ways. And this is shown
especially in the way he was received by
neoclassical French critics who held
against him that he wrote plays that
didn't obey the unities, the supposed
all-important
Aristotelian unities of uh
uh action, time, and place. The ideal
play would have an action that took
place in the amount of time it took you
to watch the play. You can see how rare
this is uh as a successful strategy.
Um but Shakespeare was what went astray
of it far more than most
um
successful playwrights. And uh
I chose Macbeth in part because this is
a this is a relatively rare instance
among his works where you do have strong
unity of action. And it's it's welded
together with character, a portrait of
character that is really
um brought out by the nature of the
action, and the moral judgment I think
we're asked to make about the play,
about Macbeth's ambition, goes with a
sequence of actions that have that sort
of interconnection
um that we look for. It is an imitation
of an action that is serious, complete,
and of a certain magnitude.
Uh I'll
try to um
uh
expand that a little or get your
thinking started on it by just reminding
you of the aphorism which we have from
Heraclitus, character is fate. Um the
Greek of it is ethos is the daimon. Both
of those keywords still with us in
English in different ways. And then a
much later um
writer, uh but interesting in the same
way of
bringing our attention to this unity of
character and sequence of events.
Um
Henry James in his essay uh on the art
of fiction asks, "What is character but
the determination of incident?
Incident a coming to a uh a a sharp
emphasis in the form of character. And
what is incident
but the illustration of character?"
I'm
going to concentrate on the idea of
action, of the idea of a deed,
and Shakespeare's sense in dealing with
Macbeth most of all, but also Lady
Macbeth, who is in some sense the
instigator of his violent action, the
murder of Duncan.
Um
by
calling attention to the strange
um
focus Shakespeare pretty much demands
that we give to doing, the very idea of
doing. Uh Lady Macbeth
uh says
soon after they've committed their
murder,
"What's What's is done."
But she'll say much later
uh on the brink of or some way into her
madness,
what's done cannot be undone.
Now,
you can hear the difference
between those two
assertions.
And of course those are often used uh
idiomatically by ordinary speakers in
English today.
Um but they they logically mean exactly
the same thing. What's done is done and
what's done cannot be undone. No
contradiction there. But they're said in
a very different tenor. The person who
says what's done is done
or to use the more modern formulation
which is even more uh seemingly bland,
it is what it is. When somebody says
that to you, they mean
um there's there's no point thinking
further about it. That's just in the
it's in the past now. No no more reason
uh to uh contemplate, to have regrets,
whatever.
But that second statement, what's done
cannot be undone,
points to something fatal about the
nature of a deed, that it is it is a
bearer of fate and it is a bearer of the
fate of the person who has performed the
deed that does a great deal to
illustrate the character um of the agent
himself.
Macbeth
seems to be
nursing the
uh nature of the deed he will perform
almost as soon as the witches plant the
idea that he might become Thane and then
become King in his mind. Um he speaks it
in a way that's uh
a little elaborate and at the same time
rushed as if his mind is overcome by the
merging of the idea of
usurpation, killing, and this prophecy
which places him already as king.
He says, and these are the lines from
the first act, "My thought, whose murder
yet is but fantastical,
shakes so my single state of man that
function is smothered in surmise,
and nothing is
but what is not."
One thing
clear, even though that's an incoherent
statement, and mean think of what it
means to say my thought whose murder yet
is but fantastical, it's as if murder
surrounds his very thought. That's a
kind of conceit, I think, um, that Jang
will probably want to have something to
say about in relation to Dante. The idea
that,
one of those, um,
condemned speaking from a flame in the
Inferno,
um, just is what the deed bounds him as
having been.
And but that's living that already in
his speech, even though he hasn't yet,
to his conscious mind, decided to do
what the witches, uh, prophecy might be
possible. They don't say you're going to
murder Duncan, they say you're going to
be king.
But this this concern, this verbal and
psychological,
uh,
freight of the idea of a deed as
defining the character and fate of a
person
is strongest when he's just on the verge
of committing the murder at the very end
of Act One. It's a great speech, and
I'll, uh,
I'll speak all of it and apologize in
advance for the inadequacy.
Very hard to
to act this part. It almost exists to be
read more than acted. Uh the part of
Macbeth.
Partly because he is
uh
imaginative, because he is
full of fantasy
uh in in a way that
>> [clears throat]
>> a mere warrior wouldn't normally
be relied on to show. He has both
aspects in him. Um but the fact that he
is haunted, the fact that he has a
certain depth does not change the fact
that he's bent on the deed that the
witches have told him
uh all but told him
uh could make his ascent to kingship
possible.
So, here's the speech at the end of the
first
act.
If it were done when 'tis done,
then 'twere well it were done quickly.
If the assassination could trammel up
the consequence and catch with his
surcease success,
that but this blow might be the be-all
and the end-all here, but here upon this
bank and shoal of time, we jump the life
to come.
But
in these cases, we still have judgment
here.
That we but teach bloody instructions,
which being taught return to plague the
inventor.
This even-handed justice commends the
ingredients of our poisoned chalice to
our own lips.
He's here in double trust. That's
Duncan. First, as I'm his kinsman and
his subject, strong both against the
deed. Then,
as his host, who should against his
murderer shut the door, not bear the
knife myself. Besides, this Duncan hath
borne his faculties so meek, hath been
so clear in his great office that his
virtues will plead like angels
trumpet-tongued against the deep
damnation of his taking off, and pity,
like a naked newborn babe striding the
blast, or heaven's cherubim horsed upon
the sightless couriers of the air, shall
blow the horrid deed in every eye that
tears shall drown the wind.
I have no spur to prick the sides of my
intent, but only vaulting ambition,
which o'erleaps itself and falls on the
other.
It's It's quite a remarkable speech, and
I'll stop at a couple points of it,
but only say now that
Lady Macbeth comes in, tries to work him
up to the crime again,
but Macbeth, in a very different vein
from what we've just heard, says to her
flatly, "We will proceed no further in
this business." There he speaks like a
general,
giving a command that is in keeping with
his or normal duties.
But you can see the amount of fantasy
and the and the sense of ambition,
um just in the way the metaphors work
uh in this speech.
He says
that
he'd leap the life to come. In fact, in
the first part of that speech, if you
could trammel up the consequence and
catch with his surcease success. It's
almost as if
the echo of those two words, surcease is
a fancy word. It's a It's a euphemism
for murder.
But if if success and surcease, the way
they almost rhyme, is just the way I
could take him out, how convenient it
would be that but this blow might be the
be-all and the end-all here, right now,
in this place, no consequences.
But then he comes to the idea of
judgment in these cases. And cases is
already a legal term. The our our idea
of casuistry, which is metaphysical and
theological, too, comes from thinking
about cases. In these cases, we still
have judgment here on Earth, right?
>> [clears throat]
>> That we but teach bloody instructions
which being taught return to plague the
inventor.
And this even-handed justice commends
the ingredients of our poison chalice to
our own lips. So,
Macbeth in those words enacts justice
upon himself. There could be no more
direct or complete judgment of the wrong
of what he's doing.
His sense of the wrong is expressed only
in terms of duty, but the duty is strong
and binding.
And he practically breaks down himself
in that strong metaphor about the
newborn babe pity striding the wind
um and confesses that he has only
vaulting ambition, which orleaps itself
and falls on the other. So, the fantasy
is in this bank and shoal of time, like
crossing a river,
but when you leap,
you just fall. You don't You don't
get to the point you would like to
arrive at.
So, that's Macbeth
trying to
make the
depth of the crime just a local event.
It stops now. But here, but by this
blow, might be the be-all and the
end-all. And I think that might be the
first use of that interesting phrase in
English. It can just be over with. It's
just over with. And that's what people
going to commit some terrible thing, I
believe often say to themselves as a
sort of consolation, it's true to life
in that regard.
Um
Lady Macbeth, of course, all this while
uh has been setting herself up as the
person willing to face
um violation of nature, violation of
duty, because of the great um gift that
it will bring them, the gift of power,
the gift of being king and queen. And
she has said, when just when Macbeth is
about to arrive,
uh
following the message that she has read
already from him that he got this
strange hint from the from the witches,
she has said, "I'm no longer part of
nature.
Come you spirits that tend on mortal
thoughts, unsex me here, and fill me
from the crown to the toe top full of
direst cruelty.
Make thick my blood, stop up the access
and passage to remorse,
that no compunctious visitings of nature
shake my fell purpose."
And that is a it's a beautiful phrase,
the compunctious visitings of nature, as
if nature can't be undone.
But uh when she says unsex me here, and
in other places where she says, you
know, "I would beat out the brains of an
infant rather than quit this deed before
it's done."
There's a very strange suggestion that,
you know, Lady Macbeth sees herself as
witch-like, sees herself as in some way
supernatural, outside nature.
She can't live up to that aspiration,
but it's she who,
as it were, um
starts the engine of Macbeth's ambition
to turn it into something efficient,
which he is hanging back from quite
committing himself to.
What's interesting about their
relationship is the
um
progression of it, the kind of exchange
it undergoes as the play
uh advances.
Because already in Act 3, that's the
dinner scene, where uh Macbeth is quite
haunted and is uh acting so much so that
guests wonder what's up. They begin to
be suspicious about something strange
going on in this
family.
Um but already in [clears throat] that
scene, uh
Macbeth is
comforting Lady Macbeth, no longer
having to be roused by her as he
eventually is to commit the murder.
Um and when she tells him to put on a
good face, gentle your looks,
um he says to her, um "Full of scorpions
is my mind, dear wife." But he's not
going to tell her exactly what's up. "Be
innocent of the knowledge, dearest
chuck, till thou applaud the deed." One
of the I can only call it Shakespearean
touches all through this play
is what a good team they are, how well
suited as husband and wife. I won't say
loving, that almost seems a you know to
a larceny against the word love, but
they're very compatible. Let's just say
they like each other a lot and they're
they're suited to each other and they
care about each other in a way that
they're not capable of caring about
anyone else. Um
Macbeth continues the self-deception
that a deed committed right here, right
now can stop right here, right now. Um
he knows that this is a deception. He
says as much when he speaks the line
to know my deed, 'twere best not know
myself.
As if you could separate your personal
agency from the things you do.
That's the fantasy nursed by Macbeth,
and I want to suggest it's also a
fantasy common to all ambition.
>> [clears throat]
>> Ambition in that sense, in that hard
sense, is something as if outside you
that takes you over.
And
that makes the person no longer
inwardly
able to care about right and wrong. No
longer part of nature to use the word
that Lady Macbeth has used.
Um that idea of being here,
where there is the
be-all and the end-all,
the fantasy of jumping the life to come,
persists throughout the play. And I want
to point out that in one of the speeches
of Shakespeare that people most like to
memorize, every bit as much as Hamlet's
to be or not to be,
um we're not getting a piece of
you know, more than ordinary human
wisdom, but a typical evasion by Macbeth
when he speaks the speech I'll now
remind you of cuz you all know it.
She should have died hereafter.
There would have been a time for such a
word. Notice his words here
and there, trying to locate the deed in
one place rather than have it stretch
out to cover the whole meaning of your
life. And that's when he goes on,
tomorrow and tomorrow and tomorrow
creeps in this petty pace from day to
day to the last syllable of recorded
time.
And all our yesterdays have lighted
fools the way to dusty death.
Out, out, brief candle. Life's but a
walking shadow,
a poor player that struts and frets his
hour upon the stage and then is heard no
more. It is a tale
told by an idiot, full of sound and
fury,
signifying nothing.
And again, I'll just
say, because it's bewildering and more
so the more you know the play, this has
been taken
as a indication of profound wisdom about
life, as if Shakespeare is speaking
everything he knows about good and evil,
love and death, through Macbeth.
But it is no such thing. This is
Macbeth's,
um, locating,
uh, of Lady Macbeth's death
in a hereafter where she should have
died, and then his, uh, revelation that
to himself now life has become a tedium.
It's just one thing and another and
another and another. We're all just
actors on stage, and that word shadow is
an Elizabethan synonym for actor, among
other things.
But let's call this speech nihilistic,
but the nihilism belongs to Macbeth and
it's an exposure of the cost of
ambition. It is not Shakespeare's
information about the nature of life.
Um,
I think I'll stop there. I had other
things to say and a couple of other
wonderful speeches that I would have
recited, but, um,
let me just pose two possible topics for
us to come back to,
uh, in discussion.
Uh,
one topic is the witches. What do you
make of them? Because,
you know, they seem to know everything
in advance. So, is a human agent even
responsible in that case?
And the second is children.
Um, Lady Macbeth says that she's given
suck. Um, so she's had a child.
Um, but the Macbeths don't have
children.
Um, and there is a curious moment in a
scene of Act 4
where uh the bad news of Macduff's whole
family being slaughtered
comes to him. And he's told by Malcolm,
the heir to the throne,
um, you know, don't cover your face,
just take it like a man in effect.
And Macduff's answer is very interesting
answer. He has no children.
>> [clears throat]
>> So, what is this about the the idea of
children as something deeply related to
what's not present in Macbeth and Lady
Macbeth.
And then the the the dynamic, to call it
that, between
nature, the nature that Lady Macbeth
hopes to separate herself from,
and um, the the supernatural, the
supernatural element in this Scottish
play. So, I'll stop there.
>> Thank you, David. Uh, Professor
Bromwich, that was wonderful. So, um,
in this class, we tend to be
imaginative. So,
um, what I'm going to do is I'm going to
paint a scene where Dante has
has been to the has um, is at the
premiere of Macbeth and Shakespeare
comes out at the end and gives and
everyone gives him a standing ovation.
And then afterwards, Shakespeare and
Dante have dinner alone together.
And of course, Dante only has effusive
praise for Shakespeare, the language,
the poetry. But during the dinner, he
raises three concerns that he'll have
about the play Macbeth.
His first concern it The first question
he'll he'll ask Shakespeare is, "Are you
fun fundamentally pessimistic?" Because
Dante, as we learned in this class, he
is a fundamentally optimistic person uh
who believes in free will, who believes
in salvation, who believes that we are
ultimately the masters of our own
destiny. And as you point out,
Shakespeare does come from the Greek
tradition.
Um and um
the example, of course, is the Oedipus
Rex tragedy, where Oedipus, regardless
of his character, regardless of um
uh what what he does, he's bound by
fate.
Um so, that's Dante's first concern. Um
is Shakespeare fundamentally a
pessimistic person? Do humans have
absolutely no agency and free will in
this world? That's first question.
Second question is,
would Shakespeare Does Shakespeare
believe in God? Is he a Christian, in
other words? Uh because he As you point
out, Macbeth, there's conception of
nature, but it's as you point out pretty
nihilistic. Um and it seems the witches
have all the power. Now, um
in this class, what we did we did What
we did discuss is Dante has particular
hatred towards fortune tellers, okay? He
has a very He has a place in hell for
them, and he thinks that they are the
cause of all misery in the world. Um and
they And it's because they reduce
people's capacity to make choices.
Because if you think about it, if
Tiresias if the fortune tellers didn't
provide these
fortunes, then
Oedipus would not have would not have um
had the tragedy that he had. He was He
was forced to act in the way that he did
because of these fortunes. So, is it
just the gods manipulating us? Okay,
that's the second question you would
have.
Um the third question you would ask
is this.
How How does Shakespeare feel about
women in society? Because the Greeks
there are a lot of extremely evil women
in their tragedies that drive a lot of
action. Um but if we read The Divine
Comedy and we did with The Divine Comedy
Dante is very
pro-woman.
In fact, in heaven it is
Mary who's queen of heaven. It is Mary
who redeems humanity, not Jesus. Okay?
So, these are the three concerns that
Dante would have about this play, right?
First to to summarize,
is Shakespeare pessimistic about human
nature? Second question is, does
Shakespeare believe in God? The third
question is,
how does Shakespeare feel about women?
So,
>> Well, Lady Macbeth is a is a
thoroughgoing
uh
female
villain and yet she is quite humanized
by the end.
Um she
not only says
uh what's done
cannot be undone,
but she says, you know, not
uh
what are the lines? Not all the perfume
in Arabia will sweeten this uh my this
little hand. I mean, that that's a the
the
fantastical
imagining of the harm to nature that
their deed has done is actually common
to Macbeth and Lady Macbeth, but she she
thinks she can elude it at the time she
is um urging him to commit the deed. Uh
and when Macbeth is hesitant, later he's
more determined and he the last decisive
action before he goes uh into his duel
against Macduff is to put on his armor.
I mean, that's he That's to forget even
um the grief that he expresses over over
his death. She is uh
showing her consciousness of um
being part of her deed when she tries to
wash the
In her sleepwalking, she's trying to
wash her hands of the blood. So, they
both they they share that awareness and
they share the repression of that
awareness. The not wanting to
acknowledge the thought that Shakespeare
lets us see nevertheless is in them. Um
Macbeth's version of, you know, not all
the perfumes of Arabia will sweeten this
little hand is even more famous. Um you
know, can uh
Neptune's all the water in great
Neptune's ocean wash clean
uh
this hand for of blood? No, rather will
my hand the multitudinous seas
incarnadine, making the green one red. I
mean, this is an extraordinary speech.
And
I mean, Macbeth is is rather um they're
they're both rhetorically powerful to
each other not uh not least, especially
she for her influence on him.
But they do have
um
consciousness
of what they've done and it doesn't ever
rise to the point of conscience that
would stop them from doing it. So, I I I
see Lady Macbeth as a a bad person who's
becoming something worse than that, but
she begins only as a a rather
conventional person who hasn't yet had
her chance.
Um she's no great indication of
Shakespeare's attitude towards women in
general. Uh you can look at the
character of Cordelia in King Lear,
of Desdemona in Othello, and a good many
women in the comedies if you want an
idea of just how
um naturalistic uh
a feminist Shakespeare was capable of
being. I'm going backwards uh in your
three questions, but about fortune and
that brings us to the role of the
witches.
I think Shakespeare there, too, um
is being naturalistic by his lights.
That is to say, observing what people in
society are like, and this is a this is
a Scottish society. Um there there uh
is a prevalent belief that witches
uh exist and operate in the world in
Scotland uh even at the time Shakespeare
wrote. The witch burnings are are um
into the 17th century. So,
uh you know, the the belief that witches
operate is is real. Um
what credit does Shakespeare give to it?
I think he treats it as something people
believe,
and Macbeth most of all. But not all
people believe it in the same way. He is
listening to the predictions that they
make
in company with Banquo,
and um
Banquo says something like uh look how
our partner's wrapped. Macbeth is so
struck by what they're saying, and is
you can use the other meaning of the
word sorry, the other spelling. It's a
different word. It's he's wrapped up in
it.
Um he he can't tear himself away from
what they have brought to mind. This
This um
murderous thought that smothers
functions and surmises. So, Macbeth is a
believer. He was a you know, apt prey
for the witches.
Um, but you know, treat
uh
treat the witches in that regard
as something like
um a statistical prediction
of you know, what the likelihood is of
me
uh
living another 10 years.
I get this from statistics. The doctors,
you know, from reputable medical
journals tell me that I my genes are
such that it doesn't much matter what I
do. I have a very good chance to live 10
years on. So, I go on a rampage of all
sorts of dangerous things because I
think, you know, the doctors have
predicted that that's the way it's going
to be for me. I think that kind of I'm
going to call it superstition, but it's
just obedience to ideas about the future
has been common in human nature
forever and Shakespeare's using it.
Um,
I also just from from having visited
Wales and certain parts of Scotland
where the mists are
um on a
twilight time
uh it becomes easier to believe in
things that are a little beyond nature.
About his pessimism, I
again, I'd only go back to what I said
um
in response or rather in in uh
interpreting that
tomorrow and tomorrow and tomorrow
speech.
Uh Shakespeare is acquainted with
nihilism uh and with the Machiavellian
version of nihilism in the character of
Edmund, for example, in King Lear.
But I think he sees it just as a one of
the human occurrences. These people
exist, therefore he is going to portray
them.
Unlike Dante, as far as I know Dante and
my my knowledge of it is nowhere near as
good as this what this class probably
has by now.
Um Shakespeare is not going to comment
on the things he sees
in human nature, in human nature and
society.
He shows you good and he shows you evil.
He He usually
uh
makes it possible for you to see how
good could triumph over evil.
But, the judgments come from the
characters, not from the author. And
maybe that difference is also partly
owing to the difference between dramatic
form and the kind of epic poem that that
Dante's writing. Just a last point, it's
just a point of information. Shakespeare
didn't know the Greek tragedy tragedians
and he probably didn't know Aristotle,
though he would have had rumors about
Aristotle. So.
>> Right.
Um so, again um
Dante and Shakespeare are having
dinner
and now that Shakespeare has responded
um Dante hears all this
and he he only feel a sense of horror at
these ideas that are being articulated.
And he has to ask this question.
Does Shakespeare Do Shakespeare Do you
believe in God?
And if so, what is God?
>> Well, this play has been called by many
commentators, you know
um
orthodox Christian of its time uh in the
beliefs that it reflects. That is to
say, when you when you
um
you know, when you rend nature, when you
uh
do something that tears the fabric of
nature and pulls yourself away from it,
uh that is an offense against God and
nature may be um from the Dante point of
view too weak a word for what you're
doing.
But
I you know, again, I I I'm I'm going to
come back maybe very inadequately or
unsatisfactorily with my secular view of
Shakespeare, which is that he takes
seriously the things that people take
seriously and belief in God is
inevitable. What the theology is behind
it exactly,
um you know, depends on the occasion of
the play he's going to um write at a
given moment.
Uh if you look at
King Lear,
I think there the pressure is is
greatest
on any belief in something beyond the
human realm that could save human life.
Um in Macbeth, I think the idea of a a
restoration of of an order of things
which God supervenes in it is stronger
by the end. Uh it's strong because of
um
the nature that Macduff feels is in him
and what Macduff's family must be to
him. I mean, we're made to feel the
absence of
children in Macbeth and Lady Macbeth
only by the planting of Macduff as a
counter character in that strange moment
when he is told of the death of his
whole family. So, it's a terrible play.
It's a frightening play. It does not
give you any image, clear image of the
good, but I think it it makes you able
to think about why it is that someone
like Macbeth
doesn't survive.
>> Okay. So, I'm going to ask one more
question and then we'll open it to uh
the students.
But in Divine Comedy, um there are lots
of prayers.
Um either Dante is making a prayer, uh
an invocation
uh by himself or maybe someone else in
Divine Comedy is making a prayer. And
for Dante, that's very important because
uh when you make a prayer to God,
um you are also speaking widely to the
universe.
So,
in Shakespeare and all his like 37, 39
plays, does anyone make a prayer? That's
the first question. And the second
question is
if not, if the soliloquy is just
you're just talking to yourself,
what exactly is the point of that?
>> Well, there is a there is a prayer I can
think of right off and I'll just use it
as another situation and that is
uh
Claudius,
uh the
uncle of uh Hamlet,
who has
uh
murdered uh Hamlet's father,
is is overheard by the audience, not by
Hamlet,
praying uh for confessing his sin.
That's the only moment in the play where
we know for sure that the ghost was
right uh in what he said about the the
the matter of his death.
Um he he prays uh for forgiveness, I
suppose, and uh he confesses, too, that
his prayers aren't going up to heaven,
but sinking down to earth and then
sinking himself into hell. So, there is
a prayer. Um it's it's just used in the
play. It's a prayer forgiveness for by a
bad man, which is not granted. It's the
kind of little moment you do get in the
Inferno, I think, but it's made a
passing moment in the play.
Um
it bears on ambition, too.
Ambition knows what it is, even though
it's something that blocks
self-knowledge.
And a curious um
fact about that speech
when Abraham Lincoln, who knew
Shakespeare pretty well, wrote a letter
to the author of a book on Shakespeare
and said some interesting things about
several of the plays
um Macbeth was his favorite, by the way,
and Lincoln knew that he, Lincoln, was
ambitious, confessed it in an
interesting notebook entry to himself
and in other places less openly. I
thought ambition was dangerous, but that
his ambition is probably what allowed
him to become president and to lead the
campaign against slavery. It had to be
somebody who had a great idea of his own
abilities.
>> So sorry
>> when he says this is his favorite speech
the word thought he would have for this
is not ambition, but hope.
All I was going to say is uh
uh
um
Lincoln says that that that's that's his
favorite speech in Shakespeare.
That speech by Claudius
uh and it's a just a passing thing.
Um but it's a confession
of just how damned he feels by what his
ambition led him to do. So make of that
what you will, but there's a prayer in
Shakespeare.
>> Okay, thank you. Okay, so we're going to
open the floor to questions. Are there
any questions for uh Professor Bloom?
Yes.
>> Um is there a specific moment in
Shakespeare's life that you think
unlocked his imagination and could have
shaped his view of the world.
>> No, but I I tend I tend to be skeptical
of such singular moments. I know that
that that Dante is uh an exception to
that uh and that other artists are too
and some of them say so.
But Shakespeare uh gradually became uh
the greatest playwright in English. I
don't think from his very first plays um
you could say that he pulled away from
the very you know impressive crowd of
competitors that he was surrounded by
including Marlowe, including Ford at a
later stage and so on.
So,
no, I think it was his knowledge of
people, his knowledge of of the court at
a tangent, his knowledge of some
aristocrats, um his knowledge of people
who had fought in battles, his knowledge
of people in the theater uh who
themselves are a diverse lot. They're
not isolated and not living in what we
now call a bubble. So, he was he was
worldly, but especially with regard to
London and the work he did um you know
as uh um
somebody who helped to run a a a theater
outfit.
>> Sorry, so um to expand the question, in
this class um we speculate on weird
things, right? So, we discuss is it
possible that Dante had access to
psychedelics? Is it possible he had
visions? Uh was he an avid dreamer? Um
did he have a near-death experience? And
so,
um is there any scholarship on
um Shakespeare and how he was able to
achieve his visions?
>> Well, there's there's lots and there's
this new movie called what is it?
Hamnet? I mean about uh the you know the
the
uh
unhappy pregnancy of his wife and how
much that mattered to him and how much
that mattered to her. There are lots of
stories like this. Um I think
Shakespeare is an unusually hard case
for making much of his life. That's
actually That's actually one of the
things that I think um
uh bewilder people about him. He doesn't
seem exceptional.
Um and and there's this that same
quality about Mozart, but at least
Mozart has one exceptional thing. He
seems able to have composed great pieces
at the age of six or seven. That you
can't say about Shakespeare. But I you
know, it There's There's not a a story
of of the germinal incident or the the
terrible near-death experience or trauma
that I think lies behind um
you know, all the interesting
productions uh that we that we have the
highest respect for.
I was saying earlier I'm before before
we started this officially that I'm
teaching a course on Melville next term.
And I think you can say about Herman
Melville that his years at sea were the
thing that mattered to him much more
than his much longer period on land.
That's clear. But you know, can you
trace to one point what what made him
write Moby Dick?
I I I'm not able to do that.
>> Okay. Great. Uh question back there?
>> If Dante was directing Macbeth
in the scene where uh Macbeth that does
the speech, "Is this a dagger that I see
before me?" Do you think Dante would
instruct the stage production to have a
dagger appear on the stage or continue
to leave it in the imagination of the
audience as is common?
>> Ah.
Dante might let you have I mean that
Dante is serious Catholic. Catholic are
not against idolatry from objects. I I
think he he might well have put the
knife right there. And I think it's
common but not universal to have the
knife be only imagined by uh um
uh by Macbeth. That's another
interesting moment of acting as if he is
led on by forces outside himself as
ambition does for you. Um because he
says to the he says to the dagger, "Thou
marshal'st the way that I was going."
Which confesses that he was going to do
it anyway, but the hallucination helps
him. And you know, he he embarks on the
deed right after that with the words, "I
go and it is done."
Um so, you know, it's a it's a stage
prop. It's and it's a favorite
performance piece isolated from
everything else in the 19th century. But
um yeah, thank you for bringing that up.
I mean, that is that's that's
one more instance of the consistency
of this portrayal that Macbeth and Lady
Macbeth are always putting off onto
something slightly external the impulses
that drives the ambition that is in
themselves.
>> Okay, thank you for that. Uh yes.
>> Um yeah, so I'm interested in your
perception of the witches.
So,
witches we could say they're humans, but
you know,
um we have demons in the Divine Comedy.
So,
what's do are the witches possessed by
demons or
what's like the how do we define the
witches? Like why why are they doing
what they are doing?
>> So, I'll I'll first point out the
naturalistic, that is to say
non-supernatural,
almost dismissal of the witches that we
get from Banquo uh in lines that run
something like
um
the Earth has bubbles as the water has.
These are of them.
So, there are, you know, almost as if
he's a professor of physics, there is
Banquo, the the ordinary um
you know, um not overambitious
uh
warrior alongside Macbeth, just saying,
"This is all very strange, but maybe it
doesn't mean much of anything." And
that's that's a fascinating proposition,
isn't it? Um
William James, uh great American
philosopher, who was uh interested in
psychic phenomena and was the head of
the society in Britain that studied that
at one point. After years and years of
studying it, said he came to believe
that there were ghosts, that there was
another world, that it that it it
actually
existed. But the disappointment from his
many years of conversing with the things
on the other side was they didn't have
very interesting things to say.
They They were like gossiping about the
housekeeper in the basement and ordinary
dreary stuff like that. So, there's
similar to William James in this case,
there is Banquo saying, "The Earth has
bubbles as the water has. Perhaps these
are of them." Um
Macbeth brings something of himself into
the way that he is haunted. And it's a
portrait of him that the that the um
that the nature of that haunting gives
us more than anything sure about the
witches. But as I say, my my own um I
think true doctrine on the witches is
people believed in them.
And uh
believed in them and and it was right to
put them there because if you believe in
something strongly enough, strongly
enough, you will probably experience it.
You will even experience your own
self-righteousness if you believe in it
strongly enough.
>> [laughter]
>> Great question. Okay, any more
questions?
Uh yes.
>> I wonder if Shakespeare um naturalistic
in his nature or is he just adopting a
naturalism view when he's writing his
play? For example, does the
sonnets reflect more about what he
really believed than his plays does?
>> The sonnets are very uh they're written
a good deal before they're written
around the same a little bit about the
same time as Romeo and Juliet a little
after towards [clears throat] the time
he's writing
um Hamlet.
Macbeth comes a few years later.
Uh and in a way is much plainer in style
than the sonnets as sonnets are of
course an ornate form compared to what
Shakespeare does with drama.
Um
I sonnets tell you some things about
Shakespeare.
Uh and this this takes us back to my
dodging the biographical uh premise, but
I'll I'll say this much. He was He was
interested in the lives the lives the
the posture um the different uh quality
of experience that he found among
aristocrats.
And the aristocrat Southampton that he
is dealing with in some of the sonnets
um made a deep impression on him. And at
the same time uh he was wary of how much
these people had at stake about the the
deception and self-deception that it
could put them on to. Um and to to a
great degree about their um ability to
manipulate others just through the
status and sometimes stature that they
held. So, I mean the sonnets tell you
something about his
um
his attitude toward aristocrats, which
is which is careful
uh and admiring and wary.
Um it also tells you something about
Shakespeare's um
what to say
uh
erotic intensity. He was capable of very
strong feelings towards a woman
uh including
um
deep physical and other kinds of
attachment. Um and also including
suspicion, jealousy.
Um so, you know, the sonnets are a
personal statement to some extent and
yet they're written from within
uh you know, a genre post-Petrarch that
is a that is already setting the terms
of much of what Shakespeare says.
>> Um any more questions? Uh yes.
Would you view
Dante's creation of a universal
architecture
kind of an articulation
of capital T truth
or would you view it more as a longing
for
moral certainty?
And
how would you compare
>> You're asking?
>> Yeah.
>> You're asking how I see Dante?
>> Yeah, Dante the author, Dante the poet.
And then how would you compare
Shakespeare in that?
>> Dante Dante had I've just been reading
the chapter on the structure of the uh
uh Divine Comedy to prepare for
questions I thought I might get from
Jang. Um
uh
uh you know, it Eric Auerbach's book
Dante and and uh
uh
the world. And I think Dante gives form
to the world and form to um
uh
moral and um,
you know, uh,
uh,
what to say, any any thought about
nature you might have being shaped by
larger surrounding, um,
uh, circumscribing
understandings that are religious, that
are essentially religious.
Um, and what he's what he's doing in the
Divine Comedy seems completely different
from the sort of thing Shakespeare's
doing in his plays. I I don't see any
unity that you can add up from the three
dozen odd plays that Shakespeare wrote,
but in the case of the Divine Comedy,
the unity is obviously obviously there
and a a single-minded vision is there.
So, uh, they're just up to different
things. Um,
T.S. Eliot said, you know, Dante and
Shakespeare divide the world between
them, there is no third.
>> Um, we we we we had a question, uh, back
here.
>> Yeah, so can you expand a bit on
Shakespeare's perception of fate?
>> So, did did you catch the question?
>> Yeah, I did. Expand a little on
Shakespeare's conception of of fate.
Um,
I think he I I may be confusing his
views with mine,
uh, so please allow for that. I feel
that I've learned a lot from Shakespeare
and, uh,
can't be sure where some thoughts come
from,
but I I think he believed that there is
an there there is an
a moral order in the world. Um, the this
comes out in King Lear, which is the
most despairing of his plays in some
ways, and yet, uh,
the you see what you see in it is that
evil is not one undifferentiated thing.
There are people who are made worse by
the other people around them or by
incidents that happen in their lives.
Um, and uh,
the the what to say,
um, assurance or um,
uh,
uh, clarity that Shakespeare seems to
have from outside this all
is that I'm going to I'm going to use a
very kind of
slang expression for it. Um,
what goes around comes around. That
there is there is order in that sense.
That the people who do wrong in some
sense know exactly what they are doing.
And that others know.
And that the fact that this can be known
and shown
gives order to the world in itself. So,
let me put it a simpler way. Um, he
believes he believes in the um,
redemptive
Sorry, that's too strong.
He believes in the strengthening power
of truth.
And that truth comes out because to all
human actions there are human witnesses.
And people want to know. They want to
know truly. Um, and and people are
interested in the good.
Um, and prone to despair when they find
nothing but the absence of the good.
>> Uh, over here.
>> It's kind of combining um, Professor
Jones' question about Shakespeare's view
on women is something that's also very
perplexing to me about Shakespeare. That
half of his female characters are either
bad like witches or Lady Macbeth. And
then on the other side you find Portia
in The Merchant of Venice, the you know,
very wise
lawyer. and then also Ophelia who's in
Ophelia who drown herself in despair who
who's loving and all that. And then
there's Taming of the Shrew where with
uh Catr- uh Katrina, I think, Kat. And I
I can't reconcile. Yeah, how are we are
we supposed to look at Taming of the
Shrew? It's like the biggest issue in my
life. I was like, I can't accept. But
>> Really? Oh, no.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> [laughter]
>> It's not It's not such a It's not such a
great play. It's not It's not um It's
not full of wisdom. It's It's done to a
done to a theme um you know, details of
it show Shakespeare's greatness, but I
don't think I don't think the plot or
the characters um uh make you think in
the way that his truly greatest plays
do. But you you're mentioning all these
women. What about What about Rosalind in
As You Like It?
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> She's completely commanding. What about
What about Cleopatra in Antony and
Cleopatra? She's the most interesting
character in the play and I think you
could say not only does Antony die in
worship of her, but Shakespeare kind of
worships her, too.
>> Yeah.
>> Um so, I mean, there's great variety in
his in his portrayals of women. And
you're right, there you know, there
there are those bad ones, but they're
they're they're they're part of the
story.
>> Mhm.
>> Um okay, so we're running out of time,
okay? So, um
um it's 10:00 and it's very late where
Professor Bromwich is. So,
um Professor Bromwich, before we
conclude, do you have any questions for
us as as a group? Maybe a question for
the students um
or
>> I would like to know, and I say this as
someone um just, let's say, barely
conversant with Dante. Um and having
been reading it uh uh, more than I
have done lately in the last few days
just to prepare for this
encounter with you. So,
let me ask you
what is what kind of satisfaction
do you have from reading Dante that
seems quite special and absent, for
example, in a less overtly religious,
um, writer like Shakespeare?
>> Well, okay. So,
guys, that's a question for you guys.
What is unique about Dante?
Anyone?
Okay, back there?
>> Oh, yeah. I think Dante's works is
really making me feel impressive because
before the Dantes, I just feel confused
about money, about power, about AI,
about technology, and all of these
things I think this come from human
mind. But after Dantes, I know that all
of these things maybe just the thing,
this kind of original thing. And even
though you can say that AI is kind of
kind of kind of technology, but it
doesn't mean that it really doesn't let
people to be controlled, right? So, even
money, which we think is quite needed,
but it also uh, we have to admit that
money surely can let people to be like
slave, you know, to be enslaved people's
mind. So, maybe Dante is really make
people recall about what what we've been
through about history. What is history
and keep telling us about truth.
>> Okay, thank you. Um, yes?
>> I just find it quite reassuring. I don't
think Shakespeare would ever let any of
his kings or queens end up in purgatory
languishing in the sweet-scented valley.
And it's a nice thought that Dante
allows even people who have great power
a little bit of leeway as long as they
have a good heart, but I've never read
it in Shakespeare.
>> Okay. Uh, yes?
>> I think I I'm sorry.
I think maybe it provides a moral
framework to work off of, especially if
you're religious.
Um, in the first case, uh,
and also, um, whether you agree with for
example how he puts some people in hell
and some people in purgatory and some
people in paradise that maybe you don't
agree with it's still I think a good
more of very reassuring moral framework
and you can really start working off of
that to get your own moral framework and
it's just really reassuring to you know
feel also I guess you said that
Shakespeare also has a similar thought
of faith is that bad people that do bad
things have a bad ending and good people
that do good things have a good ending
and I think that's a reassuring moral
framework to have even if you're not
religious.
>> Thank you.
Yes.
>> I feel like the difference is that Dante
is
more certain in his judgments like he is
trying to like he his works have a lot
of are very certain and he gives people
as
Cal was saying this reassuring moral
certainty but as you said I feel like
Shakespeare he more or less
just observes people and then tries to
show them for
like how humans act and so in that way
he is giving his readers less certainty.
Yes.
>> So I have
>> There's less certainty for sure.
>> Yeah I have read Shakespeare for AP
language and AP literature and memorized
most of the quotes that you mentioned as
a you know a high schooler and I loved
it. But after reading Dante I feel like
he's the ultimate synthesis of a lot of
the
theology that I have encountered because
I also went to Bible school and every
day we have to you know reconcile
paradoxes and stuff and I feel like
Dante is one of those that kind of
answers a lot of my questions that
Shakespeare may not I feel like
Shakespeare is like this is the world
let me present it on a stage for you for
you to see what life is.
But Dante is like well this is Earth but
there's more beyond Earth. There's
heaven and hell and like, you know, all
these things that you need to be aware
of and why there should be retribution
for the wrongs. So, I feel like, yeah,
Shakespeare's more like a matter of fact
of what it is and Dante's more like this
is the interpretation or the, you know,
outside of the cave vision. Yeah.
>> Okay. Any more?
Um
Any more? Yes.
>> I actually think you need both because
um in reading, of course, to me,
yeah, what
everybody whatever really has been
saying is true.
But, um what I've been I've not a
Shakespeare scholar. I haven't studied
Shakespeare in detail before, but I
think that observational
naturalistic
approach that Shakespeare has actually
might complement
um whatever that we've been learning so
far in Dantean
uh in the Dantean framework because if
you're able to put yourself in the shoes
of of a another person and evaluate this
this this moral framework, you might be
able to
find answers that are more pertinent to
like modernity, what we're facing now.
>> Thank you.
How about you, Carol?
>> Well, I would just say that this
conversation across time and space and
generations and eras have been
enormously enlightening. Um
in this workshop, we've been talking
about the channeling of the author's
mind and world and architecture
um implanting it into ourselves as we
become a reader and a deep reader. And
um
you know, at at our age, it's not
something that we do that often usually
in the in the mundane um vicissitudes of
life. So, I think and and you also see
that in the audience, we have people
from
different walks of life,
different places and all of that. And
it's just been enormously enriching.
You know, not dissimilar from what it
would be like on the Yale campus
in in a seminar or class with you.
And so, I mean, actually, I want to
follow up with an invitation for you to
come over in person, perhaps, next
summer.
And and and bring us through some deep
readings, as well.
I think we would really welcome that.
>> I would love to and and I hope I hope
it's possible.
If I can only make This will be my one
comment on Shakespeare and Dante
together.
That if you think about think about
ambition.
Think about ambition as a
and
>> [clears throat]
>> not not ambition as
an unnecessary desire to perform
something,
but ambition as a vice, as a vice that
takes someone over.
Shakespeare gives you a story.
A whole story.
And the story is deepened by the way
characters rub up against each other,
the friction of characters. That's the
difference between drama and the an epic
poem that Dante Dante can give you
ambition and there'll be background
incidents, very shorthand, about why
these characters are guilty of it and
what their punishment is in hell.
But it's they're just very different
ways of coming at it and their the
rewards are accordingly, I think,
different and both very great.
>> And we definitely hope to see you in
Beijing.
Um And maybe we can have a seminar on
Shakespeare and Dante together. And we
we can have a conversation between the
poles of the two two of the whole world,
right?
>> That that sounds like a greatly tempting
offer.
Thank you for the whole
for the whole class and the engagement
that I I just saw and
you know, I was I was glad to stay up
late for this.
>> Thank you so very much.
>> Okay. Well, that was Professor Bromwich
and
um
again, he was my mentor at Yale. I took
three seminars with him.
And as you can see, we are very very
different.
But a lot of it is because
um when I was at Yale, I tried very hard
to emulate him. I learned a lot about
teaching from him.
He was basically my No, no, no, no, no.
He was not my virtual No, no, no, no.
That's a trap. That's a trap question.
No, but it shows you what the learning
process is. You first want to emulate
and then once you emulate, you can then
become your own person.
Okay? So so that that's what I'm trying
to do in this class. So it seems as
though I'm trying to force ideas down
your throat, but it's really just to
help you provide a framework for you to
understand Dante so that you can develop
your own interpretation.
Okay? So
but as you as you can see, even though
he was he was my mentor at Yale and
we're still very good friends, he and I
see the world very differently. And I
think that's a very positive thing.
Okay,
so any questions
or comments or concerns from last class
that you want to address before we
continue Purgatory?
Anyone?
Yes?
>> Um yeah, so yesterday we concluded hell,
right? Or was it the day before?
No, I think the day before, but I I
thought like because we discussed
you know, I would say said that um this
is Virgil's conception of hell and not
really Dante's.
Um then what what would Dante's
conception look like?
And how far would he then agree with
Virgil's conception?
>> Yeah, that's a really great question.
And it's something that I thought a lot
about yesterday um as well. Because we
went a bit extreme yesterday. And maybe
uh we said a lot of things that are that
were actually not appropriate. For
example, we speculated as to um
if Virgil was in fact Lucifer. If if in
fact he was master of hell and why
that's the case. We also said, well,
maybe what happened was that Virgil was
the one who was being tortured by
Lucifer and then he made a deal with
Beatrice.
Um and then he got out of it, okay?
Um that's a bit extreme. And I and I and
it's great to imagine, but it's also
important to reflect and see how true
our imaginings are. And in that instance
where Beatrice cuts a deal with uh
Virgil, um that would never happen in
Dante's conception of the universe. Why
not?
Do you guys Do you guys know why not?
And it's really important. Yes?
>> Cuz then like it doesn't really make
sense cuz like your pun- punishment
would change and so it breaks the whole
thing about Inferno where you're
supposed to be punished for a certain
act. Yes. And so like why would you move
and
>> That's right. That's right. Uh yes?
>> And it's almost like Beatrice has the
right to kind of do pacts, almost like
she's got
>> Yeah. Yeah. S- But but that's is
important, okay? In Dante's world, God
is not transactional. Maybe in our
world, maybe in the Catholic Church, but
God himself is not transactional. He
would never make a deal. That's what the
devil does, okay? All right, so you are
judged for what you do and what you
believe, not because you have an a deal
an offer you can make to to God, okay?
So that's So So it's really important we
clarify this. Beatrice would not have
the power to make a deal with Virgil,
and quite honestly,
um
it wouldn't have it wouldn't have
happened, okay? So this This then leads
the question like, what then is going
on?
And um I think what Dante wants to say
is that everything in the universe is a
co-creation process, okay? It's a very
important because
um I think in Shakespeare's uh
conception
what would happen is that God creates
the universe. He's like the the master,
and then we just live in it. Whereas for
Dante, no, it's we all participate in
the co-creation process. So hell is
there are some aspects of God in it, but
there are also aspects of our
imagination in it. And um poets, because
they have the the most vibrant
imagination, they can have the most
impact in the co-creation process, okay?
So it's not as simple as saying like,
who created hell? Is it Was it Virgil?
Was it God? I would say that first of
all, it's a co-creation process, but
what's But what's much more um
um challenging to understand is that
it's a evolving process.
Right? So hell itself evolves, where
Jesus can come and take out people from
limbo, and then there'll be a like a
sundering of hell, so it changes the
physical landscape. Right? And then
Virgil can walk around it and interact
with people and change the dynamic of of
hell.
All right? So, that's something that's
really important for us to appreciate
about uh Dante. Um maybe for Shakespeare
things are much more static, but for
Dante things are much more dynamic.
Okay, it's a co-creation process that's
constantly evolving. So,
um with each reading of Inferno, Inferno
itself changes, if that makes sense.
Okay? When you read Inferno, the way you
perceive Inferno changes, and your
perception of Inferno changes Inferno
itself.
Uh yes?
>> I remember yesterday when we read about
when someone does a really bad sin,
their soul is immediately taken down.
That's right.
Um
it
I just want to work out a bit of an uh
uh problem I have where in Macbeth,
the fact that towards the end of the
play, Lady Macbeth and Macbeth go kind
of crazy, and there's like a s- flicker
of conscience in them.
How do I reconcile that? Because
it their soul would have already been
taken in Dante's conception. So, is that
Shakespeare saying that
even if your soul is taken, your body
could emulate conscience in a way, even
though you're irredeemable?
>> Okay. Uh
that's a really interesting question.
And this is how I I would reconcile
this, okay?
I would say that what's really important
to understand is that your soul exists
in infinite dimensions. So, your soul
exists at in hell, purgatory, and heaven
at the same time.
And depending on your action, your soul
emphasizes different parts differently.
Okay?
So,
um it's not as clear as, "Okay, you do
one bad thing and in an instant your
soul is transported to hell and a demon
comes in and you're just a demon." Um
I think I think it's much more
complicated. I think like now there's an
theme aspect to you.
>> [laughter]
>> Okay, does that make sense? Yeah, yes?
>> Yeah, just like the guy who died next to
Jesus because he deserves to be
crucified to show that he's probably
really bad. But right before like
seconds before he died, he said to
Jesus, I repent and then Jesus was like,
"Okay, heaven welcomes you." So then
there is this aspect of redemption to
the end of a very evil person's life.
Otherwise, all these last ending
repentance, right? Asking the priest to
come to your house and forgive you. Ask
what has happened to Oscar Wilde.
Actually, right? He has to live with the
life of Dorian Gray till the last end,
right? Like literally the day before he
died and he converted to Catholicism all
of a sudden, which he was the most
antichrist person, right, in his age.
But, you know, so then we can safely
assume that Oscar Wilde somewhere in
purgatory. If we pray for him, maybe he
will speed up to heaven, right? Like so
there is this
>> Yeah, so it's really interesting because
because what Donny is referring to is
the unity of the universe, of the
cosmos, right? So not only are you do
exist among
like amongst different dimensions, but
you're also connected to everyone else.
Okay? If that makes sense.
Right? Does that answer your question?
>> So I mean, but it was still Virgil who
kind of started off hell when he wrote
the Aeneid or was it was hell like
because in the Roman or Greek
like religious views there isn't really
a conception of hell. So before Virgil
there wasn't
hell basically or Okay, so first of all,
there was a conception. It was called
the underworld.
All right? Right? So if you read the
Aeneid, Aeneas journeys to the
underworld and he meets the shades,
right? Uh, Ditto is there. They're all
shades. So, Virgil So, Dante's drawing
from that that in the underworld you're
all just shades. That's point one. Point
two is that if the fundamental law of
the universe is free will, that means
these places are constantly changing
over time. So, maybe before Christianity
this was a pagan hell, pagan underworld.
With the rise of Christianity, then we
added Christian elements to it for a
collective imagination. So, the nature
of hell changes over time as the
conscious of humanity changes over time.
Okay, does that make sense?
>> Because I I thought of this question
probably as well because you said in an
interview, I think, once that you
yourself don't believe in hell. Really?
Right.
>> Um, yeah. What I believe is that we
exist in infinite dimensions.
And,
um, you can describe the some of these
dimensions as hellish,
right? They're just low dimensions,
uh, where your lowest lowest emotions
are based or
uh, are stored.
Right? So, um, what I mean by that is
when people refer to hell, they mean
eternal damnation.
Right? Like when you go to hell, you're
like you're there forever. You can't
escape hell.
And I think what Dante is saying is
like, "No, um, there's no such thing as
eternal damnation. You can choose
eternal damnation, but it's your choice.
So, if you make the effort, you can
always,
uh, leave hell." And there's something
something that we will learn in
purgatory, okay? Because what Virgil is
saying is that you can never you can
never leave hell.
"You are not a Christian, and so you are
you must be in limbo, okay?" So, there's
an absolute sense to Virgil, whereas for
Dante, there's nothing absolute in the
world.
Right? Everything is evolving,
everything is changing, it's dynamic
depending on how you feel, yes?
>> Everything's organic.
>> Yes, right? So, uh the difference
between heaven and hell is hell is
mechanical, whereas heaven is organic.
Okay?
Okay? Does that make sense to you or?
>> Maybe well, one thing also
that springs to my mind is like how
well, people who only read, for example,
the Aeneid only know that
you don't have a choice to get out of
hell, so if you die without ever reading
the Divine Comedy, then it's kind of
difficult to get out of hell for you.
>> That's right, and that's why and that's
why Dante had to write Divine Comedy to
give hope to the world. And this system
we'll discuss actually as we go as we go
on in in in Purgatory, because again,
Virgil is absolute here, right? Uh yes?
>> I think it's also where you would put
yourself. It's not like God created hell
and then like he just chooses is like we
said also yesterday that the difference
between Inferno and Purgatory were was
the attitude, growth mindset, and
optimistic.
And so like it would change like if your
attitude would change, then your place
would change and you would like
transcend in like these dimensions.
>> That's right. That's right. And that's
why for Dante, the hope of the world is
poetry, right? Because okay, you bring
in a new emperor and he conquers the
world and he establishes peace for 20
years. Well, you're you're back to the
same situation after he dies, right? So,
what you need to do is expand the human
consciousness through poetry. Uh and
that's why
um
you know, he feels he needs to respond
to Virgil.
Okay? He's not trying to cancel Virgil,
he's trying to respond to Virgil and and
add to Virgil to give people hope. Okay?
Does that make sense?
All right, so any more questions? Yes?
>> Yeah, maybe that to build off that. Um
I'm reading Bart Ehrman's um
>> Yes.
>> Journeys Through Heaven and Hell.
>> And essentially what they do is they
talk about every single
story that's ever written that's like
Dante's. Like, "Hey, I went down to hell
and I walked around and stuff like
this."
Um, and they're all
um it's almost like how I read the
Inferno like back in high school where
it's like, "Ooh, there's lots of
punishments and stuff like this." And
they were all all these stories were
created um because they're like looking
for a way to control in the real life.
The elites are like uh enjoy your
poverty because you're going to have
eternal blessings. If you If you get out
of line, if you do any revolts, then
these are the bad things that are going
to happen to you. Um, Dante is
revolutionary because he was able to
take Aquinas and Augustine and actually
make a philosophy behind all of this and
and tie it up with a theology so that we
can have these amazing conversations
that we're having.
>> Exactly. That's exactly right.
Uh yes.
So, as we move from
Inferno to Purgatory
and um
Heaven, it seems as this linear path to
you know, things get better, there's
more hope.
But what
uh
confuses me a bit is that Purgatory
still seems uh
fairly arduous. But before we spoke
about Limbo, which is technically still
in hell, and it seems
easier.
>> Yes.
Um
right. So,
this is a paradox, right? Limbo is a
very pleasant retirement community.
Okay?
But
Purgatory is arduous.
Well, the difference is in emotions of
people, right? In Limbo, they're sighing
all the time because they they've given
up hope. They feel hopeless.
Okay?
Whereas in Purgatory, even though it's
it's arduous, they are singing. They're
excited. They're curious.
Okay? Does that make sense?
So, it's not about
um
the actual place, it's about how you
feel while you're there.
Okay? Uh yes?
>> with my husband. Like I just want to lie
down like lay flat and enjoy my life.
And he's like, "No, you work." It's kind
of the same as a retirement community
versus working arduously to climb a
mountain because my husband is totally
into hiking. He's like,
"The purpose of man is to, you know,
achieve something to an end." Where I
just want to live in retirement. And
he's like, "Then you are less of a human
if you live in a retirement community."
I'm like, "Well, thank you very much."
You know,
>> [laughter]
>> and
to say I have no pursuit in life. But I
think it's the same idea. Yeah, that's
what men ought to be.
>> Uh yes?
>> I don't know if this is
too literal way of looking at it, but so
you've got this journey, right? Through
purgatory. And if you can clean yourself
of the sins, you'll finally get to
heaven. Do we have any idea? I don't
know if we'll see it later.
Of how successful people are in actually
making it all the way up.
>> Everyone is successful. Like like once
you enter purgatory, you will succeed.
>> Oh.
>> Right? Because you've made the choice to
succeed.
Okay? Yes?
>> Um so so before you mentioned there's
there's some people done
um
bad deeds
that too bad they're uh in annihilation.
They're not even in hell. Does that mean
these people don't have a chance to
redeem redeem themself?
>> No, no, no. They choose not to redeem
themselves. So happy in hell.
>> No, you mentioned they're in
annihilation. Ni- annihilation.
>> Well, well, I mean, yes, they're in
annihilation because they chose they
chose not to live.
>> So after Oh, so after their choice, they
are forever
>> Yeah, because like
like
they just chose to do nothing in life.
They just chose to
um sleep for life, right? How How's that
different from like animals or plants?
Uh, so does that Does that choice is
instant? Like like um
>> Yeah, they don't want to exist. It's
their choice not to exist. You have that
choice.
>> Okay. Okay.
>> Okay?
Uh, yes.
>> Um
I was trying to
maybe foolishly um
uh, correlate uh, eth- like ethics uh,
with
the Inferno.
>> Yes.
>> Um, and I was thinking like we don't
hear it explicit- Maybe we do and maybe
I missed it, but we don't explicitly
hear your um anybody say like this is a
a punishment for rapists. That probably
lost somewhere. Um, but modern ethics
would say like what's the three worst
things you can do is like rape, murder,
but then slavery. And there was a lot of
people today that would say like
slavery's worse than murder because
slavery's like
>> Yes.
>> the slaves would happily kill themselves
and stuff like this. And it makes So, I
did some research on this and
Augustine would say that it's that it's
a by-product of the fall. Is that when
sin entered the world then people
learned to to be less kind to each each
other and there were hierarchies
involved and then slaves were involved
cuz even in Dante's time
slavery's less and we're moving into
feudalism, but it's not gone and it's
just a economic reality.
>> Yeah, you make a good point about
slaves. In The Divine Comedy, there are
no slaves.
Okay? And there's a very good reason
why. Because in this world
you choose to be a slave
because you'd rather forfeit your life
uh, sorry, you'd rather forfeit your
freedom than your life. You give up your
free will in order to
um protect your life. And if you think
about it logically, for Dante, you can't
do that because free will is God's gift
to you. And you're just giving up for
like nothing, really.
Okay? So, so slaves don't matter. Like
if If if you choose to be a slave, it's
like I choose not to live anymore. Okay?
You're basically a zombie.
Uh yes?
>> But what if you didn't choose to be a
slave? You were forced to be a slave.
>> No. That That's That's what I'm talking
about, Dante. You're You've always made
a choice. You've always made a choice.
Even if you are born a slave, you can
choose to run away. If you're born a
slave, you can choose to rebel.
I I know it sounds a bit extreme, but
that's how Dante sees the world. Uh yes?
Yes, back there?
>> I mean, I I hate to just to just beat a
dead horse, but like what if rebelling
would just mean instant death?
And you know that for certain. So,
that's your free will. Would you go to
hell or limbo or where if like
>> Yes?
>> Then that's called civil disobedience,
right? I bet there were I don't forgot
who
Uh one of the great philosophers where
he was put to jail if he did not agree
to one of the government
>> Socrates.
>> Yeah, I think so.
>> Socrates, yeah.
>> Yeah. And then so he was stoned to
death. And so
>> All right.
Right. So,
Uh
So,
I mean,
if you think death is the worst thing
that can happen to you, you don't have
any faith.
Do you understand?
>> I do actually agree with you. I would
just um I'm just
>> I'm saying that's what Dante would say,
right? To faith have faith is to believe
that God gave us free choice. God wants
us to live the best life possible. And
if we cannot live the best life
possible, then our souls are immortal
and we just come back at a little point,
okay? But what's what matters is to
protect the purity of your soul. And
that means to protect your free will.
Okay? If you'd rather like surrender
your free will just so that you can be
you live live
um then, you know, yes?
>> It's kind of like the Dragon Ball
festival which you celebrated like Tien
rather die and throw himself into the
river then So, there's another act of
civil disobedience. We still celebrate a
lot of dissent heroes whoever we call
them, right? Who die, chooses to die.
>> Exactly. Yes.
>> But then are we saying it's inherently
sinful to stay as a slave because you
have no free will? But what if you're a
slave and you're treated fairly well and
you're somewhat content with how you
are?
Then is that sinful?
>> Um
Yeah, I mean, what this is again is just
a lack of faith.
Right? It's a lack of understanding of
who you are. You're here to live the
best life possible. You're here to be an
inspiration to others. You're here to
co-create the universe. You're not here
to like
I don't know, like
just get by.
Uh yes?
>> I suppose where where then I go with
this is then surely through Dante's lens
should we all just
quit our jobs because basically in
modern society, right, if we're working
that free will is also taken.
>> Um no, that's not what Dante would say.
Dante would say trust your intuition. If
your intuition is I should just quit my
job and do something else, sure.
Right? But it depends on your situation,
it depends on your on your intuition.
There there can be no absolute rule,
right? There can be no general
principles. It depends on your own
individual understanding of the
situation and your own intuition.
>> Yeah, that's what I mean. So, if the
slave is a slave but their intuition
says it's fine, I'm looked after
then it's fine.
>> Yeah, if you feel you're being a slave,
then then you should quit your job.
Okay? [laughter]
Uh yes?
Y- Y- Yes, yes.
>> Yeah, I was wondering if you uh you can
just maybe give us some diagram about
the Dantes because I think Dante make a
diagram which is we can put our people
into the diagram. For example, like some
hero in in China or some hero in the
like Hamlet, right? So, I don't know if
Hamlet is on one hand and just try to
revenge, right? But he also try to make
justice for for his father. So, what do
you think about Hamlet, for example? Do
you think he would be in the dentist
limbo ward in the
Yeah, in the
ter- ter- paradise? Uh in in in the
paradise?
>> Well, I mean, I No, I think that Hamlet
would be in paradise.
Um because first of all, Hamlet is a
poet, and second of all, he chose to
live a righteous life.
Right? Um
Um
I'm sorry, he wouldn't be in heaven
because he did kill
um
Claudius, right?
Uh so, he'd be in purgatory, but I mean,
he wouldn't be there for long.
Okay? He would have to re- re- repent uh
and redeem himself of of his sin, but um
Uh I mean, like like like I don't want
to go into Hamlet uh because it's a very
complicated situation, but if you
actually understand the plot of Hamlet,
it was not
vengeance. It was not murder. It was
justice. The reason why is
that first,
Hamlet conducted an investigation to
confirm the guilt of Claudius, and then
there was a trial, okay? If you re-
remember the plot of Ham- Hamlet,
there's a there's a trial, an open
trial, where um everyone could see the
guilt of Claudius, okay? And so, for
Hamlet, what happened he was ordered to
uh avenge his father, and he and he
delayed the process, but he's because he
wanted to turn the act of vengeance into
an act of justice, okay? And I again I I
don't want to get too much into Hamlet.
It's a very complicated play, okay? Uh
yes?
>> would be in the first circle of heaven
because they are just content with their
life, and they abandon free will. Like,
for me, this just makes sense to put
them here.
>> Not in heaven. They're not in heaven.
>> But you know, like we saw like the first
circle of heaven, it was like people who
just gave up free will, so it was like
nuns who like married uh some guy and
just like accepted their their like
>> Right. So So that's So the moon which is
about the moon
Piccarda didn't give up her free will.
She made a vow to God. Okay? And then
she was violently forced out of the vow
by her brother.
>> You're right.
>> Okay. So So that's not slavery. Yes?
>> Like is this sort of
philosophy that you'd better give up
your life than your free will? Why Cato
is in purgatory instead of in hell?
Because like I remember you said that he
he killed himself as to like not be one
of Caesar's
followers.
>> You're right. And that And that's why
he's in purgatory.
Right.
Okay. Was that a question?
Okay.
Yeah.
That's right. Yes. Exactly. Okay. Yes?
>> Um I'm obviously I'm not an expert on
slaves or history but from like the
limited knowledge that I know slaves
often times slave owners would really
terrorize their slaves like every single
week there would be public bashings to
really instill fear into the slaves to
ensure that they don't run away. So the
slaves in turn they like learned okay I
can't run away but they still had acts
of rebellion. For example a lot of times
you would have slaves you know poisoning
their masters' drinks. You would have
them spitting in their food. You would
have them like just
doing these rebellious acts. So
in this case they are still rebelling
but it's just like the constraints of
society and their lives
>> know your your your history because it's
completely wrong. That's not how slaves
are.
I don't know where where you're this
information. Like like slaves like
poison their masters and spit in their
food.
Where where are you getting this
information from?
Okay, so let's think think about how
slavery happens, okay?
In ancient times, we had slaves because
um
I would my army would go conquer your
city
and then I give you a choice. You either
die or you become slaves, right? And
it's your choice.
And so when you when you become a slave,
it means that you are now my property.
You forfeit your humanity, you forfeit
your free will. You are now my property.
And because it's your free will to make
this choice,
you no longer can resist. Do you
understand?
Okay? That's where slavery comes from.
So slavery is people who choose
to become become slaves rather than to
die.
Uh yes?
>> But
I'm not I'm not saying I disagree, but
like the question here is you are
essentially if you go to hell like
you're punishing people for their own
individuality and their own choice, but
kind I feel like you're kind of
disregarding the influence of society on
them. Like the like shouldn't you be
criticizing society for having slaves
and limiting their freedom and not
allowing them to exercise their free
will rather than criticizing the slaves
for not having faith enough to criticize
their free will.
>> Uh yes?
>> Well, I forgot who said it, but men are
born free, but everywhere he goes he's
in chains. Virgil, was it? Voltaire,
yeah. And so
in your case of slavery, I think you
refer to North American black
African-Americans, right? So they are
born into slavery and there's no
you know, choice, you know, because they
are beaten like Uncle Tom, right?
Um but I didn't Well, don't try to say
that it's every one of us who are born
into this world. We are born women who
are inferior
by society judge usually, but you know,
compared to men. They are black people
who are born of, you know, with black
skin. There are people who are born into
slavery. They are all kinds of people
who are born into, you know, DNA deficit
where you are, you know, shorter or you
are you live shorter, you get cancer,
you know? So, all of us are born free,
but you live in chains. So, you can
always make a
your, you know, choice to live a better
life like Mother Moses who got away.
Like we heard a lot underground railroad
where a lot of these people try to run
away, you know? And yeah.
>> Yeah, back there.
I just want to to say two things. Number
one, it was Rousseau, not Voltaire, who
said that. Yes, that's correct. Yeah.
So, Voltaire, yes. Um and number two,
just in reference to your point about
the slaves spitting in the food and
poisoning the master's drink,
spitting in the food is one thing.
Poisoning the master's drink would be a
true act of rebellion trying to reclaim
your free will, but it would just be
very difficult for a slave to acquire
poison without money. And
these things are you exercising your
free will, but you are not reclaiming
your full free will. You have to break
free 100%.
>> Okay. Um so, you guys are working on the
assumption that slaves aren't happy.
Okay? You're thinking to yourself that
slaves really want freedom, and it's
just like they're being beaten every
day, so they can't have this freedom.
That's not how it works, okay? If you
read these
um Iron Curtain dissidents like Vaclav
Havel and after showing showing this
then, they see the same thing about life
under totalitarian regimes, which is
it's all just a facade.
It's all just theater. And we're they're
we're all just actors on the stage. And
what is shocking to them is everyone
chooses to participate in this facade.
They just say, "It's all just a lie."
Right? It's like in the moment people
are like, "You know what? Screw this
system."
The system collapses, which is exactly
what happened to the Berlin Berlin Wall
in the in the in the Soviet Union,
right? Just one day people are like, "I
no longer want to participate in this
facade." And then the system collapses,
okay?
So, you're we're going on assumption
that
these slaves are being controlled by
these overlords evil overlords, but the
reality is that slaves believe
"I should be a slave. I want to be a
slave. I find meaning in being a slave."
And for Dante, that is just outrageous.
Yes?
>> But I mean, like how could you assume
that the slaves are happy about
themselves in the first hand? Because I
feel like generally is like
at least easier for us to understand
that they are not happy because of all
those violence that the slaveholders
kind of like cast onto them. And also
like at the same time, if they are truly
happy, isn't it in some ways reclaiming
their own free will if they are happy?
Like that's my two questions. I'm just
kind of confused with
>> Okay. So, happy is a very strong word.
They're just complacent, okay? Uh yes?
>> So, I opened this can of worms and I
didn't even explain what I
what I learned at the end of it. Um
bringing ethics into Dante is incorrect.
Racism is unethical. There's no racist
in hell. Um and so, Dante, the question
isn't is slavery unjust or unethical?
It's is the social order properly
ordained toward God?
And so, slavers, the people that own
slaves, can end up in hell for any
number of things. But slavery is just a
byproduct of the fall. And so, you're
not going to end up in hell for the
fall. You're going to end up in hell for
violence or any number of things.
They're guests in your house. So, if you
kill your slave, then you would be in
the bottom level of hell.
Um that sucks in this modern world where
we equate slavery as one of the worst
sins.
Um it just doesn't
>> Yeah, so remember in in Divine Comedy,
there are no slavers, there are no
slaves anywhere, okay? It's not really
really an issue at
at this point.
All right. Okay, so let's uh continue um
uh Divine Comedy. Okay, so this is like
Canto 5 now?
>> Yep.
>> All right.
>> Uh Purgatory, Canto 5.
I had already left those shades behind
and followed in the footsteps of my
guide when there beneath me pointing at
me, one shade shouted, "See the second
climber climb. The sun seems not to
shine on his left side and when he
walks, he walks like one alive." When I
heard these words, I turned my eyes and
saw the shades astonished as they stared
at me at me and at the broken light.
"Why have you let your mind get so
entwined?" My master said, "that you
have slowed your walk. Why should you
care about what's whispered here? Come,
follow me and let these people talk.
Stand like a sturdy tower that does not
shake its summit through the though the
winds may blast.
Always the man in whom thought thrusts
ahead of thought allows the goal he set
to move far off. The force of one
thought saps the other's force."
Could my reply be other than I come and
somewhat colored by the hue that makes
one sometimes merit grace? I spoke those
words.
>> Okay, so let's figure out what's
happening here visually, okay? So, Dante
and Virgil are walking
and they're trying to get to the gate of
Purgatory so they can climb the mountain
of Purgatory because Beatrice is waiting
for Dante, right?
And as they're walking, they get
spotted by lots of shades.
And why are these shades interested in
Dante?
Why?
>> Because he has a shadow.
>> Yeah, right? Because he has a shadow.
Because he's different from they are.
So, they gawk and they want to talk to
him, right? And what does Dante do in
response?
>> Listens.
>> He doesn't He doesn't listen.
>> slows his walk to kind of consider what
they're doing and wondering
>> Why is he slowing his walk?
>> Because he's second-guessing or not
second-guessing, but just
>> slow slow
Why Why is he slowing his walk? Dante is
like speeding ahead and Virgil and Dante
is like, you know, walking really
slowly, walking really gingerly. But why
is he doing that?
Anyone?
So, we've seen this quite a few times
already, right? Where
the souls gawk at him and say, "Hey,
shadow." And then Dante just gingerly
slows down. Why Why do we do that?
Yes?
>> He wonders if he can help them in some
way or if they can give him information
about the ascent.
>> You're such a You're such a generous and
optimistic person. No.
Yes.
>> Like You're like the celebrity of
Purgatory.
>> Exactly. Do you understand? Okay? It's
like a movie star walks into a shopping
mall and gets mobbed. Does he not know
he's going to get mobbed? Right? He's
He's going to walk into a shopping mall
to get mobbed, right?
And like so Virgil is pissed off at at
Dante. Like cuz it's happened quite a
few times now, right? Where he's like
slowing down just so like the shades can
surround him and say, "Hey, can I have
your autograph?"
Right?
And so
um
So, first of all,
um why is Dante famous?
Why is he famous?
>> What?
>> No. No. No.
No. What Why Why Why is he famous? Like
>> He has a body.
>> No.
No. Why?
It's a shadow, right? He says a shadow,
okay? What is this a reference to?
You worship shadows. What is this a
reference to?
Plato, right? Allegory of the cave.
All reality is a shadow. If you worship
shadows, you are in hell, right?
Allegory of the cave, Plato.
So, let's expand this, okay?
They're in purgatory, which is the
light. So, it's like Dante and Virgil
have escaped the cave,
but
what?
They're still stuck in the cave
mentally,
right? They still think shadows are
real, and these shades worship
uh Dante because he has a shadow.
Why What What is Dante trying to trying
to say here?
What's a shadow?
Anyone?
Yeah Yeah Uh yes, what is a shadow? E-
Explain the the metaphor to me.
>> Well, it tries to imitate something
real,
right?
>> Right.
>> But it's not Yeah.
It's two-dimensional, as well.
>> It's two-dimensional, yes?
>> It means that in the Platonic i- idea
that a form has been instantiated, so
that when light shines on it, beings can
perceive it, and that it's not in the
formal world anymore.
>> Okay. Yes. Yes.
>> Uh I think it's the negative aspects of
Dante that he collected in hell, so it's
still like his you know, like when he
was dirty and he needed to clean
himself, he's still like dirty of his
shadow, and so it's going to be a
problem.
>> right. That's right. So, shadow is an
aspect left over from hell. Yes. That
Yes?
>> It's also eclipse of lights. That's how
shadow is created.
>> What is the shadow metaphor for?
You mean?
>> Is it sin? Or
>> No.
No. Shadow is metaphor for what in this
instance?
>> Is it
lack of light? So, it's blocking light
in a way.
>> Uh yes.
>> Ego.
>> Okay. The ego.
What? What?
>> Projection.
>> No. No.
No. Come on.
>> Just concepts that's not God.
>> What?
>> Uh so
uh in the allegory of the cave, there
are people who sit at the bottom of the
cave and they're in chains and they're
looking at a wall and at this wall are
shadows. And like if you go outside the
cave, there's actually people and then
there's a fire. So, the the um the
shadow on the wall is the projection of
the fire of the action of people. So,
that I think the shadow probably means
um an illusion uh an illusion illusion
of reality.
>> Right. I understand. But but what is it
metaphor
for?
>> Knowledge that you only gain from
looking at it.
>> Yes.
>> Absence of God.
Maybe.
>> Fame, guys.
It it it's a metaphor for fame, right?
You understand? And why is this
important?
Dante is obsessed with fame.
You understand? What what is he saying
that Dante is obsessed with fame? And
and why would this be important for us?
>> Well, fame as a pride is a sin.
>> Right. But but what But why would this
be a problem for Dante?
Yes?
>> It would be something he needs to work
on in purgatory.
>> Right. Right. But but I'm saying like
why is it problem now?"
Yes?
>> Because it's just slowing him down.
>> Yes, because he's trying to get to
Beatrice, right? Do you understand? This
is a metaphor.
Fame is what slows you down from
achieving God, from achieving reunion
with God. Do you understand?
Okay? Now, here here here's a here's a
hard question. Who put this idea in his
head?
Who Who said Virgil?
Do you remember where?
We discussed this, right? Do you guys Do
you guys remember?
What was the correct What was the exact
phrase
Virgil had said?
When When was When did Virgil say say
this?
What was the context? Do you Do you guys
remember we we we discussed this.
Okay. So, they are in hell. They are in
a circle of fraud, and they are climbing
these boulders, right?
And it's tiring for Dante, so Dante
slows down, and Virgil says to him,
"Hurry up for what?"
Why should you hurry up?
Excuse me?
For fame, right?
The exact phrase was everlasting
fame.
Remember?
Right? And we said,
"Virgil, why don't you say for Beatrice,
right?" But instead, Virgil says, "For
everlasting fame."
Right? You guys You guys remember this.
And now, Dante
Dante's Dante's shadow has made him
famous in Purgatory.
Right? But the irony is that it's a
shadow, therefore we know it's not
everlasting.
And it's slowing him down. In fact, he's
not actually walking anywhere, okay?
He'd rather talk to the shades. He'd
rather just like be adored
and adulated by his fans.
He's not actually doing going anywhere.
>> Yes. And it also tries to then mirror
what he wants actually in reality in
real life. He wants this fame, right?
>> Yes.
>> And he but he gets the exact opposite by
being exiled.
>> Yes. Yes.
>> Okay.
>> Does that make sense? He thinks he he he
Virgil said, "You're doing this for
everlasting fame." And now he's like,
"Well, I have everlasting fame, so I'll
just stay here." Okay?
But the everlasting fame what gives him
everlasting fame is the shadow. And we
know shadows are just illusions.
It doesn't make sense. And this happens
to this happens a lot where
Donny is slowing down because he wants
the fans to come and adore him. Okay, he
wants that everlasting fame.
And
where's Beatrice in his mind? It's like
she's kind of gone now, right?
He's like,
"Uh my choice is climb all the way up to
the Mount Purgatory and be with Beatrice
or stay here and be adored by my fans.
I'd rather be adored by my fans."
All right.
Does that make sense?
>> [clears throat]
>> Okay.
>> Line
22.
Meanwhile, along the slope crossing our
road slightly ahead of us, people
approached singing the Miserere verse by
verse. When they became aware that
allowed no path for rays of light to
cross my body, they changed their song
into a long horse. Oh.
>> Right. Do you see what's happening here,
right? These souls are committed to God.
You see Donny is like, "This is actually
more interesting than God, okay?"
Okay, go ahead.
>> And two of them serving as messengers
hurried to meet us and those two
inquired, "Please tell us something more
of what you are." My master answered
them, "You can return and carry this
report to those who sent you. In truth,
the body of this man is flesh. If as I
think they stopped to see his shadow,
that answer is sufficient. Let them
welcome him graciously and that may
profit them.
Never did I see kindled vapors rend
clear skies at nightfall or the setting
sun cleave August clouds with a rapidity
that matched the time it took these two
to speed above.
And there arrived they with the others
wheeled back like reins that run without
a rein. "These people pressing in on us
are many. They come beseeching you." the
poet said. "Don't stop, but listen as
you move ahead."
>> So, right, do you understand? He's being
mobbed by by his bands now, okay? And
that And Dante loves this.
I'm going
>> "Also, who make their way to gladness
with the limbs you had at birth, do stay
your steps a while." they clamored as
they came to see if there's any of us
whom you knew that you may carry word of
him beyond. "Why do you hurry on? Why
don't you stop? We all were done to
death by violence and we all sinned
until our final hour. Then light from
heaven granted understanding, so that
repenting and forgiving we came forth
from life at peace with God and he
instilled in us the longing to see him.
And I, although I scrutinize your faces,
I recognize no one, but spirits born of
goodness. If there's anything within my
power that might please you, then by
that same peace which in the steps of
such a guide I seek from world to world,
I shall perform it." And one began, "We
all have faith in your good offices
without your oath, as long as lack of
power does not curb your will.
Thus I, who speak alone before the
others, beseech you, if you ever see the
land that lies between Romania and the
that realm, the realm of Charles, that
you be courteous to me in treating those
in Fano to bestow fair prayers to purge
me of my heavy sins.
My home was Fano, but the piercing
wounds from which there poured the blood
where my life lived, those I received
among Antenor's son. There, where I
thought that I was most secure, for he
of Este, hating me far more than justice
warranted, had that deed done.
But had I fled instead of toward Mira
when they overtook me at Oriaco, then I
should still be beyond where men draw
breath. I hurried to the marsh, the mud,
the reeds entangled me. I fell, and
there I saw a pool poured from my veins
from on the ground.
>> Wait, sorry. So, let's stop. I want to
ask everyone a question, okay?
Can you become so famous
that it takes you it takes you to
heaven?
Let's Let's think think about this,
okay?
Will celebrities go to
heaven?
Yes?
>> Uh because the first commandment is you
shall have no other god before me, and
celebrities basically paint themselves
idols. They're like literally called
idols.
Um unless they are like, I don't know,
idols that points to god. Maybe. So,
then they become prophets instead of
idols. Uh like John the Baptist. Um but
so John the Baptist was also a celebrity
back then, but he points to Jesus, so
it's okay. Uh
yeah.
>> Okay. Um yes?
>> I guess we've got If you've got false
counselors in hell, then there can be
true counselors.
>> Mhm.
>> And so, you could be a famous true
counselor.
>> Right. Right. Like like me, right? Like
Like Like I'm on YouTube channel, and
I'm spreading wisdom.
Is this going to get me to heaven?
Please say yes.
I say I think so. But I think the answer
is no. Is that Is that actually going to
help me get to heaven?
Why not?
What gets you to heaven?
From If you're in purgatory, what gets
you
um up to heaven?
Uh yes?
>> Uh inspiring imagination. And maybe the
problem with celebrities and idols is
even if, say, the message is right,
people will blindly follow what they say
and not use their own imaginations.
>> Okay, sure. But again, I I I don't want
to praise myself too much, but I feel as
though my YouTube channel, I am
educating a lot of people and I am in by
teaching you I am increasing your
imagination, right?
So, I like to think that I would get
into heaven, but probably not. So, so
why not?
>> I think you'll be the same as all the
great thinkers who has, you know,
intellectual giants that we have
depended on before just like Virgil,
Socrates, Aristotle, Plato.
Uh
>> Yeah, I probably end up in limbo. Thank
you. Thank you. Yeah.
>> [laughter]
>> All right. Yeah.
Yes?
>> Because the journey to heaven is still
personal.
Uh fundamentally is is your journey of
self-improvement and self-reflection
that will bring you there. You can you
can still be a celebrity while doing it,
but you can you need to almost turn that
celebrity into something that helps
yourself improve as opposed to the other
way around.
>> So, how can I,
like, you know, get up to heaven faster?
>> I think uh in general the journey to
heaven or to purgatory or to hell really
start after a person complete his life's
journey.
So, until the person uh completes his
life's journey, there's no uh you know,
there's no start.
>> Okay.
How can I, like, give me some personal
advice, okay?
Yes? Yes?
>> If people pray for you, then it's going
to speed.
>> And who's going to pray for me?
>> We can.
>> Not you guys. No, not no.
My family, do you understand? Okay?
That's what I was saying here. This is
revolutionary, right? You can be as
famous as you want, you can have a
trillion dollars, you can be a massive
celebrity. It doesn't matter, okay? What
matters is your family. What matters are
your neighbors. What matters is your
community because these people are going
to pray for you
every single day with all their heart
and soul.
Yeah, I mean, your fans might now and
then and "Oh, you know, let's give a
prayer to Professor Chow." It doesn't
matter, okay? What matters is your You
have to put your heart and soul into
praying for someone, and only your
family would do that.
Okay? So, so that's what Dante is saying
here. Don't chase fame. Fame doesn't get
you anywhere.
Chase love. Chase family.
Okay? Be kind to the people around you,
and they will pray for you after you
die. Okay? Does it make sense?
All right, let's keep on reading.
>> Line 85.
Another shade then said, "Ah, so may
that desire which draws you up the lofty
mountain be granted with kind pity help
my longing. I was from Montefeltro. I'm
Buonconte. Giovanna and the rest, they
all neglect me. Therefore, among these
shades I go in sadness." And I to him,
"What violence or chance so dragged you
from the field of Campaldino that we
know nothing of your burial place."
"Oh," he replied, "across the Casentino
there runs a stream called Archiano,
born in the Apennines above the
hermitage. There, at the place where
that stream's name is lost, I came. My
throat was pierced fleeing on foot and
bloodying the plain. And there it was as
that I lost sight and speech. And there
as I finished I had finished uttering
the name of Mary, I fell. And there my
flesh alone remained. I'll speak the
truth. Do you among the living retell
it? I was taken by God's angel, but he
from hell cried, 'You from heaven, why
do you deny me him? For just one tear
carry off his deathless part, but I
shall treat his other part in
otherwise.' You were now in the air
moist vapor will gather and again revert
to rain as soon as it has climbed where
cold unfolds. His evil will, which only
seeks out evil conjoined with intellect
and with the power his nature grants, he
stirred up wind and vapor.
And then when day was gone, he filled
the valley from Pratomagno far as the
the ridge with mist. The sky above was
such saturated. The dense air was
converted into water, rain fell, and
then the gullies had to carry whatever
water earth could not receive. And when
that rain was gathered into torrents, it
rushed so swiftly toward the royal river
that nothing could contain its
turbulence.
The angry Archiano at its mouth had
found my frozen body, and it thrust it
into the Arno and set loose the cross
that on my chest my arms in pain had
formed. It rolled me on the banks and
riverbed that covered girded me with
this debris. Pray, after you're
returning to the world when after your
long journeying you've rested, the third
soul following the second said, "May you
remember me who am Lapa, Siena made
Maremma made me. He who when we were wet
gave me his pledge, and then as nuptial
ring his gem knows that."
>> So, these are souls who died in battle,
okay? And right now in history, a lot of
people are dying in battle. It's
basically gang warfare throughout Italy,
okay? Factional fighting, just endless
wars. And so, if you die in the
battlefield and you repent,
you're put in in purgatory. But, if you
die violently, you don't you you you you
don't even have a chance to repent,
you're still put in purgatory and you
have to wait a bit before you can move
on, okay? So, again, what Dante is
trying to emphasize is God is merciful
and God is just.
Okay, canto six.
>> When dice is thrown and players
separate, the loser's left alone
disconsolate. Rehearsing what he'd
thrown, he sadly learns all the crowd
surrounds the one who won. One goes in
front and one tugs at his back and at
his side one asked to be remembered. He
does not halt, but listens to them all
and when he gives them something they
desist. And so, he can and off the
pressing throng. And I in that
persistent pack was such, this way and
that I turned my face to them and making
promises escaped their clutch. There was
the Aretine who met his death beneath
Ghino de Tacco's beastly hands, and one
who drowned when in pursuit he ran.
There with his outstretched hands was
Federigo Novello praying and the Pisan
who made good Marzucco
who showed his fortitude. I saw Count
Orso and I saw the soul cleft from its
body out of spite and envy. Not it is So
it's said, because it had been guilty. I
mean Pierre de la Brosse, and may the
lady of Bra- Brabant, while she still
moves this world, watch her ways or end
among a sadder flock.
As soon as I was free from all those
shades who always pray for others'
prayers for them so as to reach their
blessed state more quickly, I started,
"O my light, it seems to me that in one
passage you deny expressly that prayer
can bend the will of heaven. Yet these
people pray precisely for that end. Is
their hope, therefore, only emptiness or
have I not read clearly what you said?"
>> Okay. So, what Dante is doing is he's
listing a lot of people from his real
life, okay? And it's a lot of people
from his real life.
Um we don't know who they are. He But he
knows who they are.
Why is he doing this? Why is he listing
so many people from his real life who
who died?
Why would he do that?
Uh yes?
>> Shakespearean way if I write you in poem
you live everlastingly. So that's one
thing to commemorate his peers and
friends.
>> Yes.
>> And then the other one is to console
their family for writing be like, "Hey,
by the way, your son is in purgatory,
you know, like don't be too sad."
>> Yeah, that's a great point. So So even
though we don't know who they are, his
readers will know who they are and
they're consoled by the fact that their
loved ones are in purgatory.
Um and so what's the effect of that? To
know that your loved one is in
purgatory, yes?
>> Yeah, to the widows and the mothers.
And the family.
>> Yes. And and and what what will they do
with their hope?
>> Pray really hard for them. Yeah.
>> It's It's It's making people live a life
of faith, hope, and love, right?
Because because
otherwise, they don't know where their
loved ones are. They could be They could
be They could be in hell. They could be
in heaven. So, without this hope, what
would they do?
Usually.
What What What are rich people people
doing at this time? You guys know?
That's That's That's exactly what
they're doing.
>> into corruption.
>> That's exactly what they're doing, okay?
They're They They don't know. They're
uncertain. So, they're going to give
huge bribes to the Catholic Church,
which as you point out, feeds the
corruption, which feeds us endless cycle
of violence, right? So, by saying,
"Don't worry. Your loved one is in
purgatory. Don't bribe the church. Pray
for this person."
Okay? Does that make sense?
>> Yeah.
>> All right. Okay. Let's Let's keep on
going.
>> [clears throat]
>> Line 34.
And he to me My text
>> Oh, sorry. Sorry. Sorry. Sorry. I I I
forgot, okay. All right. So,
Dante hears and knows that if you pray
if if you pray for a loved one enough,
this is This is going to
reduce the loved one's time in
purgatory. But we already But we already
said God is not transactional, right?
God
has perfect justice. You are You are
punished for the crime you committed.
If your loved ones are praying for you,
why should that matter? And what Dante
says to Virgil is, "Hey, in your Aeneid,
okay, you said very clearly
we mortals cannot at all impact the
decision of the gods.
We have actually no say
in this divine cosmos. So, what is it?
Okay? That's a question that Dante
asked Virgil. And like let's analyze
Virgil's response.
>> Line 34.
And he to me, "My text is plain enough,
and yet their hope is not delusive if
one scrutinizes it with sober wit. The
peak of justice is not lowered when the
fire flood accomplishes in one instant
the expiation owed by all who dwell
here. For where I asserted this, that
prayers cannot mend their fault, I spoke
of prayers without a passageway to God.
But in a quandary so deep, do not
conclude with me, but wait for word that
she, the light between your mind and
truth, will speak. Lest you
misunderstand, the she I mean is
Beatrice. Upon this mountain's peak,
there you shall see her smiling
joyously."
>> Okay, that is such a great response from
Virgil, okay? Dante is asking him, "Hey
Virgil, didn't you say in your text, in
the Aeneid, which is the Bible, right?
Um we cannot at all impact the decision
of the heavens."
And here in Purgatorio, we're seeing
clearly
prayers are lifting people up faster to
the heavens. So, what is it? And what is
Virgil's response? Can you paraphrase
paraphrase for me what he's saying here?
It's such a great response, and it shows
you so much into his character.
What does he say?
>> [clears throat]
>> Paraphrase for me his response.
Yes?
>> When I wrote it, prayers didn't work
like that.
>> Why not?
>> Because Jesus hadn't died or Mary had
not given birth to him.
>> That's right. So, this is So, I was
talking about the pagans, guys. This
This is Christian. You understand?
That's his first response, right?
Well, what I meant was the pagan world,
not the Christian world. Now, it's
different.
And what is the second response?
To me?
>> Ask Beatrice.
>> Yeah, don't bother me, man. Go Go talk
to Beatrice, okay? His two responses are
one, well,
it's different now because it's a
Christian world. And two, go talk to
Beatrice, okay?
So, So, why is Virgil responding the way
he is?
>> [snorts]
>> Again, this is different from Beatrice,
right? Where Beatrice will actually tell
you the answer.
Right?
W- What Yes?
He really doesn't want Dante to slow
down.
And just get involved with himself.
>> a You're such a generous, altruistic
person, man.
>> [laughter]
>> Y- Yes?
>> They're that authoritarian teacher is
like, "Shut up and move on, okay? Don't
question me. I'm your teacher." Kind of
just go shoo.
>> Like, if you ask someone these
questions, like questions says, "Well,
it's a different world now. And also, go
talk to another person."
Why would you think that person has to
respond the way that he or she wants
like has responded?
>> He just coping.
>> It's cope, yes, but it's also what?
>> Dodging the questions.
>> To me?
>> want to think about this. You
understand? He He doesn't want to think
about why this is happening.
Dante proposes a contradiction. He's
like, "Well, actually, there's a
loophole, okay?" He's He's like being a
lawyer here. He's trying to dodge the
question. He's trying to avoid the
question because he does not him him
himself does not want to reflect on
what's really going on.
Okay, he wants to maintain his
worldview, right? We talked yesterday
you fixed mindset versus growth mindset.
He's a fixed mindset.
Right?
Okay.
Uh let's keep on going.
>> And I Oh, actually line 49, and I, Lord,
let us move ahead more quickly for now
I'm less weary than before. And you can
see the slope now
cast
a shadow. As long as it is day, we'll
make as much headway as possible, he
answered, but our climb won't be as
rapid as you thought. You will not reach
the peak before you see the sun
returning. Now he hides behind the
hills, he cannot interrupt his flight.
>> Okay. So, Dante says, Lord, let us move
ahead more quickly for now I'm less
weary than before, and you
and you can see the slope now cast a
shadow.
Why is Dante less weary than before?
Yes?
>> Because he's left his fans behind.
But he's happy that he had fans.
>> [laughter]
>> Yeah, again you're so generous with
Dante. No.
Think think think like like Dante is a
really proud people person, yes?
Uh yeah, that's way too generous with
Dante.
Yeah.
Why is Dante really excited now?
Yes?
>> But he's like, I saw all the loopholes
that you make, and now I'm above you in
a way, intellectually.
>> No. What does Dante care the most about
right now?
>> He has to
progress his journey so that he can meet
more friends.
>> What did Donny see that makes him happy
now?
>> Said Donny himself.
>> No, no, no, no, guys, read the text. I'm
asking you a question. What did Donny
see? Yes?
>> The slope now cast a shadow.
>> Yes. What did he see now?
>> Shh. Well, people or
>> No, guys, what's he seeing now that's
like, "Wow, yes, great."
No, no, no, no, come on. What what's he
seeing right now? Literally.
>> The peak.
>> [laughter]
>> Literally, what's he seeing literally?
He sees what?
He's focused on this.
>> Maybe a friend. So, 61, we came to him
along by
>> No, no, no, no, no, no, you're jumping
ahead. I I just want to focus on these
three sentences, right?
What's he seeing now?
>> That the slope is easier.
>> [laughter]
>> This is so hard for you guys, okay? He
sees something that makes him really,
really happy and excited. What is it?
>> Darkness.
>> Let's keep on going, okay?
Let's go Huh?
Yeah, like you guys can't can't see it,
right? He sees it and makes him really,
really happy.
>> He chooses.
>> Okay, let's read it again, okay? There's
only like so many possibilities here.
And you got I I just want something he
sees here that makes him really, really
happy. Yes?
>> The slope cast a shadow.
>> But what does he see?
>> A It's got
light casting a shadow on something
other than himself.
>> Guys, visualize this. What is he seeing
right now? What's he focused on right
now?
>> The knot. align 46 47. This
>> No, no, no, no, I'm
let's just focus on on these three
lines.
>> The what three lines?
>> Three lines.
>> Oh, 49 and 51. Sorry. So, can you read
it again for everyone? 49 and 51.
Sorry.
>> [clears throat]
>> And I, Lord, let us move ahead more
quickly. For now, I am less weary than
before. And you can see the slope now
cast a shadow.
>> What does he see?
>> Is it that purgatory is real to him now?
>> [laughter]
>> No, what does he like literally see
right now?
>> Another shadow.
>> He sees a shadow and he's really happy
about it. Why?
>> Because he's he's also still in the cave
mentally.
>> Right? So, so why is he happy to see the
shadow? What what what what's going to
happen now?
>> Maybe another friend.
>> He's going to chase the shadow.
>> Right?
Right. So, so this is
what's happening is he sees a shadow and
so what so what he knows
so what is happening what what's going
to happen now once the once the shadow
is cast?
He's being mobbed by his fans again,
right?
You understand? So, that's what makes
him excited. Not Beatrice, not God, not
the slope, not purgatory. He's like,
"Screw all that. I want my shadow, man.
That's what I care about."
Okay? Every time I cast a shadow, people
are going to run up to me and say, "Hey,
can I have your autograph?"
So, he's become addicted to his own
fame.
Do you understand the idea here? Okay?
He's narcissistic.
He's like, "All I care about is my
shadow now. I don't
Like forget Beatrice, forget heaven. I
care about my shadow. That's it, okay?"
>> [snorts]
>> And this is also true for people who are
celebrities today, right? All they care
about is their fame.
Right?
If you're a social media influencer,
what's the only thing you care about?
Exactly, right? The metrics. The number
of subscriptions you you have, the um
amount of views you get.
Right? That's all you care about. And
you're always like, how do I get more
of these subscriptions? And so what
happens eventually to some?
Yes?
>> Diet consumed by us, so then they are
eaten alive, so then they do all kinds
of extreme outrageous things.
>> Yeah.
>> Because blood and gore is what sells the
newspapers, so then you at the end turn
into destruction of yourself.
>> Yeah, I mean like I mean there's so many
examples, right? Of social media
influencers who kill themselves or who
do outrageous things to attract
attention. Because like they all they
care about are the ratings, okay?
Right? So so that's what
uh Dante is saying here, like
fame makes you egotistical,
narcissistic, and it's an empty life,
okay? Because like literally all he
cares about now is his shadow, okay?
Which is just an illusion.
Right? That doesn't make sense to you
guys?
All right. Uh let's let's keep on
reading.
>> [clears throat]
>> 52.
As long as it is day we'll make as much
headway as possible, he answered, but
our climb won't be as rapid as you
thought. You will not reach the peak
before you see the sun returning. Now he
hides behind the hills. You cannot
interrupt his light, but see beyond a
soul who is completely apart and seated
looking toward us. He will show us where
to climb most speedily. We came to him,
O Lombard soul, what pride and what
disdain were in your stance. Your eyes
moved with such dignity, such gravity.
He said no thing to us, but let us pass.
His eyes intent upon us only as a lion
watches when it is at rest. Yet Virgil
made his way to him, appealing to him to
show us how we'd best ascend, and he did
not reply to that request, but asked us
what our country was and who we were. At
which my gentle guide began, "Mantua."
And that spirit who had been so solitary
rose from his position saying, "Oh,
Mantuan, I'm Sordello from your own
land." And each embraced the other.
>> Okay. So, uh Virgil has met another
poet, Sordello, who's actually a very
important poet. He is something called a
troubadour, which is a love poet, uh a
poet of the courtly love tradition,
okay?
Uh and they're both from from the same
place, and so they embrace each other.
And you can see how happy and
enthusiastic Virgil is to meet someone
from
um the same area. Like keep keep on
going?
>> Line 76. Uh object, Italy, your you in
of sorrows. You ship without a helms-
helms- helmsman in harsh seas, no queen
of provinces, but of bordellos. That
noble soul had such enthusiasm, his
city's sweet name was enough for him to
welcome there his fellow citizen. But
those who are alive within you now can't
live without their warring, even those
whom one same wall and one same moat and
close not each other. Squalid Italy,
search around your shores and then look
inland. See if any part of you delight
in peace. What use was there in a
Justinian's mending your bridle when the
saddle's empty? Indeed, was there no
reins your shame were less? Ah, you who
have you understood what God ordained
and would then attend to things devout,
and in the saddle surely would allow
Caesar to sit. See how this beast turns
fears because there no spurs that would
correct it, since you have laid your
hands upon the bit.
Oh, German Albert, you who have
abandoned that steed become recalcitrant
and savage. You who should ride astride
its saddle bow bows, upon your blood may
the just judgment of the stars descend
with signs so strange and plain that
your successor has to feel its terror.
For both you and your father and your
greed for lands that lay more close at
hand allowed the garden of the empire to
be gutted. Come, you who pay no heed, do
come and see Monaldi Capelletti set
already and filled with fear Monaldi
Filippeschi.
Come, cruel one, come see the
tribulation of your nobility and heal
their hurts and see and how disconsolate
it's Santa Fiore. Come see your Rome who
widowed and alone weeps bitterly both
day and night. She moans, "My Caesar,
why are you not at my side?" Come see
how much your people love each other and
if no pity for us moves you, may shame
for your own repute move you to act.
And if I am allowed, oh highest Jove, to
ask, you who on earth were crucified for
us, have you turned elsewhere your just
eyes? Or are you in your judgment step
devising a good that we cannot see
completely disjoined from our way of
understanding? For all the towns of
Italy are full of tyrants and each
townsman who becomes a partisan is soon
a new Marcellus.
My Florence, you indeed may be content
that this digression would leave you
exempt. Your people striving spare you
this lament. Others have justice in
their hearts and thought is slow to let
it fly off from their bow, but your folk
keep it ready on their lips. Others
refuse the weight of public service,
whereas your people eagerly respond.
Even an ass will shout, "I'll take it
on." You might be happy now for you have
cause. You with your riches, peace,
judiciousness. If I speak truly, facts
won't prove me wrong. Compared to you,
Athens and Lacedaemon,
those civil cities with their ancient
laws had merely sketched the life of
righteousness. For you devised
provisions so ingenious, whatever
threats October sees you spin, when
mid-November comes will be unspun. How
often in the time you can remember have
you changed laws and coinage, offices,
and customs, and revised your citizens?
And if your memory has some clarity,
then you will see yourself like that
sick woman who finds no rest upon her
feather bed, but turning, tossing, tries
to ease her pain.
>> Okay, so let's kind of split it into two
parts, okay? The first part, we see the
vanity of Dante, right? All he cares
about is his shadow, because the shadow
is bringing him everlasting fame where
he is.
But in the second half of the canto,
Dante goes on this lament about Italy.
Uh it's it's returning to the prophetic
tradition where he is
um saying that Italy is full of of sin,
um and he's being very sarcastic
sarcastic about all this. He's being
very ironic.
And
um he's almost appealing to divine
justice and saying that Italy um is
terrible, it's full of sin, it's like
Sodom and Gomorrah.
And so, how can we explain this
uh dichotomy,
right? On one hand, he is just focused
on his fame, his shadow. But on the
other hand, he goes on this lament
about uh the fate of Italy, yes?
>> I think because he's thinking what good
could my fame ever do other than
change Italy? And he's using this as an
opportunity. He's thinking about, well,
I'm famous now.
It's going to be a meta thing to the
reader. Speaking of fame, what should a
good famous person do but instruct his
nation?
>> Yeah, okay.
Anyone else?
Yes?
>> I think also that he's talking about how
he feels the pull of fame even in his
self, but there are people he's talking
about that are even beyond that when
they're not even asked to
to do something, they just try and gain
power immediately.
>> Who's your favorite celebrity?
Like a movie star or like
um
>> I just tried to ditch all of them for
Jesus because they all had flaws.
>> Okay, does anyone have a celebrity that
they worship or whatever?
What are they like? Yes?
>> Kanye West.
>> Yep.
Okay.
All right. So, why do you What what what
does Kanye West say about the world that
allows you to admire him?
>> Uh not not necessarily about his opinion
on the world. Um
I admire him because he There's There's
a saying of him uh is
um we're just
what what what what what we do
um
We we should be
We we
uh how should I phrase this? Um
Basically, he's telling us to
be who we are and to
uh embrace us ourselves.
Be be more uh courageous. Yeah.
>> Okay. So, you admire him for his songs
which deliver a message of courage and
uh hope. Okay? Yes?
>> I would say uh Kanye pretty much shares
the same
uh perspective with Dante on on the on
world.
Uh like
um
choose love over fear, like be fearless,
and always be
certain, like be always be certain about
who you are and like what your impact on
the world, right? And be uh be
imaginative, right?
>> Are you at all concerned at all about
his personal life, the fact that, you
know, he marries and divorces, and he
seems to pay no attention to his kids.
Are you at all concerned about his
personal life?
>> I'm pretty much concerned about his
personal life but and
uh I don't think I
it it doesn't seems good to me but
uh
besides those his personal life I think
he still sticks sticks to himself.
And he's
pretty much hadn't changed a bit
uh among all this chaos and
and uh yeah.
>> Okay. All right. Okay, so this is hard,
okay? Um but I want to uh
uh bring up an idea that we learn in
Paradise which is there is the
absolute will.
Absolute will is just what you believe
and who you are, okay? Your absolute
will, who you are, what you believe,
what your ideal state is. And then
there's the contingent will, okay? We
learned this in Paradise. Contingent
will.
Which is what you choose to do.
Okay? The example is Piccarda.
Because Piccarda is a just
um person who's devoted to God, right?
She is a princess and she's like, "I
don't want to participate in this world
of politics. I want to go to a nunnery
and devote my myself to God." That's the
absolute will.
The contingent will are the choices you
make in your life.
And so when her brother sent soldiers to
kidnap her from the from the convent,
she did not resist. She went with them,
okay?
So, this is something to to keep in mind
as we continue to read Dante. There is a
difference, okay? There's difference
between what you believe
and what you say and what you do.
Okay? So, yes, so he is very much
concerned about the fate of the world.
But at the same time, Dante is obsessed
with his fame.
And And this is not necessarily a a
contradiction. And in life, what what
we're trying to do is align the two,
right? The alignment of the soul. And
that's hard to do.
Okay?
All right.
All right. So, let's go let's go to the
next um canto.
Okay, sorry sorry sorry sorry. Before we
begin, I I I I want I want you like
think about this.
So, Dante
is obsessed with his shadow because it's
what's bringing him all the all this
attention, okay? And so, he's slowing
down. He's looking for like wherever his
shadow is, okay? And he gets really
excited when he sees when he sees his
shadow. It's almost like like a drug
now, okay?
And
How does Virgil feel about all this?
What is going in the mind of Virgil as
he's seeing this?
Anyone?
Yes?
>> I can't believe that Beatrice sent me
for this guy.
>> Yeah, that's right. He's like
What a douchebag this guy is. Right?
What a douchebag. Okay, what else?
Uh yes?
Yeah.
>> Um maybe Virgil is happy.
>> How? Virgil is happy, why?
>> Because um he finally corrupted um uh uh
>> Yeah, like I I told him to do things for
everlasting fame. Now, he's doing what I
want. So, now and so now I control him.
Yeah. No, no, that's that's not how
Virgil thinks.
What is Virgil's major emotion right
now?
It's kind of frustration, right? Like,
what a douchebag this guy is. But what
else? What what's the major emotion you
would feel if you were Virgil?
>> [snorts]
>> Impatience, right? He's telling
Dante him up, yes?
>> A little bit of jealousy.
>> I I think jealousy. Right? I think if I
were Virgil I I I'd be very jealous
about this.
Okay?
Does that make sense?
Okay.
All right, so
remember where we are, where Dante is
now obsessed with his shadow and
Virgil's like, "Oh my god, what a
douchebag." And like he And so he
So Virgil wants to move as fast as as
possible, right?
Okay.
Okay, uh let's let's continue reading.
>> Canto seven.
When glad and gracious welcomings had
been repeated three and four times, then
Sordello drew himself back and asked,
"But who are you?" "Before the spirits
worthy of ascent to God had been
directed to this mountain, my bones were
buried by Octavian. I'm Virgil and I'm
deprived of heaven for no fault other
than my lack of faith. This was the
answer given by my guide."
>> Okay. Um
we we know Virgil is lying here. What is
false about
what he just said?
>> [snorts]
>> Sordello asked him, "Who are you?" And I
think "I'm Virgil."
"And I'm deprived of heaven for no fault
other than my lack of faith." Where's
the lie?
Yes?
>> I'll deprive of heaven because of his
lack of faith. It's his active
um ego that he chose to be
>> Okay. So we know it's a lie, okay? And
how do we know it's a lie?
The first fact is a lie. And how And how
do we know?
We know it's a lie. He may not know,
yes?
>> Because he could never have made it to
heaven uh because he was born before
uh
Mary gave birth to Jesus. So
he was never going to make it anyway. He
was always going to end up in limbo.
>> Well, that's what Virgil believes, but
we know it's a lie. Why?
We know for a fact it's a lie.
>> We say because he betrayed God through
his work.
>> No, no, no, no, no. I'm saying like we
know for a fact it's a lie because of
what evidence?
>> Pagans in Pagans in purgatory.
>> But how do we know that?
>> Cato.
>> Cato, do you understand?
We know this is a lie because we just
saw Cato in purgatory.
And Cato we know for a fact is a pagan.
And Cato was like, "Oh,
I'm a Christian now." No, no, he's like,
"I'm still Cato."
Okay, so we know this is a lie.
Right?
Does Virgil know he's lying here?
We know it's a lie.
But does he know it's a lie?
No, no, I'm saying does Virgil know it's
a lie?
Right?
>> I think he should.
>> Uh I I think he he don't.
>> He doesn't know it know it's a lie?
Yeah?
>> It's hard not to know what is a lie
because he met Cato. He talked to him
and
>> [clears throat]
>> stuff. You know, he's like, "You're the
other me and why are you here and I'm
not?" Like, "Hello."
>> We had this major encounter between Cato
and Virgil. It's It's a very
embarrassing, awkward encounter, right?
So how could Virgil not know he's lying?
That's exactly it. Cognitive dissonance,
okay? That That's the idea here. Okay?
Again, what's amazing is
cognitive dissonance, right?
What's amazing is that this is written
in the 14th century and already
Dante knows about moral psychology,
right? This is cognitive dissonance. And
what is cognitive dissonance?
>> Psychology, so you hold on to your own
world view because you you can't let it
shatter. You it's too much to you.
>> All right, do you guys understand? So,
uh
did you want to add to that?
>> Yes. So, when you hear something that
someone else is else says that is
different to your own perception of the
worldview, you feel uncomfortable.
>> No, no, it's not you don't feel you
don't feel it No, no, you don't feel
uncomfortable. What What do you do?
You reject it, you understand, okay? So,
what's happening is
Virgil had this encounter with with
Cato. It was so traumatic for him that
he just blocked it out. He doesn't
remember
this encounter. He doesn't remember
Cato.
Uh
did you want to say something?
>> Yeah, I was uh
just recently I had looked at the the
definitions and etymological origins of
a
a an illusion and a delusion. An
illusion is like a magic trick and your
mind's like, "Oh, that's not real, but
you know it's not real." And a delusion
is when you accept it into your whole
essence.
>> Right, exactly, okay? So, that's what
This This is a really interesting what's
happening, right? Where Virgil goes to
purgatory for the first time,
meets Cato, knows for a fact now that
pagans are allowed access to purgatory,
and he's like, "Screw this."
>> [laughter]
>> I don't I don't And he forgets about it.
And it's like
forever blocked from his memory.
Okay?
So, this reveals so much about his
character and his motivations, right?
All right.
Um
let's keep on going.
>> Line 10. Even like one who suddenly has
seen something before him, and then
marveling dust and does not believe
saying,
"It is is not." So did Sordello seem.
And then he bent his brow, returned to
Virgil humbly, and clasped him where the
lesser presence clasps. He said, "Oh,
glory of the Latins, you through whom
our tongue revealed its power, you
eternal honor of my native city, what
merit or what grace shows you to me? If
I deserve to hear your word, then
answer. Tell me if you're from hell and
from what cloister."
Through every circle of the sorry
kingdom, he answered him, "I journeyed
here. A power from heaven moved me, and
with that I come. Not for the having,
but not having done I lost the sight
that you desired, the sun. That high sun
I was late in recognizing. There's a
place below that only shadows, not
torments, have assigned to sadness.
There a lament is not an outcry, but a
sigh. There I am with the infant
innocence, those whom the teeth of death
had ceased before they were set free
from human sinfulness.
There I am with those souls who were not
clothed in the three holy virtues, but
who knew and followed after all the
other virtues. And if you know and
you're able to, would you point out the
path that leads more quickly to the true
entry point of purgatory?"
>> Okay, sorry. So, but let's let's let's
feel out this, okay? So, Sordello says,
"Oh my god, you are him. You are the
Virgil."
Um and how and so like
Sordello humbles himself before uh
Virgil. He basically bows down to
Virgil. And and how does Virgil feel
about this?
How does Virgil feel about this?
>> Bittersweet.
>> Bittersweet. Again, you're so generous.
Uh
not bittersweet.
No.
Just happy. He's ecstatic, okay? He can
be happier in his life. Why?
Why can't he be happier in his life?
Yeah?
>> I mean, he's gained he seems to have got
a taste of the fame even though know,
has no shadow and that
his achievements in life seem to have
raised him above the state, and that the
guy still really loves him, even though
he asked, "Are you from hell?" And he
goes, "Yeah, kind of, but" and the guy's
like, "Oh my god, I still really love
him."
>> What is Virgil really pissed off about
right now?
What is Virgil not happy about right
now?
Yeah?
>> Uh he he's he's pissed off for the
Dante. Seems like Dante has gained more
fame over him.
>> Yes.
Exactly, right? He's pissed about the
Dante. Like, why is Dante more famous
here than I am? And now, he meets
someone like, "Oh, you're more famous
than Dante." And Virgil's like, "Oh,
yes, I am, okay?"
And how do we know he is ecstatic? Let's
let's let's read his speech, okay? And
tell me what in his speech tells us he
is ecstatic.
>> Through every Sorry.
>> Uh sorry.
>> Uh
>> But line 22.
>> Okay.
Line 22.
Through every circle of the sorry
kingdom, he answered him, "I journeyed
here. A power from heaven moved me, and
with that, I come. Not for the having,
but not having done, I lost the sight
that you desired, the sun. That high sun
I was late in recognizing. There's a
place below that only shadows, not
torments, have assigned to sadness.
There a lament is not an outcry, but a
sigh. There I am with the infant
innocence, those whom the teeth of death
had ceased before they were set free
from human sinfulness. There I'm with
those souls who were not clothed in the
three holy virtues, but who knew and
followed after all the other virtues."
>> Okay, so he's ecstatic, and we know
because of his speech. What is
interesting about about about his speech
here?
You guys analyze language, yes?
>> The first point that jumps out is that
he says he is in the other virtues, so
that
he didn't have the three key ones, but
that he is
very much exemplifying all the others in
his life.
>> Yeah, so if you're really happy, you you
tend to like boast about yourself,
right? It's like
look how great I am. Yes, okay, that's
that's one thing. Yes, what else?
Yeah?
>> When he talks about his traveling
through the circles, he doesn't mention
Dante or the mission, he just says it's
a power of heaven. He said that I came
up through the circles. I came
>> a focus of all the attention, right? He
forgets to say but before he was like
okay, well, I'm helping guy Dante
through
uh
hell and purgatory. But now he's just
like me, me, me. Okay? Again, that's if
you're really ecstatic, you just focus
on yourself, right?
What else?
Again, this this is different from his
other speeches. Okay?
Uh yes.
Well,
I lost the sight that you desired the
>> sun that high sun
the high sun I was late in recognizing,
so
in a way he now does recognize the the
Christian God basically and
he he also recognizes that he
he's wrong or he was wrong.
before.
No, he's not That's not That's not what
he's doing here actually, okay? Uh yes?
>> I think he's beautifying the places that
he he is at and he's trying to kind of
Photoshop it. Like lament is not a
outcry but a sigh and I'm with the
innocent and it's just too bad I died
before, you know, Jesus came. It's not
really my fault.
>> He's using a lot of adjectives, okay?
He He is exaggerating. He's He's making
He's creating like this opulent, flowery
language and that's different from his
speeches before where he was very terse,
very short, okay? Very brief and to the
point. Now he's just
like look, um like trying to show off
his poetry to understand what he's
trying to impress someone.
>> Yeah, it's full of
simile and metaphor
and he's making himself an angel almost.
>> Yeah. Bragging, he's trying to impress.
Yes.
>> Yeah.
>> One more thing or there are more, yes?
>> He also mentioned that in hell there
full of shadows. So, this
is him saying that the fact that Dante
has shadows behind him is not a great
deal.
>> That is very clever. Yes, I didn't see
that. But that's exactly correct. Yes,
he's like why you guys like
like like focus on his shadow? There's
shadows everywhere in hell, man. Right?
He's still pissed about Dante. Exactly.
Yes, thank you thank you for that. Yes.
Anyone else?
Okay, and yes?
Yes?
>> I thought the infant innocents go to
parties.
>> Oh no, no, no.
It depends on the situation.
Most infants go to limbo, but there are
some parents who pray for the infant and
who do so many good deeds that their
actions help the infants ascend to
heaven. Okay?
Okay, so those are special cases.
Okay, yeah. I will also point out that
he uses he uses I a lot, right? I and he
also this is actually pretty long by the
standards of Virgil's speeches. Okay, so
it just shows you how ecstatic he is
that finally someone finally recognizes
him and knows he's better than Dante.
>> It takes up six stanzas.
>> Yeah.
>> Compared to all his shorter verses.
>> Yeah, yeah. He's usually very very
terse. Yes, I keep on going.
>> Line 40, he answered, "No fixed place
has been assigned to us. I'm free to
range about and climb. As far as I may
go, I'll be your guide. But see now how
the day declines, by night we cannot
climb and therefore it is best to find
some pleasant place where we can rest.
Here to the right are spirits set apart.
If you allow me, I shall lead you to
them and not without delight you'll come
to know them. How is that? He was asked.
Is it that he who tried to climb by
night would be impeded by others or his
own lack of power? And good Sordello, as
his finger traced along the ground,
said, "Once the sun has set, then look,
even this line cannot be crossed." And
not that anything except the dark of
night prevents her climbing up, it is
the night itself that implicates your
will. Once darkness falls, one can
indeed retreat below and wander
aimlessly about the slopes while the
horizon has enclosed the day. At which
my lord, as if in
in wonder, said, "Lead us then to there
where, as you say, we may derive delight
from this night's day."
>> Okay, so there's a very particular
particular rule to Purgatory, which is
like once it's night, you can't move
anymore or you can't cross certain
boundaries anymore, okay?
Why would they have this rule in
Purgatory? You don't have this in hell.
You don't have this in heaven. Why would
you have it in Purgatory?
Uh yes, you you then you, okay?
>> Tainting a real place like as it is on
Earth. So, if you're traveling on Earth
back then in Middle Ages, you can't.
>> Okay, so it's really imitate the real
world as much as possible. Uh what else?
>> I was going to say something similar,
but I also think that
other than imitating the real world,
it you're basically trying to purge your
shadow, so
in in the mystic world of Purgatory,
it's pretty difficult to know where
you would try and chase if you were like
trying to cleanse yourself if there
there [snorts] was no light at all to be
a reference.
>> Okay, okay, okay. All right, let's let's
be very simple about this, okay?
In the day,
they're walking, right?
And these souls are so excited that at
night, if they could, they walk would
walk as well.
And so they have this rule, which is
like at night you cannot proceed any
further, okay? You cannot advance your
progress.
This is very strange because you would
think that the the very very idea of
purgatory is to encourage you to expiate
your sins as as fast as possible. So,
why would they have this rule? Um you
cannot advance during the night. Yes?
>> It's maybe a moment for people to
self-reflect.
>> Yes. Why?
>> Like because you don't move, then you're
just thinking about where you are, why
you are there, and then what's going on.
>> well, if it's night and you can't move,
what are you doing?
>> You're
like talking to people, imagining, oh
yeah, dreaming. Talked about it.
>> sleeping, right? When you sleep, what
happens? You dream, right? Do you
understand?
The And you're you're right. The the
entire point of purgatory is to cause
self-reflection.
And one way to to
provoke self-reflection is just to have
the guy sleep, man, you know?
Because when you sleep, you dream, and
your dreams reveal things to you that
you couldn't know before. Does that make
sense?
Okay? So, the entire point of purgatory
is to force self-reflection.
And that's what's
And that's what what makes it different
from hell.
But there are different ways in which
you can force self-reflection, right?
So, one way is through the discussion
that the
But another way is through dreaming,
okay?
And what's another way to force
self-reflection?
Can you guys guess?
Dreaming, sleeping is a way to force
self-reflection, right?
Talking with other people is another
way. But there But there's also other
ways. And what are they?
>> Seeing someone else do the actions that
you do.
>> Yes, that's right. Yes, good. What else?
>> Worshipping, praying.
>> Yes, exactly. And they do worship and
pray here. Yes.
What else?
Yes?
>> Abstinence from things. So,
any kind of
indulgence or process that you do,
just taking it away and seeing what is
left in the void of your life.
>> Okay. All right. So, yeah, that that
that's correct, okay? But I want more
common things, okay? So, sleeping is one
way.
And then another way is?
>> Do people ever take a step back in
purgatory? There Is it Is it a bee line
one step in front of the other, always
progress? Cuz I self-reflect when I fail
or I have a shortcoming.
>> Sure, sure. Yes. So, so they will be
forced to like stand still and and fail.
Yes, okay? But but but and
what is the really common way in society
that forces our self-reflection?
>> Maybe walking.
>> Excuse me?
>> Maybe take a walk.
>> Uh yes.
You learn from mistakes, yes?
>> Writing, maybe.
>> Writing, yes. But what's causing all
this?
>> Like like reading or kind of go to class
or
something.
>> Okay, okay, okay, okay, okay. Um we're
running out of time, okay? But art,
guys. Art.
A R T.
Art.
Does it make sense to you?
When you go When you go to a museum and
you see all these paintings,
when you hear great music,
when you watch a great movie, it forces
self-reflection on you, right? Does it
make sense? So, dreaming,
artwork,
okay? And we'll see a lot of artwork in
purgatory.
All right. Uh let's keep on going.
>> Line 64. We had not gone far off when I
perceived that just as valleys hollow
mountains here in our world, so that
mountain there was hollowed. That shade
said, "It is there that we shall go to
where the slope forms of itself a lap.
At that place we'll await the day's
coming." There was a slanting path, now
steep, now flat. It led us to a point
beside the valley, just where its
bordering edge had dropped by half. Gold
and fine silver, cochineal,
white lead, and Indian lignite, highly
polished, bright, fresh emerald at fresh
emerald at the moment it is dampened. If
placed within that valley, all would be
defeated by the grass and flowers'
colors, just as the lesser gives way to
the greater, and nature there not only
was a painter, but from the sweetness of
a thousand odors, she had derived an
unknown, mingled scent. Upon the green
grass and the flowers, I saw seated
spirits singing Salve Regina. They were
not visible from the outside.
>> Okay, and also nature as well, right?
You have or you also have nature. Okay,
keep on going.
>> Before the meager sun seeks out its
nest, began the man who showed who led
us here, "Do not ask me to guide you
down among them. From this bank you'll
be better able to make out the acts and
features of them all than if you were to
join them in the hollow. He who is
seated highest with the look of one too
lax in what he undertook, whose mouth,
although the rest sing, does not move,
was Emperor Rudolph, one who could have
healed the wounds that were the death of
Italy, so that another later must
restore her. His neighbor, whose
appearance comforts him, governed the
land in which are born the waters of
Moldau, carries to the Elbe, and the
Elbe to the sea, named Ottokar. In
swaddling bands, he was more valiant
than his son, the bearded Wenceslas, who
feeds on wantonness and ease. That
small-nosed man who seemed so close in
council with his kindly friend died in
flight, deflowering the lily. So, see
how he beats his breast there, and you
see the other shade, who, as he sighs,
would rest his cheek upon his palm as on
a bed. Father and father-in-law of the
past of France, They know his life. It's
filled its flights out of that knowledge
grows the grief that has pierced them.
That other who seems so robust and sings
in time with him who has a nose so manly
wore the cord of every virtue. And if
the young man seated there behind him
had only followed him as king, then
valor might have been poured from vessel
into vessel. One cannot say this of his
other heirs. His kingdom's now belong to
James and Frederick, but they do not
possess his best bequest. How seldom
human worth ascends from branch to
branch and this is willed by him who
grants that gift. That one
That one may pray to him for it. My
words suggest the large-nosed one no
less than they refer to Peter singing
with him whose heir brings Puglia and
Provence distress.
The plant is lesser than its seed just
as the man whom Beatrice and Margaret
wed is lesser than the husband Constance
has. You see the king who led the simple
life seated alone, Henry of England. He
has better fortune with his progeny. He
who seated low is on the ground and
looking up is William the Marquis the
Marquis. For him both Alexandria and its
war make Montferrato and Canavese mourn.
>> Okay, so these are monarchs, right? Uh
and again, they're in purgatory. They're
waiting
until they've made their penance and
they're ready to climb uh purgatory,
okay?
All right, this is going to be uh
purgatory eight.
>> Canto eight. It was the hour that turns
seafarers' longings homeward, the hour
that makes their hearts grow tender upon
the day they bid sweet friends farewell.
The hour that pierces the new traveler
with love when he has heard far off the
bell that seems to mourn the dying of
the day. When I began to let my hearing
fade and watch one of those souls who
having risen had signaled with his hand
for attention. He joined his palms and
lifting them he fixed all his attention
on the east as if to say to God, I care
for nothing else. Te lucis ante
issued from his lips with such devotion
and with notes so sweet that I was moved
to be moved beyond my mind. And then the
other spirits followed him devoutly
gently through all of that hymn their
eyes intent on the supernal spheres.
Here reader, let your eyes look sharp at
truth for now the veil has grown so very
thin. It is not difficult to pass
within. I saw that company of noble
spirits silent and looking upward pale
and humble as of an expectation and I
saw emerging and ascending from above
two angels bearing flaming swords of
which the blades were broken off without
their tips.
Their garments just as green as newborn
leaves were agitated fanned by their
green wings and trailed behind them and
one angel came and stood somewhat above
us while the other descended on the
opposite embankment flanking that
company of souls between them.
My eyes made out their blond heads
clearly but my sight was dazzled by
their faces just like any sense
bewildered by excess.
Both come from Mary's bosom said
Sordello to serve as custodians of the
valley against the serpent that will
soon appear.
At this not knowing where its path might
be frozen with fear I turned around
pressing close to the trusty shoulders
and Sordello continued, let us now
descend among the great shades in the
valley. We shall speak with them and
seeing you they will be pleased. I think
that I had taken but three steps to go
below when I saw one who watched
attentively trying to recognize me. The
hour had now arrived when air grows dark
but not so dark that it deprived my eyes
and his of what before they were denied.
He moved toward me and I advanced toward
him. Noble Judge Nino, what delight was
mine when I saw you were not among the
damned.
>> Okay, all right. So one last question
and then we'll take a break, okay? So,
um clearly there are references to the
Garden of Eden.
Um because if you read Genesis, what
happens is we we get banished from the
Garden of Eden and there are two angels
with flaming swords that now watch over
the Garden of Eden to bar entry.
Um
what are the two angels doing here?
Did you guys spot that?
What What are the two angels doing? They
have flaming swords.
What are they doing?
>> They answer the valley against the
serpent.
>> Yeah. So, what what what what does that
mean?
They're they're they're protecting the
mountain from the devil, right? From the
snake. And what does that mean?
What What What What does that mean?
Yes?
>> That even in self-reflection, the devil
can come in.
Or that
in like this is a place of art of
looking at great people of history for
Dante,
um but he's been reminded that
this is not a place safe from all evil
and that there's still temptation and
trouble.
>> Sure. Yes, that's right. The snake will
always be there, okay? The The snake is
eternal, yes?
Um okay, let's just say that you we're
all going to Purgatory, okay?
Um
and we see these angels.
What would our first fear be? Oh, sorry.
Um we'd be afraid, right? Because we
think these angels, what are they doing
here?
>> They're safeguarding
Purgatory from from evil. But so so if
I'm going through the gate, right? I I
see these angels, I'd be worried that
they might stop me.
>> Yes, right? Right? Because Genesis, the
Bible told us that these angels are to
are to protect the Garden of Eden.
Which means what now?
Which means what?
What what what is it saying? Why is
there a snake here?
What what what what what is the snake
trying trying to go?
>> Because we are in the Garden of Eden
right now.
>> Okay. So, the first idea is there is a
Garden of Eden, and that's where the
snake is trying to go, right? Okay? So,
the Garden of Eden is actually on top of
Mount Purgatory, okay?
But, what But, if you're But, you again,
if you're Christian, you're kind of
surprised by all this. Why?
Why would you be surprised to hear there
are two angels guarding it, a snake
in Purgatory? Yes?
I don't know if this is
>> my Paradise Lost knowledge talking, but
I thought that Satan comes into a snake
who's in the Garden of Eden already. He
doesn't have to make a journey through
any other places. So, you'd be confused
that
the snake has to
do anything to get in there.
>> Right. So, so remember, we are now in
the future, right? So, what's happened
is Adam and Eve were tempted by the
snake, and they ate the fruit, and now
they've been banished from And they were
banished from
the Garden of Eden.
And so, why would this all be surprising
for us?
Yes?
>> Uh maybe because uh people just feel
fear, you know? So, they don't want to
die, and uh they just want to live. And
this kind of fear and and desire and the
>> If you're Christian, yes?
>> After Jesus died for our sins, are we
allowed to go back to the Garden of
Eden? We're allowed to go back now,
guys.
Okay?
It's open now.
The angels are there not to bar our
entry, they're there to
bar the snake from entry.
We're allowed to go in now.
Right?
Were you taught this in Christian
school?
And it makes sense logically, right? If
Jesus died for our sins,
and we're now redeemed in the eyes of
God,
theoretically, we should be allowed back
in the Garden of Eden. Right? And that's
what Dante's saying here.
If it is true that we're redeemed, then
the Garden of Eden should be open,
right? And who redeemed us from our
sins?
Not Jesus. Mary. And how And how And how
do we know that?
Because Virgil tells us.
No, no, no. No, no, no. I'm saying in
the text, how do we know that?
>> Mary's bosom.
>> The angels.
>> The Mary the
angels come from Mary's bosom, right?
Mary redeemed us, and so she They came
from our heart to protect us as we enter
the Garden of Eden.
Okay, does that make sense?
Okay, this is the cosmology of Dante. If
Mary redeemed us, if Mary redeemed us,
then we're allowed to back to go back to
the Garden of Eden.
Okay?
All right. Uh
okay. So, um any questions about this?
Yes?
>> Is there anyone there in the Garden of
Eden? Like, is the one of the subtexts
of this fear
that Dante feels that he is trying to
get there, and maybe the snake will be
there when he gets there? Or
is the assumption here that there's
already people hanging out in the Garden
of Eden?
>> Yes, so the Garden of Eden is is at is
at at the very top of Mount Purgatory,
okay? But our goal is not the Garden of
Eden, right?
Our goal is heaven. So, we're going to
pass the Garden of Eden, but we're
really trying to get to heaven.
Okay? But the point is, and this is
really important, is again, this is
where Dante is optimistic. He's like,
"We've been redeemed already. Therefore,
the garden of Eden has been opened to
us, and therefore we know we've been
redeemed."
Right? God has forgiven us for our for
our for our original sin.
Right? Any more questions? Yes?
>> So, the Garden of Eden is is earthly
paradise, and people in purgatory aren't
concerned with earthly paradise. They're
concerned [music] with
>> That's right. That's right. Right?
Okay, great. Okay, so let's take a
break, and we'll come back at 1:00,
okay? All right. Okay, good afternoon,
and welcome back.
Um so,
I just received an email from Professor
Bromwich, and he and he and he said you
guys are lovely, which is a pretty high
praise coming from him, okay?
Uh but he is right. Um you uh have
improved a great deal, and
um I think that our discussion right now
is very deep. If Dante were here, he
would approve. He would he would be
smiling at us. Okay, so uh
congratulations on everyone.
Uh
Okay, so any questions from this from
this morning? Any issues from this
morning?
That you would like to
Any questions? Yes?
>> I'm just a little bit confused about
what would you say is the major point of
the long canto where he lists all the
kings? Because
he's such an economical poet.
>> Yes.
>> But there's just so many kings listed.
I'm assuming that's to weigh down on the
reader something, but I'm not 100% sure
what that is.
>> Yeah, you're absolutely right in that
Dante does not waste words. This is why
this is poetry. It is
um
the best
economic uh
Um so, again, this is all speculation,
but what I think Dante is ach- trying to
achieve is one of totality, one of
completion.
Right? So, he wants So, at his heart,
he's democratic. So, he's trying to
speak to everyone. He's trying to give
people a sense of the unity of the
world. And so, he's trying to create
good role models. And at this time in
history, there are a lot of like really
bad kings.
Right? And what he's trying to say is
that even if you're a bad king, there is
hope for you. Right? Because what's the
most common thing to do? If you sin,
you're like, "Well, I'm screwed anyway.
So, go for it, man. You know? I'm going
to hell anyway. Who cares? I'm just
going to enjoy my time on Earth for the
next 10 years, kill as many people as as
possible, then I'll burn in hell for all
of eternity. You know, at least I'll die
with a bang. Right? Because there's no
hope for me."
So,
um, at this time in history, people are
are very black and white about the way
they perceive the world. What Dante's
trying to say is, "No, no, no, guys.
That's not how it works. There's hope
for everyone. You can You can be the
total for all of your life, but
at the very last minute, you're like,
'You know what? I want to repent.' And
God will give you a chance. It may mean
you are in purgatory for like the next
million years, but there's still hope
for you."
Right? Does that make sense? Okay. But
that's what I I think is happening.
Okay. But there are I'm sure there are
other explanations. And But thank you
for that. Any more questions before we
continue?
Uh, yes.
>> Wait. My last query is that
if Virgil is so smart, why does he feel
jealous ever?
>> What do you mean by that?
>> Well, like
I
I was told from when I was young that
jealousy is is bad, so I just tried very
hard from all of my life to try and not
be jealous of other people. I thought
that was
like an obvious mission. So, I thought
that people who were
very developed in their mind and soul
would have left jealousy behind. So, it
strikes me as surprising that Virgil
would feel jealous of anybody, but I can
see how he would be in this scenario.
>> Okay. So, that's a very interesting
point you make. So, there are many
religious traditions that teach you that
the ego is a source of sin. If you turn
away from the ego, you move towards God.
But, Dante doesn't believe that. Dante
believes that the ego is the source of
our imagination. These emotions that we
have, whether they be jealousy, anger,
hatred, they're part of who we are. And
they help develop our imagination with
color and with nuance. So, it's not
about avoiding these emotions, it's
coming to terms with these emotions
through experience, through reflection.
And it's a process of
self-development, okay? And And this
this is why the Divine Comedy is
constructed the way it is. It's a
journey, right? Because remember, in
hell, Dante is just like the biggest
right? He He tells the father
of his rival, "Your son's burning in
hell."
Right? That's just pure jealousy.
Pure envy.
But, what will happen is that
In the In Purgatory, he will move in the
process of redemption and salvation.
Okay? So, So, So, that's what Dante
believes. Does that make sense?
Great. Okay. Any more questions?
All right. Let's Let's continue.
>> Um Canto VIII, verse 52.
He moved toward me, and I advanced
toward him. "Noble judge Nino, what
delight was mine when I saw you were not
among the damned. There were no gracious
meeting we neglected before he asked me,
"When did you arrive across long seas
beneath this mountainside? I told him,
"Oh, by way of the sad regions I came
this morning. I'm still within the first
life, although by this journeying I earn
the other." When they heard my answer,
Sordello and Judge Nino just behind him
drew back like people suddenly
astonished. One turned to Virgil and the
other turned and called to one who sat
there. "Up, Corrado, come see what God
out of his grace has willed." Then when
he turned to me, "By that especial
gratitude you owe to him who hides his
primal aim so that no human mind may
find the ford to it, when you return
across the wide waves ask my own
Giovanna. There were There where the
pleas of innocence are answered to pray
for me. I do not think her mother still
loves me. She gave up her white veils,
surely, poor woman. She will wish them
back again. Through her one understands
so easily how brief in women is love's
fire when not rekindled frequently by
eye or touch. The serpent that assigns
the Milanese their camping place will
not provide for her a twirling sphere as
with Gallura's rooster."
So Nino spoke. His bearing bore the seal
of that unswerving zeal which, though it
flames within the heart, maintains a
sense of measure.
My avid eyes were steadfast staring at
that portion of the sky where stars are
flower, even as spokes when they
approach the axle.
And my guide, "Son, what are you staring
at?" And I replied, "I'm watching those
three torches with which the southern
pole is all aflame." Then he to me, "The
four bright stars you saw this morning
now are low beyond the pole, and whose
And where those four stars were, these
three now are."
Even as Virgil spoke, Sordello drew to
himself drew him to himself. "See there,
our adversary," he said, and then he
pointed with his finger.
And So, adversary is the name of Satan,
right? Satan literally means adversary
in the Hebrew Bible, right? So he So
again, it's referencing him to
the garden Adam the garden of Eden and
it's saying to us that we redeem
ourselves our adversary has been
defeated okay
I keep on going.
>> Line 97
At the unguarded edge of that small
Valley there was a serpent similar
perhaps to that which offered Eve the
bitter food. Through grass and flowers
the evil streak advance from time to
time it turned its head and licked its
back like any beast that preens and
slicks. I did not see and therefore
cannot say just how the Hawks of Heaven
made their move but I indeed saw both of
them in motion.
Hearing the green wings cleave the air
the serpent fled and the angels wheeled
around as each of them flew upward back
to his high station.
The shade who when the judge had called
had drawn closer to him through all of
that attack had not removed his eyes
from me one moment.
So may the lantern that leads you on
high discovering your will the wax one
needs enough for reaching the enameled
Peak. The shade began if you have heard
true tidings of Val di Magra or the
lands nearby tell them to me [snorts]
for there I once was mighty. Currado
Malaspina was my name I'm not the old
Currado but I'm descended from him to my
own I bore that love that here is
purified I answered I never visited your
lands but can there be a place in all of
Europe where they're not celebrated?
Such renown honors your house a claims
your lords and lands even when one has
not yet to journey there.
And so may I complete my climb I swear
to you your honored house still claims
the prize the glory of the purse and of
the sword.
Custom and nature privilege it so that
though the evil head contorts the world
your kin alone walk straight and shun
the path of wickedness and he be sure of
that the sun will not have rested seven
times within the bed that's covered and
held fast by all the rams four feet
before this gracious opinion squarely
nailed into your mind with stouter nails
than others talk provides if the divine
decree has not been staked.
>> Okay, so he lists a lot of people from
his real life, right? And you can
imagine um what he's doing is
he is in exile from Florence and he
needs to make a living, right? So
basically by including
families
uh that he knows from uh Florence into
this Divine Comedy, he's also soliciting
donations from them. And does that make
sense? It's like Yale, you know,
uh taking donations. Okay.
All right, let's keep my going.
>> Um
Oh, he has a question.
>> Yes.
>> We say that Dante was sponsored in a
way?
>> He had a He had patrons.
>> Patrons.
>> That's right, but you could always ask
for more, all right? Okay.
>> Canto 9.
Now she who shares the bed of old
Tithonus, abandoning the arms of her
sweet lover, grew white along the
eastern balcony. The heavens facing her
were glittering with gems set in the
semblance of chill of the chill animal
that assails men with its tail.
While night within the valley where we
were had moved across two of the steps
of climbs and now the third step made
night's wings incline. When I who bore
something of Adam with me, feeling the
need for sleep, lay down upon the grass
where now all five of us were seated. At
that hour close to morning when the
swallow begins her melancholy songs,
perhaps in memory of her ancient
sufferings when free to wander farther
from the flesh unless held fast by
cares, our intellects' envisionings
become almost divine. In dream I seem to
see an eagle poised with golden pinions
in the sky. Its wings were open, it was
ready to swoop down.
And I seemed to be there where Ganymede
deserted his own family when he was
snatched up for the high consistory.
Within myself I thought, "This eagle may
be used to hunting only here. Its claws
refuse to carry upward any prey found
elsewhere." Then it seemed to me that,
wheeling slightly and terrible with
lightning, it swooped, snatching me up
to the fire's orbit.
And there it seemed that he and I were
burning in this imagined conflagration
scorched me so I was compelled to break
my sleep. Just like the waking of
Achilles when he started up, casting his
eyes about about him, not knowing where
he was after his mother had stolen him
asleep away from Chiron and in her arms
had carried him to Skyros, the isle the
Greeks would later make him leave.
Such was my starting up as soon as sleep
had left my eyes, and I went pale as
will a man who, terrified, turns cold as
ice. The only one beside me was my
comfort. By now the sun was more than 2
hours high. It was the seat to which I
turned my eyes. My lord said, "Have no
fear. Be confident, for we're well along
our way. Do not restrain, but give free
rein to all your strength. You've
already come to Purgatory. See there the
rampart wall enclosing it. See where
that wall is breached, the point of
entry. Before at dawn that ushers in the
day, when soul was sleeping in your
body, on the flowers that adorn the
ground below, a lady came. She said,
'I'm Lucia. Let me take hold of him who
is asleep that I may help to speed him
on his way.'
Sordello and the other noble spirits
stayed there, and she took you. And once
the day was bright, she climbed, I
following behind. And here she set you
down, but first her lovely eyes showed
that open entry way to me. Then she and
Sleep Together took their leave.
Just like a man in doubt who then grows
sure, exchanging fear for confidence
once truth has been revealed to him, so
was I changed. And when my guide had
seen that I was free from hesitation,
then he moved with me behind him up the
rocks and toward the height.
>> Okay. All right. So, let's analyze this.
This is This is a very important um
section because this is the first time
he has a dream. He will actually have
many dreams because as he points out,
dreams
uh come from divine. Okay, the divine is
giving you a message.
And what happens is that um he falls
asleep, he has a dream of an eagle
snatching him,
and he wakes up startled, and Virgil
says, "Don't worry, it was actually
Lucia who came down from heaven
to carry you to the gate of Purgatory,
okay?" Before they were into Purgatory,
now they reached the gate of Purgatory,
and now they will make their ascent.
And so, that's a plot line of the first
half of this canto. Now, if I were
Dante's writing teacher, okay? And he
came to me and he showed me this, I
would be like, "Dante, you're lazy.
Okay? It's like you're trying to move
the plot along along, and you need to
get to the gate of Purgatory really
fast, so you like you just make
something up. I'm like, 'Okay, an angel
took me to to to the gates of
Purgatory.' That's it. Here, okay? So,
C- minus for you, Dante." Which is
basically a fail at Yale. Um
convince me I'm wrong.
What would Dante say?
Right?
I mean I I mean I'm thinking like this
is this is lazy writing, man. You're
just skipping the plot, right? You don't
know how to move the plot along, so you
just well, then we just got to Purgatory
because the angels took us.
Convince me I'm wrong.
How would Dante defend himself and say,
"No, no, no, no, this is actually
perfect." Yes?
>> With the divine plan or his cosmology
that you cannot enter Purgatory without
the love or support or the angel prayer
of your
family or friends, and that's how you
get there. So, it's the the
the theory.
>> That's right, okay. So, one possibility
is that Lucia and all the women, Rachel,
Ruth, and and and Beatrice are all
praying for him. And so, this is how he
gets to the gate of Purgatory, okay?
That's one possibility. Yes?
>> Um so, this whole journey, I don't want
to say it's a dream, but it's like a
vision of of some sort. And so, he's
having a dream inside of a a dream, so
to speak.
>> Mhm.
>> Um could this be
um him him willing it?
Like
where there's a will, there's a way. So,
he dreams that he's carried, and then
therefore he is carried.
>> I would just I would I would say the
opposite, right? Cuz Lucia literally
carries him.
Right? Lucia literally carries him all
the way to the gate, which is a long
way, and Virgil, and so they'll have to
walk.
Anyone else?
Want to try?
Yes?
>> So, this entire trip like down the hell
and up the
mountain Purgatory is supposed to be an
experience that the reader can actually
like participate in. So,
like
if we're
if we're to be like truly experiencing
what Dante has experienced, we need to
like
listen
listen him like listen someone else
reporting what happened during our dream
so that we can feel the same sense of
um
doubt and um
Yeah, doubt to to towards what he
actually dreamed.
>> Right. And I agree with that. But but
the problem is like is like if you were
to do that, you would write about how
arduous the turn journey is, right? You
would write about your emotions during
this journey. You wouldn't say like I
had a dream and then I got to where I
am.
Right? So so that's why I would I would
give him a C- minus because he's being
lazy here. I'm I'm trying to get you to
convince me I'm not He doesn't He
doesn't deserve an A+. Yes?
>> I'm I just think that
for him to describe the arduous journey,
any detail is a distraction and not
true. Because of course he's creating
the cosmology, but
he would have to say there was some
really tricky rocks, there was some
animals, but what do these signify? I
just think he doesn't want to confuse us
with any detail that we'd read into
before we get to the gates cuz there's
so much symbolic in just imagery even
when he's trying to get through the
gates. There's like three steps made of
different rock and stuff. And I just
think
any detail of the journey towards the
gate would distract us from the
symbolism past the gate.
>> Uh so yesterday we talked about this,
right? How the details add to the
journey, how details make us part of the
story. Uh yes?
>> Well, I don't know about um
Dante, but like in life
sometimes to get through purgatory get
through life, you need help from other
people. And sometimes these forms of
help come at you without you necessarily
being aware
or conscious. I don't know if that's
this is a message that he's trying to
convey.
>> Okay.
Um but it is conscious cuz Virgil tells
him what the dream is about.
Uh yeah? Go ahead.
>> Um
I
I would connect it back to prior one
hour prior to our 1 hour break. uh Uh we
were just told by Sordello that nobody
can move ahead at night. But this is
actually um you can move ahead but
at night.
And so I would argue that um
you know, there's transcendence
>> Mhm.
>> to this and you can actually transcend
whatever rules there are.
>> Right. Okay. I actually
took this to I actually took with this
as like he was so tired he slept he
slept through through the day.
And and so like Virgil so Dante kept on
walking and like he like he was asleep
so Lucy is like I have to come and get
him.
Okay. Uh yes?
>> Yeah, I I had your same interpretation
but then there's a line it's like the
sun rose and then they were killed.
>> Yeah, yeah. So it's daytime he's still
asleep. Yeah.
Right.
Okay.
Um any other suggestions?
Yes.
>> Is it possible that Dante is so happy
because many people get so happy they
they can't remember so many things and
they just
maybe
>> Okay. All right. So um
we have to remember that ultimately this
is a movie. Okay? This is a journey, a
movie where the characters are real.
What is Dante's state of mind right now?
What does he really care about right
now?
What what what is he in love with right
His shadow, okay? Okay? So
he's in love with his shadow. So he's
like walking really slowly, he's
procrastinating, he's oversleeping, he's
spending a lot of time with the other
shades, getting like offering
autographs, okay?
Beatrice and watch is up there watching
this and and what is she thinking right
now?
Yeah, she's kind of pissed right now.
Right?
Why is she pissed?
Yeah, she's like, "What about me, man?
Right? I only I only did you this favor
because I thought you truly loved me and
only loved me, and now you love your own
shadow.
All right?
So, if you're Beatrice, what are you
going to do?
>> This guy and just bring him to me.
Closer.
>> No, but I but but like, why don't I just
go and like punch the guy, you know?
Like just curse the guy. Why are you
like lifting the guy and carrying him to
the gates of purgatory?
Yes?
Okay.
Right, no no but I'm sure if you got why
not why not just like curse this guy?
Like like like because Virgil would do
that, right?
Right?
>> Your uh Beatrice in heaven isn't going
to curse anybody, but um
what is Saint Lucia a saint of? Is Is
that a clue?
>> Uh Saint Lu- Saint Lucy.
Saint Lucy. So, there's argument about
who she is,
but um what most most people believe is
that she
is someone who
who's who um became a Christian, and
then when she was forced to get married,
she killed herself rather than um
uh get married.
And so she she's like the opposite of of
Piccarda.
Yeah.
Um
There's there are lots of these saints
in the in the church. Yes?
>> I think if you're coming from a mother
or like a wife perspective or
girlfriend, because you love this guy so
much and you know that he has his faults
and he's stupid sometimes. But
right, but you still forgive him and you
want to speed him alone. And so then
you're like, "I'm going to send you help
so that you just skip this part of
temptation that's going to make you
fall, make you slow down."
>> It's a nudge, right? And this nudge is
going to force Dante to think, "Why did
this happen? Why did I have this dream?"
Right? Cuz it's a dream. It's an eagle
coming to snatch you up. What does this
dream signify?
Right? So, it's two things. It's one,
it's like the dream, and Dante's forced
to think about how to interpret this
dream. It's also Lucia coming down from
heaven um herself and carrying
Dante. If you are Dante, what are you
thinking right now?
What are you thinking right now?
Yes?
>> I'll probably feel a bit guilty, and
then I'll just stick to my task.
>> No, you're not going to feel guilty.
What are you going to feel?
Yes?
>> Maybe annoyed?
>> Not annoyed.
>> Lucky.
>> No.
If you're Dante and this happens to you,
what are you going to feel?
>> Ashamed.
>> Uh ashamed maybe, but also
No, I mean like
like
Yes?
>> That's like, "Oh man, all my fans. Now I
don't get to see them."
>> No, I would feel fear.
What Why would I feel fear?
>> So, he's mad he's no longer going to get
all the help from her, and then
he'll just be left in the purgatory.
>> Uh
No, it's actually much more subtle
subtle subtle. Like, can you try?
>> Um because the story of Ganymede is kind
of creepy to me because he was like
kidnapped by the eagle,
>> Yes.
>> became the cupbearer. So, he's like
basically the slave in heaven.
>> Yeah, that basically exactly right. The
dream is making him afraid, right? Do
you understand? The dream ISN'T LIKE,
"OH, WOW. Lucia came to like, you know,
take me to Purgatorio. I'm really,
really happy." No, it's fear. The
emotion in the dream is fear. He's
afraid.
Right? But, I'm trying to figure out why
he'd be afraid. Because Lucia came to
help you out.
Right?
Why Why would he be Why Why would he be
afraid?
Do you guys not have like girlfriends?
Do you not know how girlfriends behave?
Yes?
Yeah, d- d-
Oh my god. Guys, she does not She does
not have girlfriends, okay? Or a wife,
or mother.
Like, they're really pissed at you. What
What do they What do they do?
Y- Yes?
>> Well,
Beatrice thinks that
Dante is kind of cheating or on her,
basically.
>> Basically, yes.
>> And she And so,
they will the the angel will judge him
maybe for it. So, that's what he's
afraid of. That that that he's going to
get judged based on that.
>> Right. Okay. So, so I like like This is
hard, but but this is a life lesson for
our guys, okay?
W- Truly,
if you're a girlfriend, right? And like
you do something stupid,
um and she shouts at She shouts at you,
right? She hits you.
You're good, okay?
But, if she like she buys you dinner,
and she gives you flowers, you're really
screwed. She's going to kill you now,
okay? Life lesson for for for the guys
in here.
All right?
So, Dante is now terrified, right? Do
you understand? He had this dream, which
is like, "Ha. Someone's pissed at you,
Dante, right?" This dream is an omen.
It's a divine message. And then Virgil
says, "Lucia came and like and then
Virgil and they thought it was like
Lucia is Beatrice's best friend, right?
I'm now in a lot of trouble.
Right? And he knows it's because for the
past, you know, whatever, he's he's been
in love with with his own shadow.
Okay?
But but you see how
how amazing
this is, right? Because it gives you
complete insight into human psychology
and it's very real.
Okay? All right, let's let's keep on
going.
>> Verse 70.
Reader, you can see clearly how I lift
my matter. Do not wonder therefore if I
have to call on more art to sustain it.
Now we were drawing closer. We had
reached the part from which where first
I'd seen a breach precisely like a gap
that cleaves the wall.
I now made out a gate and there below it
three steps, their colors different
leading to it, and a custodian who had
not yet spoken. And I looked more and
more at him and I saw him seated on the
upper step, his face so radiant I could
not bear it. And in his hand he held a
naked sword which so reflected rays
toward us that I time and again tried to
sustain that sight in vain.
"Speak out from there. What are you
seeking?" So he began to speak. "Where
is your escort? Take care lest you be
harmed by climbing here." My master
answered him. "But just before a lady
came from heaven and familiar with these
things told us that's the gate. Go
there."
"And may she And may she speed you on
your path of goodness." The gracious
guardian of the gate began again. "Come
forward therefore to our stairs."
>> Okay. So, um
Dante and Virgil are approaching the
gates of Purgatory and with each gate in
Purgatory there's going to be an angel
guarding it.
And um and this is very similar to hell,
right? Where there's certain demons
guarding certain passages in hell. And
Virgil has to come forward and say,
"Uh we've come here
we come here uh with a mission from
heaven."
And uh what's the difference in
responses for um between the demons and
the angels? The demons in hell and the
angels here.
What is the difference?
Again, it it it it seems like these
subtle details that make Divine Comedy
so
um imaginative. Yes?
>> The demons usually say, "Why have you
come?" but the angels say, "What do you
want?" or "What are you looking for?"
The The demons are usually angry or just
are disturbed.
>> What's the most common response when
Virgil says that we have a mission from
heaven? What's the most common common
response from the demons?
You guys remember?
And again, this is what makes
uh Divine Comedy so uh magical because
because he pays attention to these
details.
They're silent. Right?
Okay?
You don't know the You don't know what
the response is. They're just silent.
Uh whereas these angels are actually
enthusiastic. "Great! Sure, come in. Let
me help you, okay?"
All right. So So again, this attention
to detail. I I
Can Can I go on?
>> 24
There we approached and the first step
was white marble, so polished and so
clear that I was mirrored there as I
appeared in life. The second step, made
out of crumbling rock, rough textured,
scorched with cracks that ran across its
length and width, was darker than deep
purple. The third, resting above more
massively, appeared to me to be of
porphyry, as flaming red as blood that
spurts from veins. And on this upper
step, God's angel, seated upon the
threshold, which appeared to me to be of
adamant, keeps feet planted. My guide,
with much goodwill, had me ascend by way
of these three steps, and joining me,
"Do ask him humbly to unbolt the gate."
I threw myself devoutly at his holy
feet, asking him to open out of mercy,
but first I beat three times upon my
breast.
Upon my forehead he traced seven P's
with his sword's point and said, "When
you have entered within, take care to
wash away these wounds."
>> Okay, so the seven P's, the P stands for
peccata, which is Italian for sin, okay?
So, the idea is that Dante has to climb
seven terraces,
which are the seven deadly sins, and he
has to purge himself of these seven
deadly sins. Each time he purges
himself, an angel will come and take
away a P.
Okay? So, he's tracking his progress for
for Purgatory, okay? All right, keep on
going.
>> Line 115. Ashes or dry earth that has
just been quarried with share one color
with his robe, and from beneath that
robe he drew two keys. The one was made
of gold, the other was of silver. First
with the white, then with the yellow key
he plied the gates so as to satisfy me.
Whenever one of these keys fails, not
turning appropriately in the lock, he
said to us, "This gate of entry does not
open. One is more precious, but the
other needs much art and skill before it
will unlock. That is the key that must
undo the knot. These I received from
Peter, and he taught me rather to err in
opening than in keeping this portal shut
whenever souls pray humbly."
Then he pushed back the panels of the
holy gate saying, "Enter, but I warn
you, he who would not He who He who
would look back returns again outside."
And when the panels of that sacred
portal, which are of massive and
resounding metal, turned on their
hinges, then even Tarpia, when good
Metellus were removed from it, from
which that rock was left impoverished,
did not roar so nor show itself so
stubborn.
Hearing that gate resound, I turned
attentive. I seemed to hear inside and
words that mingled with gentle music,
"Te Deum laudamus."
And what I heard gave me the very same
impression one is used to getting when
one hears a song accompanied by organ,
and now the words are clear and now are
lost.
>> Okay, so the angel is saying two things
about this gate, okay? The first thing
about this gate is that they're
generous. They will let in more people
than they actually need to. They want to
give people opportunities and a chance,
okay? Second thing is, the moment you
come in, don't look back. Go in with
total faith and be resolute. The moment
you lose your
faith, the moment you become doubtful,
then you're you'll be kicked out again,
okay?
We'll let anyone in, but when you come
in,
you have to be pretty harsh on yourself.
Okay? And And those are the rules for
purgatory.
Which is very different from what the
church teaches you at this time, which
is that it's very hard to get in. Once
you're in, you're good. Okay?
It's the opposite. Okay, so this is
purgatory 10.
>> Okay.
Canto 10.
When I had crossed the thresh threshold
of the gate that sends the souls
apparent love would make the crooked way
seem straight is seldom used, I heard
the gate resound, and hearing knew that
it had shut. And if I turned toward it,
how could my fault have found a fit
excuse? Our upward pathway ran between
cracked rocks. They seemed to sway in
one then the other part, just like a
wave that flees then doubles back. Here
we shall need some ingenuity, my guide
warned me, as both of us draw near this
side or that side where the rock wall
veers.
This made our steps so slow and hesitant
that the declining moon had reached its
bed to sink back into rest before we had
made our way through the needle's eye,
but when we were released from it in
open space above a place at which the
slope retreats. I was exhausted. With
the two of us uncertain of our way, we
halted on a plateau lonelier than desert
paths.
The distance from its edge, which rims
the void, into the base of the steep
slope, which climbs and climbs what
measures three times one man's body.
And for as far as my sight took its
flight, now to the left, now to the
right hand side, that terrace seemed to
me equally wide. There we had yet to let
our feet advance when I discovered that
the bordering bank, less sheer than
banks of other terraces, was of white
marble and adorned with carving so
accurate, not only Polycletus, but even
nature there would feel defeated.
The angel who reached earth with the
decree of that peace which for many
years have been invoked with tears, the
peace that opened heaven after long
interdict, appeared before us, his
gracious action carved with such
precision. He did not seem to be a
silent image. One would have sworn that
he was saying, "Ave." For in that scene
there was the effigy of one who turned
the key that had unlocked the highest
love.
And in her stance there were impressed
these words, "Ecce ancilla Dei."
Precisely like a figure stamped in wax.
"Your mind must not attend to just one
part," the gentle master said. He had me
on the side of him where people have
their heart. At this I turned my face
and saw beyond the form of Mary, on the
side where stood the one who guided me,
another story upon the rock. Therefore,
I moved past Virgil and drew close to it
so that the scene before me my eyes was
more distinct. There carved in that same
marble were the cart and oxen as they
drew the sacred ark, which makes men now
fear tasks not in their charge. People
were shown in front, and all that group
divided into seven choirs made two of my
senses speak. One sense said, "No." The
other said, "Yes, they do sing."
Just so, about the incense smoke shown
here shown there, my nose and eyes
contended too with yes and no.
And there the humble psalmist went
before the sacred vessel dancing,
lifting up his robe. He was both less
and more than king.
Facing the that scene and shown as at
the window of a great palace, Michal
watched as would a woman full of scorn
and suffering.
To look more closely at another carving
which I saw gleaming white beyond
Michal, my feet moved past the point
where I had stood. And there was the
noble action of a Roman prince was
presented. He whose worth had urged on
Gregory to his great victory. I mean the
Emperor Trajan and a poor widow was near
his bridle. And he stood even as one in
tears and sadness would. Around him
horsemen seemed to press and crowd.
Above their heads on golden banners
eagles were represented moving in the
wind. Among that crowd the miserable
woman seemed to be saying, "Lord, avenge
me for the slaying of my son. My heart
is broken."
And he was answering, "Wait now until I
have returned." And she, as one in whom
grief presses urgently, "And Lord, if
you do not return." And he, "The one who
will be in my place will perform it for
you." She, "What good can others'
goodness do for you if you neglect your
own?" He, "Be consoled. My duty shall be
done before I go. So justice as so mercy
makes me stay."
This was the speech made visible by one
within whose sight no thing is new. But
we who lack its likeness here find
novelty.
While I took much delight in witnessing
these effigies of true humility, feared
to see because he was their maker. The
poet murmured, "See the multitude
advancing, though with slow step on this
side. They will direct us to the higher
stairs." My eyes, which had been
satisfied in seeking new sight, a thing
for which they longed, did not delay in
turning toward him.
But what I would not have you, reader,
be deflected from your good result by
hearing from me now how God would have
us pay the debt we owe.
Don't dwell upon the form of punishment.
Consider what comes after that. At worst
it cannot last beyond the final
judgment.
"Master," I said, "what I see moving
toward us does not appear to me like
people, but I can't tell what is there.
My sight's bewildered." And he to me,
"Whatever makes them suffer their heavy
torment bends them to the ground. At
first, I was unsure of what they were,
but looking intently and let your eyes
unravel what's beneath those stones, you
can already see what penalty strikes
each."
"O Christians, arrogant, exhausted,
wretched, whose intellects are sick and
cannot see, who place your confidence in
backward steps, do you not know that we
are worms and born to form the angelic
butterfly that soars without defenses to
confront his judgment? Why does your
mind presume to flight when you are
still like the imperfect grub, the worm
before it has attained its final form?
Just as one sees a time as corbel for
support of ceiling and or of roof, a
figure with knees drawn up into chest,
and this oppressiveness, unreal, gives
rise to real distress in him who watches
it. Such was the state of those I saw
when I looked hard. They were indeed
bent down, some less, some more,
according to the weights their backs now
bore, and even he whose aspect showed
more patience and tears appeared to say,
"I can no more."
>> Okay. All right. So, they are past the
gates of Purgatory. They're now inside
Purgatory proper.
What's the first thing that Dante sees?
What's the first thing he sees?
What's there awaiting him in in
Purgatory, the first thing?
Excuse me?
>> Rocks.
>> Yeah.
>> Right.
>> Correct.
>> And what
are
these rocks? What's inside these rocks?
Carvings, okay? This is artwork. The
first thing that Dante sees
when he enters Purgatory is artwork.
Carvings of the rock that depict scenes
of humility. Okay? These are just famous
scenes.
And um what Dante does is that he turns
these scenes into basically a movie,
right? A story that he plays in his
head.
So, what he's trying to suggest here is
if you want to really
redeem yourself, if you really want to
cleanse yourself, what do you need first
and foremost?
What enables you to redeem yourself?
What it we What allows you to absolve
yourself?
>> Reflection.
>> Uh yes.
>> Humility.
>> Um
examples of humility to copy.
>> Uh you need reflection, but what drives
the human the reflection?
>> Art.
>> But but why art?
>> Imagination.
>> Imagination, okay? That's what Dante is
saying here. If you really want to start
the process, you need imagination. So,
what I want to do now is let's draw
let's draw the Mona Lisa.
Yeah?
It is the Mona Is Do you guys like like
the Mona Lisa?
Okay. Or may maybe some something else.
Do Do Do you guys prefer the Mona Lisa
or another piece of art?
Huh?
The Last Supper? Okay, let let's do
both, okay? Let's Let's Let's Let's
Let's Let's Let's do both the Mona Lisa
and Last Supper, okay?
All right. So,
now what I want to do is this.
What Dante is suggesting is like the act
of looking at art, okay? The act of
interacting with art of art
betters you as a person, okay?
And I want to I want to figure out why.
All right, so
>> [snorts]
[clears throat]
>> you have the artwork, okay, the
painting,
and it could be Mona Lisa or The Last
Supper. Let's Let's Let's just do
uh Last Supper. Yeah, let's just do Last
Supper, okay?
All right. [snorts]
And I want to figure out why this is the
case. Why when you look at art
it changes you for the better or and it
and it enhance your imagination, okay?
Let's try to figure this out.
You You go to
uh the Louvre.
Where's The Last Supper? The The Last
Supper is in
And you you you've seen it, right?
Right? So So So let's let's let's say
you're you're there, right? And you you
have the room to yourself and you're
sitting down for a whole afternoon and
you're looking at The Last Supper by
yourself, okay?
And what Donny's saying is that when you
do that, it changes you as a person and
you become a more virtuous person. I'm
trying to figure out why that's the
case.
All right. Has Has Has anyone actually
done that? Has anyone just sat down in
front of a painting for a whole
afternoon and just looked at it?
Okay? Well, well, tell me what's going
on.
All right, let's let's let's just list
them. What What is your mind doing as
you look at at the painting?
Yes?
>> Uh yeah, I I used to uh try to keep
looking down at that kind of painting
and uh I I don't know, I just feel so so
strange. I just I was just in the
painting. I was in the painting. I was
in the
uh in the Jesus' position or even try to
imagine myself if I were in the
painting, I would I was standing on the
table. And what what should I think?
>> All right.
So So you participate in it, yes? Okay,
what else?
>> Well, first I would try to figure out
who the people are in the painting
first. Like so the background, what what
Yeah. Like just knowledge about them so
I can better understand them and where
they come from.
>> Okay. So what what what you trying to do
is you're trying to fill in the story,
right? Does that make sense?
There's a story inside the painting
you're trying to fill it in. You're
trying to figure who they are, what what
they're doing, okay?
Yes?
>> I put try and put
try [clears throat] and put myself in
the shoes
of of the artist and ask, you know, why
is he put
a certain detail in the painting.
>> Okay, right. Okay, so analysis. You do
analysis, technical analysis, yes?
Sure.
Right? So you're switching perspectives,
okay?
Sure.
What else?
Yes?
Good. Yes, okay. You're you're trying to
connect it to yourself. Connection.
Good. Yes, excellent.
Uh yes?
>> You start looking at the colors and you
see the picture as a whole, but you also
start looking focusing on details.
>> Yes, okay. Right, okay. So you're trying
to
focus on the details. Details focus.
Yes. And why would you do that?
>> Because you already see the whole
picture, so you want to
see what each part of the picture is
like.
>> Okay, right. So so you're basically
trying to world build, okay?
World build.
Okay. Anyone else? Yes?
>> I will try to understand what the
um
what the artist try to convey.
>> Okay. Okay, the the the the story, okay?
The message, yes?
Anyone else?
Yes?
>> I usually try to dissolve myself a kind
of disassociation in order to assimilate
within the painting trying to forget
yourself trying to forget yourself. And
it's like
how do you get moved by a painting where
you have to
disassociate into the painting?
>> Okay, that that's a really interesting
comment, okay? But, I want you to
break it down for us and try to try to
like literally explain what's going on.
>> So, it's like constantly trying to ebb
and flow between doing what being the
viewer and being the artist, being the
subject and being the physical object.
And you're just trying to play back and
forth between who am I and who what is
the painting and trying to bring them
together.
>> okay. So, is it dialogue, right?
A dialogue assimilation, okay? Yeah,
assimilation, right?
Would Would it be fair to say that when
you do this, you're also moving beyond
time and space?
Okay, so you're moving outside of time
and space, which creates unity, okay?
Does that make sense, guys?
Time and space create separation, but
once you move out of time and space, it
creates unity. All right, thank you.
Yes.
>> I like looking at portraits of people,
so I asked for all dining halls who have
like all the famous alumna alumni
hanging or like and then they'll be
looking down on you as you're eating and
then you you feel like you have this
connection with them. They used to sit
at these halls and tables and eat under
the same candle light and then you
wonder if they're still somehow alive in
heaven looking down on you and expecting
you to do some great things as well so
that one day your pictures will be
hanging up here.
>> [laughter]
>> That's a really interesting comment, but
like try to explain how this connection
works. There's connection, you're at
Oxford and all these great people these
portraits are all around you and it
looks it seems as though they're staring
at you from heaven. Explain how that
could happen.
>> Because the pictures were positioned so
high up on the ceilings and then
literally they're like looking down on
you while you look up at them while
you're eating and like it feels like
there's this eternal
capsule of their souls in essence
somewhere left in the painting or their
memories of this whole resonates with
you.
>> Okay. Right, okay. So, like all and
wonder resonance, sure.
Resonance.
Okay.
Um so, Benjamin Franklin I'm sorry, not
Benjamin Franklin. Walter Benjamin w- w-
w- would have a phrase for it. He calls
it aura.
Okay? And his argument is this.
Okay. I It's a very strange argument,
okay? But but like
like obviously we we can't know with
this, right? But in the in The Last
Supper in the church in Florence, is it
Florence? Or yeah. So, you're sitting
there, okay? Whenever you're sitting
there, that painting is sucking up your
energy,
right? So, it has its own aura.
It's alive.
Okay?
Right? And so, and that aura then
becomes reflected reflected in you as
well, right? And so, that that's what
Walter Benjamin would say. Every artwork
has its own aura, meaning its own
personality uh developed over um
hundreds of years of audience
participation, okay?
Any other
Come on, you guys have all looked at
artwork, right? Yes?
>> I guess just looking at the lines we
just read.
Um yes.
>> About
resolving paradoxes, but also using your
imagination to give life to the painting
cuz like the first carving he says, "Two
senses were inside me. One sense said,
'No, they're not seen.'" Like that's the
realistic material Dante. And the other
sense, "Yes, they do sing."
>> Yes.
>> So, I guess it's giving yourself over to
the reality of the painting. I I don't
don't know what to call that process.
>> Well, I I would say it's co-creation,
right? Because the artist has created a
reality with your imagination, you are
making this reality much more vibrant
and you're changing the dynamic of this
reality. Such a cool creation process.
Right?
Uh yes. Oh sorry sorry sorry yeah.
>> Um so this is before
pictures or cell phones or anything like
this. So you're capturing a moment of
time.
Um and
there's like a duality going on here of
like
declaring yourself into the
universe or even narcissism, however you
want to call that.
>> Yeah.
>> Also
um
and
putting yourself out there to
empathize and be empathized with.
>> Right, okay. So it's almost like a form
of meditation, right?
A meditation that creates a sort of
mystical experience.
Mystical connection.
Does that make sense, guys?
Right? When you're looking at a
painting, yes.
>> Um so when I went to Florence and went
to one of the museums there,
uh I went with a friend and uh when I
just start when I started looking at the
paintings, I
we just started to like debate about the
paintings. We we we looked from
different perspectives what the artist
was trying to convey.
>> Yes.
>> we like we really went deep and we kind
of that's really how I started to
understand
the picture more through debate, through
listening to someone else's perspective
as well.
>> Yeah, but what's interesting is what the
painting has done is
enhance your individuality.
And so when you engage in debate, you're
expressing your individuality, right?
But but the main point is
first of all, your individual
individuality was activated, right? And
that's why everyone who looks at a
painting is going to have a different
interpretation because we're all unique
individuals. Okay? So
um it really activates your
individuality.
Good. Okay, anyone else? Yes?
>> I think this is why one the Catholic
Church will always have the stained
glass window with a lot of stories and
greeted on them. The The whole point is
that most of the time you are illiterate
coming into the church and then all you
can do is look at pictures and then the
pictures can kind of, you know, wash
away the sin in a way, right? Like or
kind of purified you plus it makes you
bow in humility towards the beauty of
God. Like the minute you enter this hall
of pictures and light shining through
the window shining on you does and make
you feel elevated in a sense of like
Hallelujah. And then you go you
you without the organ you can feel the
organ, you know, and then so it's like
very spiritual experience.
>> Right. Uh can can we go to the Mona
Lisa, please?
Who Who's actually seen the Mona Lisa?
Like in your life?
All right. Okay.
What is unique about the Mona Lisa? Only
the Mona Lisa does this. Can Can Can you
tell us?
>> Are we talking about the fact that where
wherever you are in the room she looks
at you?
>> It's really weird.
Can Can Can you see it?
>> Yeah.
>> When you walk around
her eyes follow you. They track you.
It's really weird.
Right?
>> You really feel it because like wherever
you are in the room the aura is here and
you can just like turn your back and
then look back she's still here. Like
you can't move away from like the energy
>> It's really weird. I've never been but
like you know, I I I've read stories.
Yes?
>> Not just that but there's a song by Nat
King Cole the singer he sang a song
called the Mona Lisa
>> Yes.
>> where he says is your smile to tempt a
lover
or is it just another work of art you're
putting on your face? So when you in
front of her it's very about co-creation
because it's your inner feeling in that
moment defines what you read her smile
as because it's such an elusive smile.
And it's amazing standing in front of it
because
sometimes she's upset with you.
Sometimes she's like Beatrice like
saying come on you need to rise up." And
then sometimes she's saying, "Well, it's
okay. You're a human being."
>> Right. It's like she's alive. Right. Uh
all right.
So, did did you did you your your
experience with Mona Lisa? Can you talk
about it?
>> It is really, you know, really hard to
actually look clear careful at it Mona
Lisa because there are so many people
sitting in front of you.
So,
uh
>> I understand that, yes.
>> Yeah. And uh I feel the energy. Yeah. I
feel the energy, but I see
>> So, you felt energy too, right?
>> Yeah, I feel the energy. Yeah, that's
that's that's the uh
>> Yeah, it's it's that that's the aura,
yes. Yeah, yeah, yes?
>> I guess I wanted to expand on these
ideas then. Would art
would art show you what is possible and
therefore
expand [clears throat] your imagination?
>> Yes, that's right. That's right.
You're forced to expand your imagination
in order to have all these feelings,
right? And the more feelings you have,
the more your imagination expands. Yes,
exactly.
Um any other yes?
>> Yeah, because I've also
heard that her her
Mona Lisa's hands is not the woman's
hands. It must baby's infant's hand. And
uh the face is is like a like man. It's
not a woman. So, maybe it's uh Da Vinci
who just try to portray himself.
So, and even the the bone, I think it is
kind of combination between the baby,
between a woman, between a man. So, it's
kind of incarnation or
>> Okay. Yes?
>> Uh just to add on to that about art,
it's actually one of the reasons why me
and my husband converted from
Protestantism to Catholicism because in
Protestant religion, like you you can
only have the cross, which is a symbol
for Christ. There's no art, very little
music. Well, there is Hillsong, but
that's it. Um so, there was no mystical
stuff, no incense, no but Catholic
church is like, man, full on, you know,
like art, music, incense, all this very
materialistic, almost you know, like
down-to-earth things that really incites
like kind of all your senses to feel
God. And then with
Protestantism is all abstract ideas,
symbols, theories, concepts. That's very
soul or spirit, but
Catholicism [clears throat]
is very bodily. It's very femininely.
It's very womanly. It's very artly or
musically. And that kind of has a
connection to your soul or your body.
Like in a way your senses awakes your
awakes your soul or spirit to feel
closer to God. So this concreteness, you
know.
>> Great.
Great. Okay. So we've established what
art is and what the impact of art is on
you. But now we want to figure out why
the imagination explain the imagination
would necessarily make you a more
virtuous person. Right? That does That
doesn't actually connect. Okay? Yeah, we
know art expands your imagination, but
why would that make you a much more
virtuous person ready for
um catharsis, ready for purgatory?
Why would the first step to self self
self salvation or redemption be art?
Why?
Yes.
>> Can create consciousness about your
emotions cuz like when you see art then
you feel something and then you think
about it. Why am I feeling this?
>> Yeah. Okay. So So So let's um
Let's go over this, okay? One is
the emotions.
Okay? The entire point of art really,
okay, is to like shock your emotions to
the forefront, right? So your emotions
are now
like alive and you actually feel them
much more
uh closely. Yeah, thank you. Okay?
Anyone else?
Starts with person, okay? Art will shock
you and then your emotions come to the
forefront.
Right? Then then what happens? Yes?
>> Well, to add to that point, it
strengthens your empathy for especially
the artist, obviously, who tries to
express his own emotions, and then you
can start to emphasize with his
emotions, and then that's how you expand
your imagination because
you can put yourself into his shoes and
feel as though you are him.
>> Yeah, exactly. Okay. So, imagine this,
okay? Your emotions are being shocked,
right? They're jolted. They're They're
in motion now, and what the artwork does
is we focus your emotions
in order to empathize with the painting,
right? So, it's reordering your
emotional state.
Okay, does that make sense?
All right? And obviously,
um it makes you more virtuous. But, why?
Yes?
>> Yes, my first practical answer would be
you realize that acting virtuously is
what creates a universe where
imagination can flourish and come into
being. So, the virtues are designed so
agents in a universe act so that
everybody can
imagine more and there can be more in
the universe.
>> Um okay. That's true, okay? But, I want
to go into the technical details of how
this happens, okay? What you say is
abstractly true, but like I want I want
I want to know how concretely it
happens, yes?
>> Um
what that comes to mind is dissociation,
and then the ability to put your center
away from yourself,
and I guess come back to empathizing
with the artist's emotions, empathizing
with the technique he uses, the process,
his story, everything, like being able
to think outside of yourself.
>> Okay, yes?
>> You have a love with the artist, and you
become thankful to him for creating
this.
>> Sure, but I'm saying like what does
that?
>> It's It's like love. So, like basically
you
there's a relation between you and the
art and so you and the artist and then
thanks to this you become thankful
through this like
>> Okay. Okay. Yes. Yes. That's the end,
okay? I I think I think you first of all
your emotions are are forced into
motion, okay? Then your emotions become
more focused on the artwork and then
there's a step and then at the end you
are you have a sense of gratitude to to
to the artist. You have a sense of
connection to the artist. But what's the
missing step?
What focus your emotions?
>> Um self-reflection.
Like You start
>> What is the art?
>> It forces you away from the material and
you think about more of the abstract.
>> are thinking too hard about this. What
is art?
Why do we watch art?
Yes?
>> Because fundamentally it's proof that
other minds exist. Like it's against
solipsism. So you
>> What draws you to the art?
>> Beautiful. It's beautiful.
>> It's beauty, do you understand? Okay?
You see how this works?
The beauty
shocks your emotions, okay? It's like
seeing a beautiful woman on the street.
You're like, "Oh my god, I need to meet
her, okay?" Your emotions are shocked
into place. The beauty then focuses your
emotions
and then orders the emotions into
something that is virtuous.
But why would why would beauty be
virtuous?
What's the connection between beauty and
virtue? Yes?
>> Because on the surface of beauty and
and after the surface of beauty and in
the depths of an artwork is love.
So eventually the greatest artwork
eventually has to
be the
most associatative
and the most associatative power, I
think, is is love.
>> Yes, okay. Yes, that's right. Beauty
will lead you to love. But what But what
is it about beauty that allows you to
love? Yes?
>> I think because beauty as a construct
has formulas in a way like we talk about
geometry, numerology, and all these
essence just the same way you see math
and science reflect the beauty of the in
the design or whatever divinity reflects
in it. And so the moment you see beauty,
you kind of makes you think about the
smart designer who, you know, has
designed these things.
>> Yes, okay. Yes.
>> And maybe because the curving because
the you can see the women they got
curving waves. They they got a shape
which is quite it's like up and down.
>> Right. So there are mathematical
principles to beauty, right? There's
symmetry, there's the um
uh pi principle, right? Uh yeah yes yes
yes if you want to have a
>> Yeah, so um I'm a member of the Cormac
McCarthy Society and he has this line,
"Beauty and truth are one."
>> Yes, that's right. Exactly.
>> The the key is the word you just said,
"Symmetry." Um in all great art the sym-
symmetrical when you see a beautiful man
or woman, there's symmetry in their
face.
The But how how all of this correlates
to truth is
um we don't just say, "I'm wearing a
gray shirt." That's uh shirt. That's not
truth. That's a just a fact. If I say
the Vietnam War started because of XYZ,
uh that's not the truth because I need
to know what happened right before it
and what happened right before that and
what happened on the moon and what
happened a thousand years before. And
and and the reason that we can't get to
truth or no journalist can get to truth
is because you can't write everything.
But there was is one entity that can
write everything and know all and that's
God.
>> Yes.
>> And so beauty and truth are one.
>> Exactly, okay? So do you guys see how
this works, right? The beauty there's a
mathematical principles behind the
beauty including symmetry, all that, and
that goes that takes you into the mind
of God. That's the very center of God.
And that's and then that becomes truth
and that's what allows you to love. You
understand?
Okay? So our great artwork gives you
access into the very mind of God, allows
you to connect with the universe, and
that's what makes you virtuous.
Okay? It activates the love inside of
you.
All right? Uh yes?
>> Is that not a very platonic view? Like
Plato really thought about mathematics
and its connection to God.
>> Yes.
>> But he still But I What I don't
understand is then he still denied art
as a form of God or like a expression of
God, right?
>> Okay, that's a really good question,
okay? So, it is true that for Plato uh
mathematics is the mind of God. It's
also true
that if Plato were to see the Mona Lisa,
he'd be horrified. Why would he be
horrified? Do you guys know why?
Yes?
>> Because it's just a falsity. It's like
an just an illusion and it's It's being
praised as form of God.
>> That's right. It's a shadow. And we And
so for for for Plato
what
to really access the mind of God is you
can you have to avoid the beauty and
just focus on the mathematics. You
understand? For him, it's not beauty
gives you access to mathematics, it's
beauty distracts you from the
mathematics. You just focus on the
mathematics, okay?
Don't Don't look at the painting, just
look at the mathematics behind the
painting. And that's what gives you
access to God.
But Plato's wrong, okay? I mean like
just because he's Plato doesn't mean
he's right all the time. It Does Does
that make sense?
Okay. Uh yes?
>> Do you personally think maybe that's why
some mathematicians
go crazy? Cuz they're getting
>> I agree. Yeah. Can you explain that?
>> They're getting too close to God.
Or
>> No, I think it's because they're too far
away from God. Yeah, I I think it's
because they create their own reality
and they've lost connection to the real.
And that's why, you know, like the best
mathematicians, they do their best math
at like maybe around 20 to 30, that that
age group. And then afterwards they go
insane, okay? And it's it's no different
from, I would say, computer programmers,
if that makes any sense. Like once you
create your own reality and you try to
inhabit this reality, uh and you lose
your connection to the divine through
beauty and through truth and through
love, you're going to go crazy.
Okay?
And and and yes.
>> But how does that looking at the
painting make people a more virtuous
person?
>> Okay, so the process is this, okay?
The beauty the the beauty of the
painting draws you, okay? It compels you
to look at it forever, okay? You lose
You lose the sense of time and space.
You're just focusing focusing on it. You
become one with the painting. In this
process, what happens is your emotions
become jolted. They become out of place,
okay? What this basically means is that
your world view is evolving. And through
this process, then your emotions become
rearranged in a new world view that
focuses on the painting. Okay? And the
the painting, once you keep looking at
more more at it, you access truth. Why?
Because beauty and truth are one if if
if it's God, right? So you're giving
access into the mind of God.
And then that
Because you know that God is love, that
forces your emotions to be rearranged in
a way that allows for more love, which
is more virtue. Does that make sense?
Okay, yes?
>> I have a question
just on about what you personally feel.
So there's a fractal called the
Mandelbrot set.
>> Okay.
>> Which maybe it'd be good if we saw a
picture of it.
>> Sure, let's try and draw it up.
>> And it's basically a small very short
formula which
uh
lists points to do with primes and
and and you'll see it.
I've been obsessed with these and I and
they move me so much from when I was a
very very small child that you can zoom
in with infinite complexity. Do you
think this is more beautiful than any
human art because it's literally the art
contained within mathematics.
>> Uh yes.
>> major
at Peking University and when he saw
these images, he's also a computer
programmer, he got the Olympics into uh
for computer programming. But he said
that it is what that moves him to God in
as a middle schooler because the minute
he saw the signs and the design and the
numerology, the symmetry, the golden
ratio and all of these is that you
cannot study science without knowing
logos, without understanding like all
these
design. So that's how he moved from
atheism
to religion.
>> But but let me ask you this question.
Would you rather spend like 10 years
looking looking at the Mona Lisa or 10
years looking at the Mandelbrot set?
>> You can zoom in the Mandelbrot set
forever and it's never the same.
You can zoom in and it it changes
forever and ever and ever and ever.
>> But what do you feel emotionally when
when you
look at the Mandelbrot set?
>> Not like a human being.
>> What what do you mean by that?
>> Well like when I feel when I want to
feel like a human being, the Mona Lisa
and things, they really do it for me.
But then there's some kind of
transcendental feeling when your
individuality leaves you and you're just
trying to
be with the mind of God or whatever you
think that is.
>> Right. I understand. I understand. And
if you do that for a long long time,
that might be problematic.
>> Yeah, I think definitely 10 years Mona
Lisa is is is better. She's a bit of
company. She's a bit of company.
>> So yes. Yes. Okay. I would think so. All
right. Okay. Good. Let's continue guys.
Okay?
All right.
Let's let's go to canto 11. Okay?
Okay. So we are now in the first terrace
which is to purge you of pride. Okay? So
um you have to learn humility in this
terrace. Okay, let's let's
read, okay?
>> Our Father, you who dwell within the
heavens but are not circumscribed by
them out of your greater love for your
first works above. Praise be your name
and your omnipotent by every creature
just as it is seeming to offer thanks to
your sweet effluence. Your kingdom's
peace come unto us for if it does not
come then though we summon all our force
we cannot reach it of ourselves.
Just as your angels as they sing hosanna
offer their wills to you a sacrifice so
may men offer up their wills to you.
Give unto us this day the daily manner
without which he who labors most to move
ahead through this harsh wilderness
falls back.
Even as we forgive all who have done us
injury may you benevolent forgive and do
not judge us by our worth. Try not our
strength so easily subdued against the
ancient foe but set it free from him who
goads it to perversity. This last
request we now address to you dear Lord
not for ourselves who have no need but
for the ones who we have left behind.
Beseeching thus good penitents for us
and for themselves those shades moved on
beneath their weights like those we
sometimes bear in dreams. Each in his
own degree of suffering but all
exhausted circling the first terrace
purging themselves of this world's cory
ice.
>> Okay, so again these are people with
pride and so they're giving weights and
they have to move very slowly
um
on this terrace and they
they're they're being burdened by these
weights and this is meant to
um relieve them of their pride and then
they will have to learn humility.
How is this different from hell?
Look.
What is the difference? Yes.
Okay.
I don't understand
if you were in hell, it would be the
same thing,
right?
>> Well, they but they want to do it. Like
they know why they do it. They
understand why they do it.
The people in hell who punished
I don't think they're like
I mean they they know they're guilty,
but
they don't think that it's fair that
they're being punished probably.
>> Yes. Yes, okay. Yes, anyone else?
>> They are receiving this punish in the
hope that one day they will reach
paradise and then they know that they
did something wrong and then they're
kind of like punishing themselves
physically, but then they still have
hope that one day
they'll make it into like upper tiers or
like make it to heaven.
>> Yes, okay, exactly.
But I don't understand why
the people in hell can't be like, "You
know what? You just do this for 10,000
years and then we'll send you to
purgatory." It's always like, "No, in
hell it's for all of eternity."
What What's the logic of this?
>> Maybe unlike those in hell, they did not
do deeds that puncture the fabric of
society
and sow discord or
create societal ills that they
would not be doing this forever.
>> Yeah, we don't know that, right? Because
um the condition for being purgatory is
that one, you repent, and second is that
people pray for you, right?
It doesn't say there are certain crimes
that um prevent you from going to
purgatory.
And so again, this is a question for us
where it seems as though the punishment
is the same. So if they're doing the
same punishment, couldn't you have a
system where in hell, if you do this for
10,000 years, you're given access to
purgatory?
Why why not do that?
Yes?
>> Because
even the promise of 10,000 years would
not give you a growth mindset. So, I
think in this scene, they're just
singing themselves into the growth
mindset. So, the actuality of what
they're doing is purifying them.
>> Yes.
>> And so, that if you were in hell,
even if you knew you that by doing this
for 10,000 years, you might make it out,
it wouldn't give you the growth mindset
that would actually
render you above
>> Yeah, but why? I'm asking you why,
right?
Why?
>> Because you have to do every second with
no thought of the end.
You can't do it as if there's a finish
line. You have to just do it as if
you're doing it forever. And the mindset
that you have in every second is what
counts.
>> Okay, so this is actually a really
important question. If you really
understand Dante, why are people in hell
and why are people in purgatory?
What's the difference?
Yes?
>> So, I'm seeing [clears throat] this as
like an Aristotelian golden mean. And
so, the example I have, even though
bravery is not something that will get
you in the heaven, is the two extremes
that Aristotle would see would be
cowardice, but then also recklessness.
>> Yes.
>> And those would get you in this
fictional hell. But there's a spectrum.
And so, the closer you get to bravery on
either end of the extremes, then you're
going to end up at a point, which I
don't know why, you would end up God
would say that's good enough that you're
get into
into purgatory.
>> Yes, okay.
Um
Uh Dante has read a lot of Aristotle,
and he would definitely agree on on on
on this idea. But that still doesn't
clarify for me why,
if it's the same punishment, right?
Why? What's the difference between
heaven What's the difference between
hell and purgatory?
Yes?
>> Maybe people in hell they just by
reason, but in purgatory people they
they don't just always by reason. They
just by inspiration or what?
Or hope or what?
>> Okay, this is like hard, okay? But what
Dante suggests, wait, I I know Dante
believes this, okay? Is that people are
are in hell because they choose to be
there. People are purgatory because they
choose to be there. It's a law of free
will.
Okay?
Does that make sense to you guys? That's
where the growth mindset comes from.
Because you believe you can be better.
But if you like I don't believe I can be
better, then I'm just better off in
hell.
Right?
Okay? What what why are people in
purgatory doing this thing? Because they
think that by doing this thing, I can be
better. Right? But in hell you're like
they you make you make them do this.
You're like, well, I'll keep on doing
this, but it's not going to change me.
It's just my punishment, right? So it's
perception where people in hell see it
as their punishment, but people in
purgatory see it as their opportunity.
Does that make sense?
That's the difference. It's attitude.
And that's this fundamental
understanding Dante and how he sees the
world.
Okay, let let's let's keep on going.
>> Line 16. Even as we forgive all who have
done us injury, may you benevolent
forgive and do not judge us by our
worth.
Try
Oh, sorry.
Um line 25. Beseeching thus good good
penitence for us and for themselves,
those shades moved on beneath their
weight like those we sometimes bear in
dreams, each in his own degree of
suffering, but all exhausted, circling
the first terrace, purging themselves of
this world's score, eh?
If there they pray on our behalf, what
can be said and done here on this earth
for them by those whose wills are rooted
in true worth?
Indeed, we should help them to wash away
the stains they carried from this world
so that made pure in light, they reach
the starry wheels. Ah, so may justice
and compassion soon unburden you so that
your wings may move as you desire them
to and uplift you. Show us on which hand
lies the shortest path to reach the
stairs. If there's more than one
passage, then show us that which is less
deep for he who comes with me because he
wears the weight of Adam's flesh as
dress. Despite his ready will, is slow
in his ascent. These words which have
been spoken by my guide were answered by
still other words we heard for though it
was not clear who had replied. An answer
came.
Come with us to the right along the wall
of rock and you will find a path where
even one alive can climb and where I'm
not impeded by the stone that since it
has subdued my haughty neck compels my
eyes to look below. Then I should look
at this man who's still alive and
nameless to see if I recognize him and
to move his pity. Pity for my burden. I
was Italian, son of a great Tuscan. My
father was Guglielmo Aldobrandesco. I do
not know if you have heard his name.
The ancient blood and splendid deeds of
my forefathers made me so presumptuous
that without thinking on our
common
common mother, I scorned all men past
measure and that scorn brought me my
death. The Sienese know how as this each
child in Campagnatico.
I'm Umberto and my arrogance has not
harmed me alone for it has drawn all of
my kin into calamity. Until God has been
satisfied, I bear this burden here among
the dead because I did not bear this
load among the living.
My face was lowered as I listened and
one of those souls not he'd spoken
twisted himself beneath beneath the
weight that burdened them. He saw and
knew me and called out to me fixing his
eyes on me laborious as I completely
hunched walked on with them.
"Oh, I cried out. Are you not Oderisi?
Glory of Gubbio, glory of that art they
call illumination now in Paris."
"Brother," he said, "the page was
painted by the brush of Franco
Bolognese. Smile more brightly. All the
glory now is his. Mine but a part. In
truth, I would have been less gracious
when I lived. So great was that desire
for eminence that drove my heart. For
such pride, here one pays the penalty,
and I not be here yet had it not been
that while I still could sin, I turned
to him."
O empty glory of the powers of humans,
how briefly green endures upon the peak,
unless an age of dullness follows it. In
painting, Cimabue Cimabue
thought he held the field, and now it's
Giotto they acclaim. The former only
keeps a shadowed fame. So did one Guido
from the other wrest the glory of our
tongue, and he perhaps is born who will
chase both out of the nest.
Worldly renown is nothing other than a
breath of wind that blows now here, now
there, and changes name when it has
changed its course, its course.
Before a thousand years have passed, a
span that for eternity is less space
than an eye blink for the slowest sphere
in heaven,
would you find greater glory if you left
your flesh when it was old than if your
death had come before your infant fourth
year was spent?
All Tuscany acclaimed his name, the man
who moved so slowly on the path before
me, and now they scarcely whisper of him
even in Siena,
where he lorded it when they destroyed
the raging mob in Florence, then as
arrogant as now its prostitute.
Your glory wears the color of the grass
that comes and goes. The sun makes it
wither first drew it from the ground
still green and tender. And I to him,
"Your truthful speech has filled my soul
with sound humility, abating my over
swollen pride. But who is he who of whom
spoke now?
Provenzan Salvani, he answered. Here,
because presumptuously he thought his
grip could master all Siena.
So, he has gone and so he goes with no
rest since his death. This is the
penalty extracted from those who there
overreached.
And I, but if a spirit who waits the
edge of life before repenting must,
unless good prayers help them stay below
and not ascend here for as long as time
as he had spent alive. Do tell me how
Salvani's entry here has been allowed.
When he was living in his greatest
glory, said he, then of his own free
will he set aside all shame and took his
place upon the Campo of Siena. There to
free his friend from suffering in
Charles' prison, humbling himself he
trembled in each vein.
I say no more. I know I speak obscurely,
but soon enough you'll find your
neighbor's acts are such that what I say
can be explained. This deed delivered
him from those confines.
>> Okay. So,
um here we meet a man who
uh did a lot of wrong.
Okay? But once he did some good. Okay?
Once he helped his friend um escape uh a
prison.
And he begged uh his neighbors to help
him free his friend. Okay? So, the idea
here is, look, you can spend your you
could you could
uh live a life of complete sin, okay?
But the moment you choose to do one good
act, it will be it will be remembered
and it will redeem you. Does that make
sense?
Okay? So, this is extremely radical of
Dante to say, look,
you could for 100 years you could have
lived a terrible life, but if you just
commit yourself to doing one good thing
before you die, that's going to redeem
you in the eyes of God.
So, there is always hope and salvation,
no matter who you are, no matter what
you've done.
Uh yes?
>> So, when you ask that question prior to
the reading of like
what
makes the same thing uh what makes the
same sin
differentiate from from hell and
purgatory?
This the Catholic Church would say
repent at your death.
And are you saying that Dante says that
works are are what can get you into
purgatory and not just uh it seems like
I could sin sin sin sin and then
sincerely repent at my death and make it
into purgatory would be the Catholic
Church's interpretation.
>> Right, the formula isn't that simple.
Um there are there are lots of like
conditions, okay? But the way to
understand this is
uh the conditions to get into purgatory
are a lot more flexible than the
conditions to get into hell. Does that
make sense? Right? If you do something
really really bad, like murder your
guest, that condemns you to hell
automatically.
But um the
criteria conditions for purgatory are
much more wide, much more flexible than
people um imagine. So, it's possible you
repent. It's possible you were uh
murdered accidental uh you you were
murdered and you didn't have time to
repent. It's possible that you did one
good work and that helped a lot of
people. Okay? So, do do do you
understand? There's a lot of different
things you can do to get into into
purgatory. And the reason why is once
you're once you're purgatory, you have
to show total commitment.
Okay?
All right. So, as the angel says, it's
easy to get in, but once you're in,
you're you're in, you have to work
really really hard.
Okay? If you really if you if you want
to commit yourself to working hard for
eternity, then you'll you come in, okay?
Because the thing about purgatory that's
very upsetting for a lot of people is
um it's a really long time.
Right? It could be 10,000 It could be 10
million years. Okay?
>> [laughter]
>> Um
And some people are like, "Screw that.
I'll I'll I'll I'll just spend my time
in hell. It sounds It sounds a lot
easier." Right?
Okay?
All right. Uh let's let's go to Canto
12.
>> [snorts]
>> Canto 12.
Oxen yoked proceeded abreast, so I moved
with the burden slow as long as my kind
pedagogue allowed me to. But when he
said, "Leave him behind and go ahead.
We're here it's fitting that with wings
and oars each urged his boat along with
all his force." I drew my body up again
erect, the stance most suitable to man,
and yet the thoughts I thought were
still submissive bent.
>> Okay, so during the um
um his time in the terrace of humility,
he lowered himself to um
develop humility, okay? Does that make
sense? Because remember, before he came
here it
he became really famous because of his
shadow, and he was proud, and to um
uh redeem himself, he held himself low,
okay?
All right, keep it going.
>> Um line 10. Now I was on my way, and
willingly I followed in my teacher's
steps, and we together showed what speed
we could command. He said to me, "Look
downward, for the way will offer you
some solace if you pay attention to the
pavement at your feet.
As on the lids of pavement tombs there
are stone effigies of what the buried
were before, so that the dead may be
remembered. And there, when memory,
inciting only the pious, has renewed
their mourning, men are often led to
shed their tears again. So did I see,
but carved more skillfully with greater
sense of likeness, effigies on all the
path protruding from the mountain. I saw
to one On of the path one who had been
created nobler than all other beings,
falling lightning-like from heaven.
I saw upon the other side Briareus
transfixed by the celestial shaft. He
lay ponderous on the cold and fatal
cold. I saw them Briareus, I saw Mars
and Pallas, still armed as they
surrounded Jove their father gazing upon
the giant's scattered limbs.
I saw bewildered Nimrod at the foot of
his labor great labor. Watching him were
those of Shinar who had shared his
arrogance. Oh Niobe, what tears
afflicted me when on that path I saw
your I saw your effigy among your
slaughtered children seven and seven. Oh
Saul, you were portrayed there as one
who had died on his own sword upon
Gilboa, which never after knew the rain,
the dew. Oh mad Arachne, I saw you
already half spider wretched on the
ragged remnants of work that you had
wrought to your own hurt.
Oh Rehoboam, you whose effigy seems not
to menace there, and yet you flee by
chariot terrified though none pursues.
It also showed that pavement of hard
stone how much Alcmaeon made his mother
pay the cost of the ill-omened ornament.
It showed the children of Sennacherib as
they sailed their father in the temple
then left him dead behind them as they
fled.
It showed the slaughter and the
devastation wrought by Tomyris when she
taunted Cyrus, "You thirsted after
blood, with blood I fill you." It showed
the rout of the Assyrians sent reeling
after Holofernes' death. It also showed
his body what was left. I saw Troy
turned to caverns and to ashes. Oh
Ilium, your effigy in stone. It showed
you there so squalid, so cast down. What
master of the brush or of the stylus had
there portrayed such masses, such
outlines as would astonish all
discerning minds? The dead seemed dead
and the alive alive. I saw had bent
trading those effigies as long as well
as those who'd seen those scenes
directly. Now sons of Eve persist in
arrogance and haughty stands do you let
your eyes bend lest you be forced to see
your evil path. We now had circled more
of the mountain and much more of the
sun's course have been crossed and I my
mind absorbed and gauged when he who
always looked ahead insistently as he
advanced to begin. Lift up your eyes,
it's time to set these images aside. See
there an angel hurrying to meet us and
also see the sixth of the handmaidens
returning from her service to the day.
Adorn your face and ask with reverence
that he be pleased to send us higher.
Remember today will never know another
dawn.
>> Okay, stop. Okay, all right. So, they
passed through the terrace
of um
pride to learn humility. Now they have
entered new terrace and of course
there's more artwork. And what is
Dante's emotional reaction to this
artwork?
What's he doing?
When he sees this artwork, what is his
response?
>> He seems quite shocked and sad.
>> What what what what's he doing
literally?
>> Remembering and reme- like
>> What what what what's the word? What
what's the what what what is his action?
He's sad. What what is his action?
What does the text say?
What's he literally doing right now?
As he's watching this artwork.
>> Looking down.
Looking at his feet.
>> No, what what what is he literally doing
right now?
What is he doing right now as he's
watching this artwork? As he's watching
this as he's looking at this artwork,
how is he feeling? What is he doing?
Yes?
>> I'd say grieving.
>> He's crying.
>> Yeah, grieving.
>> Right? It literally says he's crying,
okay? So, now I I want to talk about
tragedy, okay? Because like things he
saw, this artwork, they are tragic.
There's tragedy in everything that he's
seen, right?
So,
I want to discuss
tragedy
and why what crying does.
Okay? Now, think of a movie
uh you've seen that made you cry. Think
of Think about a theater
that made you cry. Think about an
artwork that made you cry, a song that
made you cry, okay? But just think of
something that made you cry.
All right? What does crying do?
Yeah, it's catharsis, right?
Okay? Catharsis.
Does anyone know what catharsis means?
What is catharsis?
>> Purifying through release.
Releasing your tears.
>> Yeah,
>> it's purging, you understand? Catharsis
literally means purging. Basically,
throw up and release
your emotions, okay? That's what crying
is. You're purging yourself.
Okay? So, why would that be
Why would that be
Why would that lead to virtue?
>> [snorts]
>> Yes?
>> I guess you can start to feel all over
your body the pain of an of other people
who have also felt tragedy.
>> Because like what leads to the crying is
the empathy, right?
That is what
leads to the crying because you see the
pain in others,
right? If you didn't see the pain in
others, you would be you would be
laughing like, "Haha, you know, he got
his top chopped head chopped off." Okay?
So, it's the empathy that allows you to
cry.
Okay?
And so, what is empathy?
Where does empathy come from?
>> I think imagination and emulation from
evolution, I think. So, it starts with
imagining the position of another person
or a situation and then trying to
feel that within yourself, but a lot of
the time it's more too complicated for
you to feel, so you just try and feel
the sadness that you can see another
person and it's to um
comfort people by showing that you
understand and that their pain is enough
to move you beyond your normal state.
>> So, are you saying that it is a
an adaptation of evolution?
>> Yes.
>> Okay. With then where where where is
empathy located in our brains then?
>> Um I think there are certain regions
that activate in a mother's brain when
her baby is crying and I think that
crying is like
>> Does Has anyone say psychology?
Where where where How do How do our
brains actually achieve empathy? Do you
guys know?
Or we can call it cortex. The cortex is
in
>> Okay, let's let's go Yes.
>> Let's leave it at term as mirror
neurons.
>> Yeah, let's Google mirror neurons, okay?
And and and like I I want to see if this
is actually true, okay? Do mirror mirror
Are mirror mirror neurons responsible
for empathy?
Okay, are they responsible for empathy?
>> Like
>> Uh yes.
>> I had sometimes problems growing up and
like I knew people that
um had problems like when sometimes I
see people crying
I would laugh because I didn't know how
to properly emulate it. Like there's an
interview with Messi where the
interviewer is so overwrought with
emotion at interviewing him because it's
his livestream and Messi just goes
starts laughing.
>> Okay.
>> Cuz
>> Right.
Uh yes.
>> So there's a psychological experiment
where they take a
a two-year-old um and they they
put
like a
I don't know, a ball in a drawer.
And then the parent comes in and the
parent doesn't know that the ball's in
the drawer or something like this.
Um
The way I'm screwing this up, but the
way that this works is like um if you're
under two years old then you can
empathize, oh my parent doesn't have
that information that the ball's in the
drawer. And if you're over two years
old, then you can say, oh my parent
doesn't know, I need to inform them. And
And so two-year-olds is when we get
empathy according to psychologists.
>> Okay, so at two years old is when we
develop the mirror neurons, right?
Okay.
All right. Um
I'm not convinced mirror mirror neurons
actually exist. It's a theory, but do we
have any concrete evidence evidence that
it it it actually exists?
What What does Google say?
Do mirror Do mirror mirror neurons
actually exist?
It's a theory, okay? We don't We don't
even know how this works.
What What Yes?
>> I am totally on your side. I believe
that empathy is is beyond one mind and
it's definitely a divine emotion.
>> Right.
Right. And so what would Donny say?
What is empathy?
But how do we connect to God?
>> Imagination.
>> Connect to God by connecting to others
among you, your peers, their pain.
>> But but what does that?
>> Love, compassion for another person.
>> Okay. So, um the idea is there's a
spark, right?
And so empathy how it works is the two
sparks the two sparks connect together.
Does that make sense?
Okay? So, that's why you cry because
when you see another spark in pain, your
spark also feels pain and you cry.
Okay?
So,
um
why would that lead to virtue?
Yes?
>> Because if you connect to another
person's pain and sorrow, then
um it makes you not want to commit that
same sin that could inflict pain on
other people. So, you want to be a
better person so that you don't cause
this kind of suffering in the world.
>> That's right. That's right.
That's right. So, that's the idea here
where if you where a tragedy is watched
by a group of people and the fact that
they cry together connects them
together. And that builds community.
Okay?
All right.
Okay.
So, let's
let's keep on going.
But but you can see how complex divine
comedy is, right? Because it's a
treatise on everything, philosophy,
religion, art, yes?
>> Yeah, it also kind of makes me think
about Lazarus' death and Jesus went and
cried at his funeral. So, I only if he
had told me, you know, I'll come
earlier, but Jesus cried a lot at the
funeral even though 10 minutes later he
resurrected Lazarus anyways. So, people
are like, "Well, what the heck with the
crying if you could just resurrect him?
What do you know? Are you pretending? Is
this theater, you know?" But Jesus kind
of explains, you know, that he needs to
sympathize with Mary and Magdalene on
the loss of Lazarus even though he's
going to resurrect him 10 minutes later.
>> Yes, because it's a human reaction,
right? It's something you you you can
control.
>> Yeah.
>> Right, exactly. Yes. Um
Let's keep on going.
>> Line 85. I was so used to his insistent
warnings against the loss of time
concerning that his words to me could
hardly be obscure. That handsome
creature came toward us. His clothes
were white and in his aspect he seemed
like the trembles trembling star that
rises in the morning.
He opened wide his arms and spread his
wings. He said, "Approach, the steps are
close at hand. From this point on one
can climb easily."
This invitation's answered by so few. Oh
humankind born for the upward flight,
why you driven back by wind so slight?
He led us to to a cleft within the rock
and then he struck my forehead with his
wing. That done, he promised me safe
journeying.
As on the right when one ascends the
hill where over
>> So so just to clarify, the angel strikes
Dante on the forehead to wipe him off a
P. You understand? So each time he
clears a terrace a P wiped off a peccata
sin is wiped off, okay?
Uh keep on going.
>> As on the right when one ascends the
hill where over Rubaconte's bridge there
stands the church that dominates the
well-ruled city. The daring slope of the
ascent is broken by steps that were
constructed in an age when record books
and measures could be trusted.
So was the slope that plummets there so
deeply down from the other ring made
easier, but on this side and that high
rock encroaches. While we began to move
in that direction, Beati pauperes
spiritu was sung. So sweetly it cannot
be told in words. How different were
these entryways from those of hell? For
here it is with song one enters, down
there it is with savage lamentation.
Now we ascended by the sacred stairs,
but I seemed to be much more light than
I had been before along the level
terrace.
At this I asked, "Master, tell me what
heavy weight has been lifted from me so
that I in going notice almost no
fatigue."
He answered, "When the P's that still
remain upon your brow, now almost all
our fate have been completely like this
P erased, your feet will be so mastered
by goodwill that they not only will not
feel travail, but will delight when
they're urged uphill."
>> Okay, so as more sins are purged from
your system, you will literally be
lighter, okay? You will feel lighter and
you'll be lighter, so you will move
faster. And keep on going.
>> Line 127, then I behaved like those who
made their way with something on their
head of which they're not aware till
other signs make them suspicious, at
which the hand helps them to ascertain.
It seeks and finds and touches and
provides the services that sight cannot
supply.
So with my right hand's outspread
fingers, I found just six of the letters
once inscribed by him who holds the keys
upon my forehead, and as he watched me
do this, my guide smiled.
>> Okay, canto 13 now.
>> We now had reached the summit of the
stairs where once again the mountain
whose ascent delivers man from sin has
been indented. There, just as in the
case of the first terrace, a second
terrace runs around the slope, except
that it describes a sharp or arc. No
effigy is there and no outline. The bank
is visible, the naked path, only the
livid color of raw rock. "If we wait
here in order to inquire of those who
pass," the poet said, "I fear our choice
of path may be delayed too long." And
then he fixed his eyes upon the sun,
letting his right side serve to guide
his movement. He wheeled his left around
and changed direction. "Oh gentle light,
through trust in which I enter on this
new path. May you conduct us here," he
said, "for men need guidance in this
place. You warm the world and you
illuminate. Unless a higher power urges
elsewhere, your rays must always be the
guides that lead." We had already
journeyed there as far as we should
reckon here to be a mile and done it in
brief time. Our will was eager when we
heard spirits as they flew toward us,
though they could not be
They could not be seen. Spirits
pronouncing courteous invitations to
love's table.
The first voice that flew by called out
aloud, "Vinum non habent." And behind us
that same voice reiterated its example.
And as that voice drew farther off
before it faded finally, another cried,
"I am Orestes." It too did not stop.
"What voices are these, Father?" were my
words. And as I asked him this, I heard
a third voice saying, "Love those by
whom you have been hurt."
And my good master said,
"The sin of envy is scourged within this
circle. Thus the cords that form the
scourging lash are plied by love. The
sounds of punished envy, envy curbed,
are different. If I judge right, you'll
hear these those sounds before we reach
the pass of pardon."
"But let your eyes be fixed attentively
and through the air you'll see people
seated before us, all of them on the
stone terrace." I opened wider than
before my eyes. I looked ahead of me and
I saw shades with clothes that shared
their color with the rocks. And once
we'd moved a little farther on, I heard
the cry of "Mary, pray for us." And then
heard Michael, Peter, and all saints. I
think no man now walks upon the earth
who is so hard that he would not have
been pierced by compassion by what I saw
next.
For when I had drawn close enough to see
clearly the way they paid their penalty,
the force of grief pressed tears out of
my eyes.
These souls, it seemed, were cloaked in
coarse haircloth and on their shoulders
served each shade as prop, and all of
them were bolstered by the rocks. So, do
the blind who have to beg appear on
pardon days to plead for what they need,
each bending his head back and toward
the other.
That who that all who watch feel quickly
pity's touch, not only through the words
that would entreat, but through the
sight which can no less beseech. And
just as to the blindness sun appears, so
to the shades of whom I now speak here
the light of heaven would not give
itself.
For iron wire pierces and sews up the
lids of all those shades as untamed
hawks are handled lest to unrest,
lest to restless they fly off.
It seemed to me a gross discourtesy for
me going to see and not be seen.
Therefore, I turned to my wise
counselor,
knew quite well what I, though mute, had
meant. And thus he did not wait for my
request, but said, "Speak, and be brief
and to the point."
Virgil was to my right along the outside
near the terrace edge. No parapet was
there to keep a man from falling off.
And to my other side were the devout
devout shades. Through their eyes sewn
so atrociously, those spirits forced the
tears that bathed their cheeks. I turned
to them, "And you who can be certain," I
then began, "of seeing that highlight
which is the only object of your
longing, may in your conscious all
impurity soon be dissolved by grace, so
that the stream of memory flow through
it limpidly.
Tell me, for I shall welcome such dear
words, if any soul among you is Italian,
if I know that, then I perhaps can help
him."
"My brother, each of us is citizen of
one true city. What you meant to say was
one who lived in Italy as pilgrim."
My hearing placed the point from which
this answer had come somewhat ahead of
me. Therefore, I made myself heard
farther on moving.
I saw one shade among the rest who
looked expectant, and if any should ask
how, its chin was lifted as a blind man
is.
"Spirit," I said, "who have subdued
yourself that you may climb, if it is
you who answered, then let me know by
your place or name. Know you by your
place or name."
"I was a Sienese," she answered, "and
with others here I mend my wicked life,
weeping to him that he grant us himself.
I was not Sapient, though I was called
Sapia, and I rejoiced far more at
others' hurts than my own good fortune.
And lest you should think I have
deceived you, hear and judge if I was
not and I have as I have told you, mad
when my years' arc had reached its
downward part, my fellow citizens were
close to Colle, where they joined battle
with their enemies, and I prayed God for
that which he had willed.
Thereat they were routed, beaten. They
were reeling along the bitter path of
flight, and seeing that chase, I felt
incomparable joy, so that I lifted my
daring face and cried to God, "Now I
fear you no more." So did the blackbird
after brief fair weather.
I looked for peace with God at life's
end. The penalty I owe for sin would not
be lessened now if my penitence had not
one who was sorrowing for me because of
charity in him.
Pia
remembered me in his devout petitions.
But who are you who question our
condition as you move on, whose eyes, if
I judge right, have not been sewn, who
uses breath to speak?
"My eyes," I said, "will be denied me
here, but only briefly. The offensive
envy was not committed often by their
gaze. I fear much more the punishment
below. My soul is anxious and suspense.
Already I feel the heavy weights of the
first terrace."
And she, "Who then let you up here among
us, if you believe you will return
below?" And I, "He who is with me and is
silent. I'm alive and therefore chosen
spirit, if you would have me move my
mortal steps on your behalf, beyond ask
me for that. Oh, this, she answered, is
so strange a thing to hear. The sign is
clear, you have God's love. Thus help me
sometimes with your prayers. I ask if
you by that which you desire most, if
you should ever tread the Tuscan Earth
to see my name restored among my kin.
You'll see them among those vain ones
who have put their trust in Telamon.
Their loss and hope will be more than
Diana cost, but there the Admirals will
lose the most.
>> Okay, so why is it that in the Terrace
of Envy, their punishment is their eyes
are shut, sewn shut?
Or why would that be the case?
>> So they don't constantly look at others
and compare themselves to others.
>> Right.
Yes.
Um
And so so and so once their eyes are are
shut, are sewn shut, what effect does it
have in them? Yes?
>> self, and you work on yourself, you're
no longer comparing yourself to others,
and you work on yourself to make
yourself better.
>> That's right.
>> And not because I want to be better than
the other guy next to me.
>> That's right, exactly, okay?
All right, um
And how would it be different in hell?
What what would the punishment in hell
be?
>> You have to keep looking at others.
>> Okay.
And why would that be
punishing?
>> Because
you have Well, well
because in hell you're not really
reflecting, so you still don't look at
yourself and try to better yourself, but
you feel more jealousy to other people.
>> You're forced to look at other people.
I I'm trying to figure out how visually
that works, right?
Yes?
>> I think in hell it would just like in
the pride be a mindset difference. So in
hell everyone believe that everybody
else could see.
And they were lying to them and somehow
they were the ones that couldn't see and
that would be the ultimate envy. Because
they would never be able to check.
>> have the same punishment guys, okay? But
as you point out, the attitude would be
different, right? Where if you're not if
you're not
if you can't see another person, it
drives you insane. It makes you believe
that that person is able to see I can't
see.
Do you understand the logic here, right?
Here, because these people will have
growth mindset, because they are on the
path to redemption, they recognize that
I should take the time to focus inward.
But in hell, they'll be like
they they're still stuck
focusing on other people. If you can't
they can't they can't look can't look at
other people, it drives them insane
because they have to imagine that their
lives are so much better than my life,
right?
Does that make sense?
>> hell in a way.
>> ultimate hell, right? Okay?
So it's really interesting to think
about, but yeah, the punishments would
be the same, but the way that the person
be reacts to the punishment would be
completely different.
Okay?
All right. Uh let's go on to 14, please.
>> Canto 14.
Who is this man who, although death has
yet to grant him flight, can circle
round our mountain and can at will open
and shut his eyes?
I don't know who he is, but I do know
he's not alone. You're closer. Question
him and greet him gently so that he
replies. So were two spirits leaning
toward each other discussing me along my
right hand side. Then they bent back
their heads to speak to me and one
began, "O soul, who is still enclosed
within the body, make your way toward
heaven. May you through love console us.
Tell us who you are, from where you
come. The grace that you've received, a
thing that's never come to pass before,
has caused us much astonishment."
And I, "Through central Tuscany there
spreads a little stream first born in
Feltro now. 100 miles can't fill the
course it needs. I bring this body from
that river's banks to tell you who I am
with me to speak in vain. My name has
not yet gained much fame." "If with my
understanding I have seized your meaning
properly," replied to me the one who'd
spoken first, "You mean the Arno?" The
other said to him, "Why did he hide that
river's name even as one would do in
hiding something horrible from view?"
The shade to him this question was
addressed replied with this, "I do not
know, but it is right for such a
valley's name to perish. For from its
source, at which the rugged chain, from
which Pelorus were cut off, surpasses
most other places with its massive
mountains, until its end point where it
offers back those waters that
evaporating skies drew from the sea that
streams may be supplied.
Virtue is seen as serpent, and all flee
from it as if it were an enemy, either
because the site is ill starred or their
evil custom goes them so.
Therefore, the nature of that squalid
valley's people has changed as if they
were inserted this pasture. That river
starts with miserable course among foul
hogs, more fit for a corn stone food
device to serve the needs of man.
Then, as that stream descends, it comes
on curves that, though their force is
feeble, snap and snarl, snarl, scornful
of them, it swerves its snout away, and
downward it flows on. And when that
ditch ill-fated and accursed grows
wider, it finds more and more the dogs
becoming wolves. Descending then through
many dark ravines, it comes on foxes so
full of deceit. There's no trap that
they cannot defeat. Nor will I keep from
speech because my comrade hears me, and
it will serve you too to keep in mind
what prophecy reveals to me.
I see your grandson. He's become a
hunter of wolves along the bank of the
Fierce River, and he strikes every one
of them with terror.
He sells their flesh while they're still
alive. Then, like an ancient beast, he
turns to slaughter, depriving many of
life himself of honor.
Bloody he comes out from the wood he's
plundered, leaving it such that in a
thousand years it will not be the forest
that it was that it was.
Just as the face of one who has heard
word of pain and injury becomes
perturbed, no matter from what side that
menace stirs, so did I see that other
soul who turned to listen, growing
anxious and dejected when he had taken
in his comrade's words.
The speech of one, the aspect of the
other had made me need to know their
names, and I both queried and beseeched
at the same time at which the spirit who
had spoken first to me began again.
You'd have me do for you that which to
me you have refused, but since God would
and you have his grace glow so brightly,
I shall not be miserly. Know therefore
that I was Guido del Duca.
My blood was so afire with envy that
when I had seen a man becoming happy,
the lividness in me was plain to see.
From what I've sown, this is the straw I
reap. O humankind, why do you set your
hearts there when our sharing cannot
have a part? This is Rinieri, this is he
the glory, the honor of the house of
Calboli. But no one hasn't inherited his
worth. It's not his kennel between the
Po and the mountains and the Reno and
the coast who have lost the truth's
grave good and lost the good of gentle
living, too. Those lands are full of
poisoned stumps by now, however much one
were to cultivate. It is too late.
Where's good Lizio, Arrigo Manardi, Pier
Traversaro, Guido de Campinia, or
Ramanoli's return to bastardy. When will
a Fabbro flourish in Bologna? When in
Faenza a Bernardin de Fosco, the noble
offshoot of a humble plant? Don't wonder
Tuscan if I weep when I remember Ugolino
d'Azzo, one who lived among us, and
Guido de Popprat
Guido de Pratt of the house of
Traversara of Anastagi, both houses
without heirs, and Federigo Tignoso and
his gracious company.
The ladies and the knights, labors and
leisure to which we once were urged by
courtesy and love, where hearts now host
perversity.
>> Okay, sorry. Um we'll stop. We'll go
Please we're out of time. But I But I
But what I'll ask you one more question
and then uh we'll end today.
What What does it mean to say to say,
"Why do you set your hearts there where
our sharing cannot have a part?"
So we interpret what this means and then
and then we'll we'll end the the
session. Yes.
>> Humans are obsessed with zero-sum games.
>> Exactly.
Okay? But But explain to everyone else
what that's what this means.
>> So it means your actions if if you uh
operating in a sphere where there is a
limited amount of resources
there has to be winners and losers.
>> Yes.
>> And there cannot be anything else.
>> And people really like this because you
feel like your actions are meaningful
and every gain feels like it matters so
much more because you really know it's
not that you're constantly thinking
about the loss of another person, but
you are aware of it and you know that
everything you gain is something that
someone else had to lose.
>> Exactly. Yeah, so So what this saying is
we're materialistic and all we care
about is material accumulation
and so it becomes a zero-sum game,
right? Because if I have this, you can't
have that.
Right?
Um
so
what is the solution then?
How How do we get out of this zero-sum
game?
Is there a solution?
Yes?
>> Quality so that you can have a win-win
situation.
>> is a win-win situation?
>> Try to co-create something instead
making the cake bigger instead of just
cutting of the cake.
>> What is a win-win scenario for humanity?
Yes?
>> The solution um
to which we once were urged by courtesy
and love where hearts and hosts
perversity so
love I would say.
>> Yeah.
>> But but but but what what's What does it
mean in practice?
>> Mhm. Well, instead of trying to
wear down others, you help them and you
have empathy for them and instead of
trying to gain everything for yourself,
you
try to
have like
Yeah.
>> Okay. So So, be generous, right? Right?
If you need help, I'll help you.
And then what are you going to do?
You'll help others and then they'll help
others as well, right? So, rather than a
zero-sum game where there's only finite
resources, generosity creates infinite
love.
Okay? Does that make sense?
All right. Okay.
Um we'll we'll end
uh here and then we'll we'll start with
Canto 15 tomorrow
and we'll try to do at least 10
possibly more than that and that'll give
us room and space for the final day to
talk more in depth about um Dante and
how he sees our world, okay? Um
also I want at the last day to give
people an opportunity to talk about your
personal experience with Dante. I think
that's very, very important, okay? So,
uh if possible for next 2 days, think
about what it's been like to read Dante
and how you as a person have changed.
And also think about where you think
in the future you'll go from here, okay?
Has this been a life-transforming
experience for you? Has it changed the
trajectory of your life? And it you
know, it There's no There's no right or
wrong. You don't have to You don't have
to answer, but I think that everyone
would appreciate it if you could share
your emotional journey with Dante. And
because we have such a diverse crowd of
people, I think everyone's journey will
be different, okay? So, I think we will
all appreciate that. But any questions
before we can we conclude today?
Okay, great. So, I will see uh yes, one
one one question, yes.
>> So, I noticed that it took
nine cantos for Dante to reach the gate
of Purgatory, but it only took three
cantos to reach the gate of hell. So, I
wonder why
it's different.
>> Um do you Do you have a theory?
Uh yes.
>> I've thought about this. I think there's
more
There's more sins that aren't
like all that the betrayal of uh
against country and family and stuff
like this that don't end up in
Purgatory.
>> Okay.
Uh yes, so
at what canto do they enter this?
But you you can actually check it.
What kind of do you What kind of inferno
do you think they start to enter disc?
Excuse me?
We'll We'll We'll check this, okay? Can
Can you go to Inferno 9
and see what happens in Inferno 9 or
Inferno 10, I think.
I can't remember which it is, okay?
Let's figure out where where they are in
Inferno 9 first.
Okay.
So, Inferno 9, they're outside the gates
of Dis. Inferno 10 is when they enter
Dis. So, it's the same thing, do you
understand? Because in Inferno, there's
one additional canto for the
introduction. So, all three are are 33
cantos.
And so, what's happening is
Dis is where Hell proper is.
And then, the other circles, they're
kind of like
not that serious.
Do you understand? And any part And like
before they enter Purgatory, they have
to go through Ante-Purgatory.
Okay? So, it's so so so symmetrical.
Okay. All right. Thanks for the
question, okay? I'll see you all
tomorrow, okay?